12 The Mark and the Region

Emacs, like many other applications, lets you select some arbitrary part of the buffer text and invoke commands that operate on such selected text. In Emacs, we call the selected text the region; its handling is very similar to that of selected text in other programs, but there are also important differences.

The region is the portion of the buffer between the mark and the current point. You define a region by setting the mark somewhere (with, for instance, the C-SPC command), and then moving point to where you want the region to end. (Or you can use the mouse to define a region.)

The region always extends between point and the mark, no matter which of them comes earlier in the text; each time you move point, the region changes.

Setting the mark at a position in the text activates it. When the mark is active, we say also that the region is active; Emacs indicates its extent by highlighting the text within it, using the region face (see Customizing Faces).

After certain non-motion commands, including any command that changes the text in the buffer, Emacs automatically deactivates the mark; this turns off the highlighting. You can also explicitly deactivate the mark at any time, by typing C-g (see Quitting and Aborting).

Many commands limit the text on which they operate to the active region. For instance, the M-% command (which replaces matching text) normally works on the entire accessible portion of the buffer, but if you have an active region, it’ll work only on that region instead.

The mark is useful even if it is not active. For example, you can move to previous mark locations using the mark ring. See The Mark Ring. Additionally, some commands will have an effect even on an inactive region (for example upcase-region). You can also reactivate the region with commands like C-x C-x.

The above behavior, which is the default in interactive sessions, is known as Transient Mark mode. Disabling Transient Mark mode switches Emacs to an alternative behavior, in which the region is usually not highlighted. See Disabling Transient Mark Mode.

Setting the mark in one buffer has no effect on the marks in other buffers. When you return to a buffer with an active mark, the mark is at the same place as before. When multiple windows show the same buffer, they can have different values of point, and thus different regions, but they all share one common mark position. See Multiple Windows. Ordinarily, only the selected window highlights its region; however, if the variable highlight-nonselected-windows is non-nil, each window highlights its own region.

There is another kind of region: the rectangular region. See Rectangles.

12.1 Setting the Mark

Here are some commands for setting the mark:

C-SPC

Set the mark at point, and activate it (set-mark-command).

C-@

The same.

C-x C-x

Set the mark at point, and activate it; then move point where the mark used to be (exchange-point-and-mark).

Drag-mouse-1

Set point and the mark around the text you drag across.

mouse-3

Set the mark at point, then move point to where you click (mouse-save-then-kill).

Shifted cursor motion keys

Set the mark at point if the mark is inactive, then move point. See Shift Selection.

The most common way to set the mark is with C-SPC (set-mark-command)^4. This sets the mark where point is, and activates it. You can then move point away, leaving the mark behind.

For example, suppose you wish to convert part of the buffer to upper case. To accomplish this, go to one end of the desired text, type C-SPC, and move point until the desired portion of text is highlighted. Now type C-x C-u (upcase-region). This converts the text in the region to upper case, and then deactivates the mark.

Whenever the mark is active, you can deactivate it by typing C-g (see Quitting and Aborting). Most commands that operate on the region also automatically deactivate the mark, like C-x C-u in the above example.

Instead of setting the mark in order to operate on a region, you can also use it to remember a position in the buffer (by typing C-SPC C-SPC), and later jump back there (by typing C-u C-SPC). See The Mark Ring, for details.

The command C-x C-x (exchange-point-and-mark) exchanges the positions of point and the mark. C-x C-x is useful when you are satisfied with the position of point but want to move the other end of the region (where the mark is). Using C-x C-x a second time, if necessary, puts the mark at the new position with point back at its original position. Normally, if the mark is inactive, this command first reactivates the mark wherever it was last set, to ensure that the region is left highlighted. However, if you call it with a prefix argument, it leaves the mark inactive and the region unhighlighted; you can use this to jump to the mark in a manner similar to C-u C-SPC.

You can also set the mark with the mouse. If you press the left mouse button (down-mouse-1) and drag the mouse across a range of text, this sets the mark where you first pressed the mouse button and puts point where you release it. Alternatively, clicking the right mouse button (mouse-3) sets the mark at point and then moves point to where you clicked. See Mouse Commands for Editing, for a more detailed description of these mouse commands.

Finally, you can set the mark by holding down the shift key while typing certain cursor motion commands (such as S-RIGHT, S-C-f, S-C-n, etc.). This is called shift-selection. It sets the mark at point before moving point, but only if there is no active mark set via a previous shift-selection or mouse commands. The mark set by mouse commands and by shift-selection behaves slightly differently from the usual mark: any subsequent unshifted cursor motion command deactivates it automatically. For details, see Shift Selection.

Many commands that insert text, such as C-y (yank), set the mark at the other end of the inserted text, without activating it. This lets you easily return to that position (see The Mark Ring). You can tell that a command does this when it shows ‘Mark set’ in the echo area.

Under X, every time the active region changes, Emacs saves the text in the region to the primary selection. This lets you insert that text into other X applications with mouse-2 clicks. See Cut and Paste with Other Window Applications.

12.2 Commands to Mark Textual Objects

Here are commands for placing point and the mark around a textual object such as a word, list, paragraph or page:

M-@

Set mark at the end of the next word (mark-word). This does not move point.

C-M-@

Set mark after end of following balanced expression (mark-sexp). This does not move point.

M-h

Move point to the beginning of the current paragraph, and set mark at the end (mark-paragraph).

C-M-h

Move point to the beginning of the current defun, and set mark at the end (mark-defun).

C-x C-p

Move point to the beginning of the current page, and set mark at the end (mark-page).

C-x h

Move point to the beginning of the buffer, and set mark at the end (mark-whole-buffer).

M-@ (mark-word) sets the mark at the end of the next word (see Words, for information about words). Repeated invocations of this command extend the region by advancing the mark one word at a time. As an exception, if the mark is active and located before point, M-@ moves the mark backwards from its current position one word at a time.

This command also accepts a numeric argument n, which tells it to advance the mark by n words. A negative argument −n moves the mark back by n words.

Similarly, C-M-@ (mark-sexp) puts the mark at the end of the next balanced expression (see Expressions with Balanced Parentheses). Repeated invocations extend the region to subsequent expressions, while positive or negative numeric arguments move the mark forward or backward by the specified number of expressions.

The other commands in the above list set both point and mark, so as to delimit an object in the buffer. M-h (mark-paragraph) marks paragraphs (see Paragraphs), C-M-h (mark-defun) marks top-level definitions (see Moving by Defuns), and C-x C-p (mark-page) marks pages (see Pages). Repeated invocations again play the same role, extending the region to consecutive objects; similarly, numeric arguments specify how many objects to move the mark by.

C-x h (mark-whole-buffer) sets up the entire buffer as the region, by putting point at the beginning and the mark at the end.

12.3 Operating on the Region

Once you have a region, here are some of the ways you can operate on it:

Kill it with C-w (see Killing and Moving Text).
Copy it to the kill ring with M-w (see Yanking).
Convert case with C-x C-l or C-x C-u (see Case Conversion Commands).
Undo changes within it using C-u C-/ (see Undo).
Replace text within it using M-% (see Query Replace).
Indent it with C-x TAB or C-M-\ (see Indentation).
Fill it as text with M-x fill-region (see Filling Text).
Check the spelling of words within it with M-$ (see Checking and Correcting Spelling).
Evaluate it as Lisp code with M-x eval-region (see Evaluating Emacs Lisp Expressions).
Save it in a register with C-x r s (see Registers).
Save it in a buffer or a file (see Accumulating Text).

Some commands have a default behavior when the mark is inactive, but operate on the region if the mark is active. For example, M-$ (ispell-word) normally checks the spelling of the word at point, but it checks the text in the region if the mark is active (see Checking and Correcting Spelling). Normally, such commands use their default behavior if the region is empty (i.e., if mark and point are at the same position). If you want them to operate on the empty region, change the variable use-empty-active-region to t.

As described in Erasing Text, the DEL (backward-delete-char) and Delete (delete-forward-char) commands also act this way. If the mark is active, they delete the text in the region. (As an exception, if you supply a numeric argument n, where n is not one, these commands delete n characters regardless of whether the mark is active). If you change the variable delete-active-region to nil, then these commands don’t act differently when the mark is active. If you change the value to kill, these commands kill the region instead of deleting it (see Killing and Moving Text).

Other commands always operate on the region, and have no default behavior. Such commands usually have the word region in their names, like C-w (kill-region) and C-x C-u (upcase-region). If the mark is inactive, they operate on the inactive region—that is, on the text between point and the position at which the mark was last set (see The Mark Ring). To disable this behavior, change the variable mark-even-if-inactive to nil. Then these commands will instead signal an error if the mark is inactive.

By default, text insertion occurs normally even if the mark is active—for example, typing a inserts the character ‘a’, then deactivates the mark. Delete Selection mode, a minor mode, modifies this behavior: if you enable that mode, then inserting text while the mark is active causes the text in the region to be deleted first. However, you can tune this behavior by customizing the delete-selection-temporary-region option. Its default value is nil, but you can set it to t, in which case only temporarily-active regions will be replaced: those which are set by dragging the mouse (see Setting the Mark) or by shift-selection (see Shift Selection), as well as by C-u C-x C-x when Transient Mark Mode is disabled. You can further tune the behavior by setting delete-selection-temporary-region to selection: then temporary regions by C-u C-x C-x won’t be replaced, only the ones activated by dragging the mouse or shift-selection. To toggle Delete Selection mode on or off, type M-x delete-selection-mode.

12.4 The Mark Ring

Each buffer remembers previous locations of the mark, in the mark ring. Commands that set the mark also push the old mark onto this ring. One of the uses of the mark ring is to remember spots that you may want to go back to.

C-SPC C-SPC

Set the mark, pushing it onto the mark ring, without activating it.

C-u C-SPC

Move point to where the mark was, and restore the mark from the ring of former marks.

The command C-SPC C-SPC is handy when you want to use the mark to remember a position to which you may wish to return. It pushes the current point onto the mark ring, without activating the mark (which would cause Emacs to highlight the region). This is actually two consecutive invocations of C-SPC (set-mark-command); the first C-SPC sets the mark, and the second C-SPC deactivates it. (When Transient Mark mode is off, C-SPC C-SPC instead activates Transient Mark mode temporarily; see Disabling Transient Mark Mode.)

To return to a marked position, use set-mark-command with a prefix argument: C-u C-SPC. This moves point to where the mark was, and deactivates the mark if it was active. Each subsequent C-u C-SPC jumps to a prior position stored in the mark ring. The positions you move through in this way are not lost; they go to the end of the ring.

If you set set-mark-command-repeat-pop to non-nil, then immediately after you type C-u C-SPC, you can type C-SPC instead of C-u C-SPC to cycle through the mark ring. By default, set-mark-command-repeat-pop is nil.

Each buffer has its own mark ring. All editing commands use the current buffer’s mark ring. In particular, C-u C-SPC always stays in the same buffer.

The variable mark-ring-max specifies the maximum number of entries to keep in the mark ring. This defaults to 16 entries. If that many entries exist and another one is pushed, the earliest one in the list is discarded. Repeating C-u C-SPC cycles through the positions currently in the ring.

If you want to move back to the same place over and over, the mark ring may not be convenient enough. If so, you can record the position in a register for later retrieval (see Saving Positions in Registers).

12.5 The Global Mark Ring

In addition to the ordinary mark ring that belongs to each buffer, Emacs has a single global mark ring. Each time you set a mark, this is recorded in the global mark ring in addition to the current buffer’s own mark ring, if you have switched buffers since the previous mark setting. Hence, the global mark ring records a sequence of buffers that you have been in, and, for each buffer, a place where you set the mark. The length of the global mark ring is controlled by global-mark-ring-max, and is 16 by default.

The command C-x C-SPC (pop-global-mark) jumps to the buffer and position of the latest entry in the global ring. It also rotates the ring, so that successive uses of C-x C-SPC take you to earlier buffers and mark positions.

12.6 Shift Selection

If you hold down the shift key while typing a cursor motion command, this sets the mark before moving point, so that the region extends from the original position of point to its new position. This feature is referred to as shift-selection. It is similar to the way text is selected in other editors.

The mark set via shift-selection behaves a little differently from what we have described above. Firstly, in addition to the usual ways of deactivating the mark (such as changing the buffer text or typing C-g), the mark is deactivated by any unshifted cursor motion command. Secondly, any subsequent shifted cursor motion command avoids setting the mark anew. Therefore, a series of shifted cursor motion commands will continuously adjust the region.

Shift-selection only works if the shifted cursor motion key is not already bound to a separate command (see Customization). For example, if you bind S-C-f to another command, typing S-C-f runs that command instead of performing a shift-selected version of C-f (forward-char).

A mark set via mouse commands behaves the same as a mark set via shift-selection (see Setting the Mark). For example, if you specify a region by dragging the mouse, you can continue to extend the region using shifted cursor motion commands. In either case, any unshifted cursor motion command deactivates the mark.

To turn off shift-selection, set shift-select-mode to nil. Doing so does not disable setting the mark via mouse commands. If you set shift-select-mode to the value permanent, cursor motion keys that were not shift-translated will not deactivate the mark, so, for example, the region set by prior commands can be extended by shift-selection, and unshifted cursor motion keys will extend the region set by shift-selection.

12.7 Disabling Transient Mark Mode

The default behavior of the mark and region, in which setting the mark activates it and highlights the region, is called Transient Mark mode. This is a minor mode that is enabled by default in interactive sessions. It can be toggled with M-x transient-mark-mode, or with the ‘Highlight Active Region’ menu item in the ‘Options’ menu. Turning it off switches Emacs to an alternative mode of operation:

Setting the mark, with commands like C-SPC or C-x C-x, does not highlight the region. Therefore, you can’t tell by looking where the mark is located; you have to remember.

The usual solution to this problem is to set the mark and then use it soon, before you forget where it is. You can also check where the mark is by using C-x C-x, which exchanges the positions of the point and the mark (see Setting the Mark).

Some commands, which ordinarily act on the region when the mark is active, no longer do so. For example, normally M-% (query-replace) performs replacements within the region, if the mark is active. When Transient Mark mode is off, it always operates from point to the end of the buffer. Commands that act this way are identified in their own documentation.

While Transient Mark mode is off, you can activate it temporarily using C-SPC C-SPC or C-u C-x C-x.

C-SPC C-SPC

Set the mark at point (like plain C-SPC) and enable Transient Mark mode just once, until the mark is deactivated. (This is not really a separate command; you are using the C-SPC command twice.)

C-u C-x C-x

Exchange point and mark, activate the mark and enable Transient Mark mode temporarily, until the mark is next deactivated. (This is the C-x C-x command, exchange-point-and-mark, with a prefix argument.)

These commands set or activate the mark, and enable Transient Mark mode only until the mark is deactivated. One reason you may want to use them is that some commands operate on the entire buffer instead of the region when Transient Mark mode is off. Enabling Transient Mark mode momentarily gives you a way to use these commands on the region.

When you specify a region with the mouse (see Setting the Mark), or with shift-selection (see Shift Selection), this likewise activates Transient Mark mode temporarily and highlights the region.

Footnotes

(4)

There is no C-SPC character in ASCII; usually, typing C-SPC on a text terminal gives the character C-@. This key is also bound to set-mark-command, so unless you are unlucky enough to have a text terminal that behaves differently, you might as well think of C-@ as C-SPC.

Appendix H Emacs and Microsoft Windows/MS-DOS

This section describes peculiarities of using Emacs on Microsoft Windows. Some of these peculiarities are also relevant to Microsoft’s older MS-DOS operating system. However, Emacs features that are relevant only to MS-DOS are described in a separate section (see Emacs and MS-DOS).

MS-Windows is a non-free operating system; that means it denies its users the freedom that every computer user deserves. That is an injustice. For your freedom’s sake, we urge you to switch to a free operating system.

We support GNU Emacs on proprietary operating systems because we hope this taste of freedom will inspire users to escape from them.

The behavior of Emacs on MS-Windows is reasonably similar to what is documented in the rest of the manual, including support for long file names, multiple frames, scroll bars, mouse menus, and subprocesses. However, a few special considerations apply, and they are described here.

H.1 How to Start Emacs on MS-Windows

There are several ways of starting Emacs on MS-Windows:

From the desktop shortcut icon: either double-click the left mouse button on the icon, or click once, then press RET. The desktop shortcut should specify as its “Target” (in the “Properties” of the shortcut) the full absolute file name of runemacs.exe, not of emacs.exe. This is because runemacs.exe hides the console window that would have been created if the target of the shortcut were emacs.exe (which is a console program, as far as Windows is concerned). If you use this method, Emacs starts in the directory specified by the shortcut. To control where that is, right-click on the shortcut, select “Properties”, and in the “Shortcut” tab modify the “Start in” field to your liking.
From a task-bar shortcut icon, by clicking once the left mouse button. Windows versions since Vista allow you to create such shortcuts by pinning the icon of a running program that appears in the task bar. You can do that with Emacs, but afterwards you will have to change the properties of the pinned shortcut to run runemacs.exe, not of emacs.exe. You can also pin Emacs to the task bar by clicking the right mouse button on its icon in the Start menu, then selecting ‘Pin to taskbar’. Once again, be sure to specify runemacs.exe as the program to run. You can control where Emacs starts by setting the “Start in” field of the shortcut’s Properties.
From the Command Prompt window, by typing emacs RET at the prompt. The Command Prompt window where you did that will not be available for invoking other commands until Emacs exits. In this case, Emacs will start in the current directory of the Windows shell.
From the Command Prompt window, by typing runemacs RET at the prompt. The Command Prompt window where you did that will be immediately available for invoking other commands. In this case, Emacs will start in the current directory of the Windows shell.
From the Windows Run dialog (normally reached by clicking the Start button). Typing runemacs RET into the dialog will start Emacs in the parent directory of the Windows equivalent of your user’s HOME directory, see HOME and Startup Directories on MS-Windows.
Via emacsclient.exe or emacsclientw.exe, which allow you to invoke Emacs from other programs, and to reuse a running Emacs process for serving editing jobs required by other programs. See Using Emacs as a Server. The difference between emacsclient.exe and emacsclientw.exe is that the former is a console program, while the latter is a Windows GUI program. Both programs wait for Emacs to signal that the editing job is finished, before they exit and return control to the program that invoked them. Which one of them to use in each case depends on the expectations of the program that needs editing services. If that program is itself a console (text-mode) program, you should use emacsclient.exe, so that any of its messages and prompts appear in the same command window as those of the invoking program. By contrast, if the invoking program is a GUI program, you will be better off using emacsclientw.exe, because emacsclient.exe will pop up a command window if it is invoked from a GUI program. A notable situation where you would want emacsclientw.exe is when you right-click on a file in the Windows Explorer and select “Open With” from the pop-up menu. Use the ‘--alternate-editor=’ or ‘-a’ options if Emacs might not be running (or not running as a server) when emacsclient is invoked—that will always give you an editor. When invoked via emacsclient, Emacs will start in the current directory of the program that invoked emacsclient.

Note that, due to limitations of MS-Windows, Emacs cannot have both GUI and text-mode frames in the same session. It also cannot open text-mode frames on more than a single Command Prompt window, because each Windows program can have only one console at any given time. For these reasons, if you invoke emacsclient with the -c option, and the Emacs server runs in a text-mode session, Emacs will always create a new text-mode frame in the same Command Prompt window where it was started; a GUI frame will be created only if the server runs in a GUI session. Similarly, if you invoke emacsclient with the -t option, Emacs will create a GUI frame if the server runs in a GUI session, or a text-mode frame when the session runs in text mode in a Command Prompt window. See emacsclient Options.

H.2 Text Files and Binary Files

GNU Emacs uses newline characters to separate text lines. This is the convention used on GNU, Unix, and other POSIX-compliant systems.

By contrast, MS-DOS and MS-Windows normally use carriage return followed by linefeed, a two-character sequence, to separate text lines. (Linefeed is the same character as newline.) Therefore, convenient editing of typical files with Emacs requires conversion of these end-of-line (EOL) sequences. And that is what Emacs normally does: it converts carriage return followed by linefeed into newline when reading files, and converts newline into carriage return followed by linefeed when writing files. The same mechanism that handles conversion of international character codes does this conversion also (see Coding Systems).

One consequence of this special format-conversion of most files is that character positions as reported by Emacs (see Cursor Position Information) do not agree with the file size information known to the operating system.

In addition, if Emacs recognizes from a file’s contents that it uses newline rather than carriage return followed by linefeed as its line separator, it does not perform EOL conversion when reading or writing that file. Thus, you can read and edit files from GNU and Unix systems on MS-DOS with no special effort, and they will retain their Unix-style end-of-line convention after you edit them.

The mode line indicates whether end-of-line translation was used for the current buffer. If MS-DOS end-of-line translation is in use for the buffer, the MS-Windows build of Emacs displays a backslash ‘\’ after the coding system mnemonic near the beginning of the mode line (see The Mode Line). If no EOL translation was performed, the string ‘(Unix)’ is displayed instead of the backslash, to alert you that the file’s EOL format is not the usual carriage return followed by linefeed.

To visit a file and specify whether it uses DOS-style or Unix-style end-of-line, specify a coding system (see Specifying a Coding System for File Text). For example, C-x RET c unix RET C-x C-f foobar.txt visits the file foobar.txt without converting the EOLs; if some line ends with a carriage return followed by linefeed pair, Emacs will display ‘^M’ at the end of that line. Similarly, you can direct Emacs to save a buffer in a specified EOL format with the C-x RET f command. For example, to save a buffer with Unix EOL format, type C-x RET f unix RET C-x C-s. If you visit a file with DOS EOL conversion, then save it with Unix EOL format, that effectively converts the file to Unix EOL style, like the dos2unix program.

When you use NFS, Samba, or some other similar method to access file systems that reside on computers using GNU or Unix systems, Emacs should not perform end-of-line translation on any files in these file systems—not even when you create a new file. To request this, designate these file systems as untranslated file systems by calling the function w32-add-untranslated-filesystem. It takes one argument: the file system name, including a drive letter and optionally a directory. For example,

(w32-add-untranslated-filesystem "Z:")

designates drive Z as an untranslated file system, and

(w32-add-untranslated-filesystem "Z:\\foo")

designates directory \foo on drive Z as an untranslated file system.

Most often you would use w32-add-untranslated-filesystem in your .emacs or init.el init file, or in site-start.el so that all the users at your site get the benefit of it.

To countermand the effect of w32-add-untranslated-filesystem, use the function w32-remove-untranslated-filesystem. This function takes one argument, which should be a string just like the one that was used previously with w32-add-untranslated-filesystem.

Designating a file system as untranslated does not affect character set conversion, only end-of-line conversion. Essentially, it directs Emacs to default to creating new files with the Unix-style convention of using newline at the end of a line. See Coding Systems.

H.3 File Names on MS-Windows

MS-Windows and MS-DOS normally use a backslash, ‘\’, to separate name units within a file name, instead of the slash used on other systems. Emacs on MS-DOS/MS-Windows permits use of either slash or backslash, and also knows about drive letters in file names.

On MS-DOS/MS-Windows, file names are case-insensitive, so Emacs by default ignores letter-case in file names during completion. To this end, the default value of read-file-name-completion-ignore-case is non-nil on MS-DOS/MS-Windows. See Completion Options.

The variable w32-get-true-file-attributes controls whether Emacs should issue additional system calls to determine more accurately file attributes in primitives like file-attributes and directory-files-and-attributes. These additional calls are needed to report correct file ownership, link counts and file types for special files such as pipes. Without these system calls, file ownership will be attributed to the current user, link counts will be always reported as 1, and special files will be reported as regular files.

If the value of this variable is local (the default), Emacs will issue these additional system calls only for files on local fixed drives. Any other non-nil value means do this even for removable and remote volumes, where this could potentially slow down Dired and other related features. The value of nil means never issue those system calls. Non-nil values are more useful on NTFS volumes, which support hard links and file security, than on FAT, FAT32, and exFAT volumes.

Unlike Unix, MS-Windows file systems restrict the set of characters that can be used in a file name. The following characters are not allowed:

Shell redirection symbols ‘<’, ‘>’, and ‘|’.
Colon ‘:’ (except after the drive letter).
Forward slash ‘/’ and backslash ‘\’ (except as directory separators).
Wildcard characters ‘*’ and ‘?’.
Control characters whose codepoints are 1 through 31 decimal. In particular, newlines in file names are not allowed.
The null character, whose codepoint is zero (this limitation exists on Unix filesystems as well).

In addition, referencing any file whose name matches a DOS character device, such as NUL or LPT1 or PRN or CON, with or without any file-name extension, will always resolve to those character devices, in any directory. Therefore, only use such file names when you want to use the corresponding character device.

H.4 Emulation of ls on MS-Windows

Dired normally uses the external program ls to produce the directory listing displayed in Dired buffers (see Dired, the Directory Editor). However, MS-Windows and MS-DOS systems don’t come with such a program, although several ports of GNU ls are available. Therefore, Emacs on those systems emulates ls in Lisp, by using the ls-lisp.el package. While ls-lisp.el provides a reasonably full emulation of ls, there are some options and features peculiar to that emulation; they are described in this section.

The ls emulation supports many of the ls switches, but it doesn’t support all of them. Here’s the list of the switches it does support: -A, -a, -B, -C, -c, -G, -g, -h, -i, -n, -R, -r, -S, -s, -t, -U, -u, -v, and -X. The -F switch is partially supported (it appends the character that classifies the file, but does not prevent symlink following).

On MS-Windows and MS-DOS, ls-lisp.el is preloaded when Emacs is built, so the Lisp emulation of ls is always used on those platforms. If you have a ported ls, setting ls-lisp-use-insert-directory-program to a non-nil value will revert to using an external program named by the variable insert-directory-program.

The order in which ls-lisp.el sorts files depends on several customizable options described below.

The default sorting order follows locale-specific rules derived from your system locale. You can make the order locale-independent by customizing ls-lisp-use-string-collate to a nil value.

On GNU and Unix systems, when the locale’s encoding is UTF-8, the collation order follows the Unicode Collation Algorithm (UCA). To have a similar effect on MS-Windows, the variable ls-lisp-UCA-like-collation should have a non-nil value (this is the default). The resulting sorting order ignores punctuation, symbol characters, and whitespace characters, so .foobar, foobar and foo bar will appear together rather than far apart.

By default, ls-lisp.el uses a case-sensitive sort order for the directory listing it produces; this is so the listing looks the same as on other platforms. If you wish that the files be sorted in case-insensitive order, set the variable ls-lisp-ignore-case to a non-nil value.

By default, files and subdirectories are sorted together, to emulate the behavior of ls. However, native MS-Windows/MS-DOS file managers list the directories before the files; if you want that behavior, customize the option ls-lisp-dirs-first to a non-nil value.

The variable ls-lisp-verbosity controls the file attributes that ls-lisp.el displays. The value should be either nil or a list that contains one or more of the symbols links, uid, and gid. links means display the count of different file names that are associated with (a.k.a. links to) the file’s data; this is only useful on NTFS volumes. uid means display the numerical identifier of the user who owns the file. gid means display the numerical identifier of the file owner’s group. The default value is (links uid gid) i.e., all the 3 optional attributes are displayed. The value nil means not to display any of these attributes.

The variable ls-lisp-emulation controls the flavor of the ls emulation by setting the defaults for the 3 options described above: ls-lisp-ignore-case, ls-lisp-dirs-first, and ls-lisp-verbosity. The value of this option can be one of the following symbols:

GNU
nil

Emulate GNU systems; this is the default. This sets ls-lisp-ignore-case and ls-lisp-dirs-first to nil, and ls-lisp-verbosity to (links uid gid).

UNIX

Emulate Unix systems. Like GNU, but sets ls-lisp-verbosity to (links uid).

MacOS

Emulate macOS. Sets ls-lisp-ignore-case to t, and ls-lisp-dirs-first and ls-lisp-verbosity to nil.

MS-Windows

Emulate MS-Windows. Sets ls-lisp-ignore-case and ls-lisp-dirs-first to t, and ls-lisp-verbosity to nil on Windows 9X and to t on modern versions of Windows. Note that the default emulation is not MS-Windows, even on Windows, since many users of Emacs on those platforms prefer the GNU defaults.

Any other value of ls-lisp-emulation means the same as GNU. Customizing this option calls the function ls-lisp-set-options to update the 3 dependent options as needed. If you change the value of this variable without using customize after ls-lisp.el is loaded (note that it is preloaded on MS-Windows and MS-DOS), you can call that function manually for the same result.

The variable ls-lisp-support-shell-wildcards controls how file-name patterns are supported: if it is non-nil (the default), they are treated as shell-style wildcards; otherwise they are treated as Emacs regular expressions.

The variable ls-lisp-format-time-list defines how to format the date and time of files. The value of this variable is ignored, unless Emacs cannot determine the current locale. (However, if the value of ls-lisp-use-localized-time-format is non-nil, Emacs obeys ls-lisp-format-time-list even if the current locale is available; see below.)

The value of ls-lisp-format-time-list is a list of 2 strings. The first string is used if the file was modified within the current year, while the second string is used for older files. In each of these two strings you can use ‘%’-sequences to substitute parts of the time. For example:

("%b %e %H:%M" "%b %e  %Y")

Note that the strings substituted for these ‘%’-sequences depend on the current locale. See Time Parsing in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for more about format time specs.

Normally, Emacs formats the file time stamps in either traditional or ISO-style time format. However, if the value of the variable ls-lisp-use-localized-time-format is non-nil, Emacs formats file time stamps according to what ls-lisp-format-time-list specifies. The ‘%’-sequences in ls-lisp-format-time-list produce locale-dependent month and day names, which might cause misalignment of columns in Dired display. The default value of ls-lisp-use-localized-time-format is nil.

H.5 HOME and Startup Directories on MS-Windows

The Windows equivalent of HOME is the user-specific application data directory. The actual location depends on the Windows version; typical values are C:\Documents and Settings\username\Application Data on Windows 2000 up to XP, C:\Users\username\AppData\Roaming on Windows Vista and later, and either C:\WINDOWS\Application Data or C:\WINDOWS\Profiles\username\Application Data on Windows 9X/ME. If this directory does not exist or cannot be accessed, Emacs falls back to C:\ as the default value of HOME.

You can override this default value of HOME by explicitly setting the environment variable HOME to point to any directory on your system. HOME can be set either from the command shell prompt or from ‘Properties’ dialog of ‘My Computer’. HOME can also be set in the system registry, see The MS-Windows System Registry.

For compatibility with older versions of Emacs^27, if there is a file named .emacs in C:\, the root directory of drive C:, and HOME is set neither in the environment nor in the Registry, Emacs will treat C:\ as the default HOME location, and will not look in the application data directory, even if it exists. Note that only .emacs is looked for in C:\; the older name _emacs (see below) is not. This use of C:\.emacs to define HOME is deprecated; Emacs will display a warning about its use during startup.

Whatever the final place is, Emacs sets the internal value of the HOME environment variable to point to it, and it will use that location for other files and directories it normally looks for or creates in your home directory.

You can always find out what Emacs thinks is your home directory’s location by typing C-x d ~/ RET. This should present the list of files in the home directory, and show its full name on the first line. Likewise, to visit your init file, type C-x C-f ~/.emacs RET (assuming the file’s name is .emacs).

Your init file can have any name mentioned in The Emacs Initialization File.

Because MS-DOS does not allow file names with leading dots, and older Windows systems made it hard to create files with such names, the Windows port of Emacs supports an init file name _emacs, if such a file exists in the home directory and .emacs does not. This name is considered obsolete, so Emacs will display a warning if it is used.

H.6 Keyboard Usage on MS-Windows

This section describes the Windows-specific features related to keyboard input in Emacs.

Many key combinations (known as “keyboard shortcuts”) that have conventional uses in MS-Windows programs conflict with traditional Emacs key bindings. (These Emacs key bindings were established years before Microsoft was founded.) Examples of conflicts include C-c, C-x, C-z, and C-a. You can redefine some of them with meanings more like the MS-Windows meanings by enabling CUA Mode (see CUA Bindings). Another optional feature which will make Emacs behave like other Windows applications is Delete Selection mode (see Operating on the Region).

By default, the key labeled Alt is mapped as the Meta key. If you wish it to produce the Alt modifier instead, set the variable w32-alt-is-meta to a nil value.

MS-Windows reserves certain key combinations, such as Alt-TAB and a number of Windows key combinations, for its own use. These key combinations are intercepted by the system before Emacs can see them. Also, on Windows 10, all Windows key combinations are reserved by the system in such a way that they are never propagated to applications, even if the system does not currently define a hotkey on the specific combination. You can use the w32-register-hot-key function to allow a key sequence to be seen by Emacs instead of being grabbed by Windows. When registered as a hot key, the key combination is pulled out of the system’s input queue before it is handled by Windows, effectively overriding the special meaning of that key sequence for Windows. The override is only effective when Emacs is active; with other applications on the foreground the keys behave normally.

The argument to w32-register-hot-key must be a single key with a single modifier, in vector form that would be acceptable to define-key. The control and shift modifiers have no effect on the argument. The meta modifier is interpreted as the Alt key if w32-alt-is-meta is t (the default), and the super and hyper modifiers are interpreted according to the bindings of w32-lwindow-modifier and w32-rwindow-modifier. Additionally, a modifier with the trailing dash but with no key indicates that all Windows defined hotkeys for that modifier are to be overridden in the favor of Emacs.

For example, (w32-register-hot-key [M-tab]) lets you use M-TAB normally in Emacs; for instance, to complete the word or symbol at point at top level, or to complete the current search string against previously sought strings during incremental search. (w32-register-hot-key [s-]) with w32-lwindow-modifier bound to super disables all the Windows’ own Windows key based shortcuts.^28

Note that w32-register-hot-key checks the w32-[lr]window-modifier values at the time of the function call. Thus, you can set w32-lwindow-modifier as super, then call (w32-register-hot-key [s-r]), and finally set w32-rwindow-modifier as super as well. The result is that the left Windows key together with R invokes whichever function you have bound for the combination in Emacs, and the right Windows key and R opens the Windows Run dialog.

The hotkey registrations always also include all the shift and control modifier combinations for the given hotkey; that is, registering s-a as a hotkey gives you S-s-a, C-s-a and C-S-s-a as well.

On Windows 98 and ME, the hotkey registration is more restricted. The desired hotkey must always be fully specified, and w32-phantom-key-code can be customized to achieve desired results.

The function w32-unregister-hot-key reverses the effect of w32-register-hot-key for its argument key sequence.

By default, the CapsLock key only affects normal character keys (it converts lower-case characters to their upper-case variants). However, if you set the variable w32-capslock-is-shiftlock to a non-nil value, the CapsLock key will affect non-character keys as well, as if you pressed the SHIFT key while typing the non-character key.

If the variable w32-enable-caps-lock is set to a nil value, the CapsLock key produces the symbol capslock instead of the shifted version of typed keys. The default value is t.

Similarly, if w32-enable-num-lock is nil, the NumLock key will produce the symbol kp-numlock. The default is t, which causes NumLock to work as expected: toggle the meaning of the keys on the numeric keypad.

The variable w32-apps-modifier controls the effect of the Apps key (usually located between the right Alt and the right Ctrl keys). Its value can be one of the symbols hyper, super, meta, alt, control, or shift for the respective modifier, or nil to appear as the key apps. The default is nil.

The variable w32-lwindow-modifier determines the effect of the left Windows key (usually labeled with start and the Windows logo). If its value is nil (the default), the key will produce the symbol lwindow. Setting it to one of the symbols hyper, super, meta, alt, control, or shift will produce the respective modifier. A similar variable w32-rwindow-modifier controls the effect of the right Windows key, and w32-scroll-lock-modifier does the same for the ScrLock key. If these variables are set to nil, the right Windows key produces the symbol rwindow and ScrLock produces the symbol scroll. If you want ScrLock to produce the same effect as in other applications, i.e. toggle the Scroll Lock LED indication on the keyboard, set w32-scroll-lock-modifier to t or any non-nil value other than the above modifier symbols.

Emacs compiled as a native Windows application normally turns off the Windows feature that tapping the Alt key invokes the Windows menu. The reason is that the Alt serves as Meta in Emacs. When using Emacs, users often press the Meta key temporarily and then change their minds; if this has the effect of bringing up the Windows menu, it alters the meaning of subsequent commands. Many users find this frustrating.

You can re-enable Windows’s default handling of tapping the Alt key by setting w32-pass-alt-to-system to a non-nil value.

The variables w32-pass-lwindow-to-system and w32-pass-rwindow-to-system determine whether the respective keys are passed to Windows or swallowed by Emacs. If the value is nil, the respective key is silently swallowed by Emacs, otherwise it is passed to Windows. The default is t for both of these variables. Passing each of these keys to Windows produces its normal effect: for example, Lwindow opens the Start menu, etc.

The variable w32-recognize-altgr controls whether the AltGr key (if it exists on your keyboard), or its equivalent, the combination of the right Alt and left Ctrl keys pressed together, is recognized as the AltGr key. The default is t, which means these keys produce AltGr; setting it to nil causes AltGr or the equivalent key combination to be interpreted as the combination of Ctrl and Meta modifiers.

Some versions of MS-Windows, typically East Asian localized Windows, enable the Input Method Manager (IMM) that allows applications to communicate with the Input Method Editor (IME), the native Windows input method service. Emacs uses the IME when available to allow users to input East Asian non-ASCII characters, similarly to Emacs’s built-in input methods (see Input Methods). However, in some situations the IME can get in the way if it interprets simple ASCII keys you input as part of a key sequence that designates a non-ASCII character. The IME can be temporarily turned off and then on again by using the w32-set-ime-open-status function.

H.7 Mouse Usage on MS-Windows

This section describes the Windows-specific variables related to the mouse.

The variable w32-mouse-button-tolerance specifies the time interval, in milliseconds, for faking middle mouse button press on 2-button mice. If both mouse buttons are depressed within this time interval, Emacs generates a middle mouse button click event instead of a double click on one of the buttons.

If the variable w32-pass-extra-mouse-buttons-to-system is non-nil, Emacs passes the fourth and fifth mouse buttons to Windows.

The variable w32-swap-mouse-buttons controls which of the 3 mouse buttons generates the mouse-2 events. When it is nil (the default), the middle button generates mouse-2 and the right button generates mouse-3 events. If this variable is non-nil, the roles of these two buttons are reversed.

H.8 Subprocesses on Windows 9X/ME and Windows NT/2K/XP/Vista/7/8/10

Emacs compiled as a native Windows application (as opposed to the DOS version) includes full support for asynchronous subprocesses. In the Windows version, synchronous and asynchronous subprocesses work fine on all versions of MS-Windows, as long as you run only 32-bit or 64-bit Windows applications. However, when you run a DOS application in a subprocess, you may encounter problems or be unable to run the application at all; and if you run two DOS applications at the same time in two subprocesses, you may have to reboot your system.

Since the standard command interpreter (and most command line utilities) on Windows 9X are DOS applications, these problems are significant when using that system. But there’s nothing we can do about them; only Microsoft can fix them.

If you run just one DOS application subprocess, the subprocess should work as expected as long as it is “well-behaved” and does not perform direct screen access or other unusual actions. If you have a CPU monitor application, your machine will appear to be 100% busy even when the DOS application is idle, but this is only an artifact of the way CPU monitors measure processor load.

You must terminate the DOS application before you start any other DOS application in a different subprocess. Emacs is unable to interrupt or terminate a DOS subprocess. The only way you can terminate such a subprocess is by giving it a command that tells its program to exit.

If you attempt to run two DOS applications at the same time in separate subprocesses, the second one that is started will be suspended until the first one finishes, even if either or both of them are asynchronous.

If you can go to the first subprocess, and tell it to exit, the second subprocess should continue normally. However, if the second subprocess is synchronous, Emacs itself will be hung until the first subprocess finishes. If it will not finish without user input, then you have no choice but to reboot if you are running on Windows 9X. If you are running on Windows NT and later, you can use a process viewer application to kill the appropriate instance of NTVDM instead (this will terminate both DOS subprocesses).

If you have to reboot Windows 9X in this situation, do not use the Shutdown command on the Start menu; that usually hangs the system. Instead, type Ctrl-Alt-DEL and then choose Shutdown. That usually works, although it may take a few minutes to do its job.

The variable w32-quote-process-args controls how Emacs quotes the process arguments. Non-nil means quote with the " character. If the value is a character, Emacs uses that character to escape any quote characters that appear; otherwise it chooses a suitable escape character based on the type of the program.

The variable w32-pipe-buffer-size controls the size of the buffer Emacs requests from the system when it creates pipes for communications with subprocesses. The default value is zero, which lets the OS choose the size. Any valid positive value will request a buffer of that size in bytes. This can be used to tailor communications with subprocesses to programs that exhibit unusual behavior with respect to buffering pipe I/O.

If you need to invoke MS-DOS programs as Emacs subprocesses, you may see low rate of reading data from such programs. Setting the variable w32-pipe-read-delay to a non-zero value may improve throughput in these cases; we suggest the value of 50 for such situations. The default is zero.

The function w32-shell-execute can be useful for writing customized commands that run MS-Windows applications registered to handle a certain standard Windows operation for a specific type of document or file. This function is a wrapper around the Windows ShellExecute API. See the MS-Windows API documentation for more details.

H.9 Printing and MS-Windows

Printing commands, such as lpr-buffer (see Printing Hard Copies) and ps-print-buffer (see PostScript Hardcopy) work in MS-DOS and MS-Windows by sending the output to one of the printer ports, if a POSIX-style lpr program is unavailable. The same Emacs variables control printing on all systems, but in some cases they have different default values on MS-DOS and MS-Windows.

Emacs on MS Windows attempts to determine your default printer automatically (using the function default-printer-name). But in some rare cases this can fail, or you may wish to use a different printer from within Emacs. The rest of this section explains how to tell Emacs which printer to use.

If you want to use your local printer, then set the Lisp variable lpr-command to "" (its default value on Windows) and printer-name to the name of the printer port—for example, "PRN", the usual local printer port, or "LPT2", or "COM1" for a serial printer. You can also set printer-name to a file name, in which case “printed” output is actually appended to that file. If you set printer-name to "NUL", printed output is silently discarded (sent to the system null device).

You can also use a printer shared by another machine by setting printer-name to the UNC share name for that printer—for example, "//joes_pc/hp4si". (It doesn’t matter whether you use forward slashes or backslashes here.) To find out the names of shared printers, run the command ‘net view’ from the command prompt to obtain a list of servers, and ‘net view server-name’ to see the names of printers (and directories) shared by that server. Alternatively, click the ‘Network Neighborhood’ icon on your desktop, and look for machines that share their printers via the network.

If the printer doesn’t appear in the output of ‘net view’, or if setting printer-name to the UNC share name doesn’t produce a hardcopy on that printer, you can use the ‘net use’ command to connect a local print port such as "LPT2" to the networked printer. For example, typing net use LPT2: \\joes_pc\hp4si^29 causes Windows to capture the LPT2 port and redirect the printed material to the printer connected to the machine joes_pc. After this command, setting printer-name to "LPT2" should produce the hardcopy on the networked printer.

With some varieties of Windows network software, you can instruct Windows to capture a specific printer port such as "LPT2", and redirect it to a networked printer via the Control Panel->Printers applet instead of ‘net use’.

If you set printer-name to a file name, it’s best to use an absolute file name. Emacs changes the working directory according to the default directory of the current buffer, so if the file name in printer-name is relative, you will end up with several such files, each one in the directory of the buffer from which the printing was done.

If the value of printer-name is correct, but printing does not produce the hardcopy on your printer, it is possible that your printer does not support printing plain text (some cheap printers omit this functionality). In that case, try the PostScript print commands, described below.

The commands print-buffer and print-region call the pr program, or use special switches to the lpr program, to produce headers on each printed page. MS-DOS and MS-Windows don’t normally have these programs, so by default, the variable lpr-headers-switches is set so that the requests to print page headers are silently ignored. Thus, print-buffer and print-region produce the same output as lpr-buffer and lpr-region, respectively. If you do have a suitable pr program (for example, from GNU Coreutils), set lpr-headers-switches to nil; Emacs will then call pr to produce the page headers, and print the resulting output as specified by printer-name.

Finally, if you do have an lpr work-alike, you can set the variable lpr-command to "lpr". Then Emacs will use lpr for printing, as on other systems. (If the name of the program isn’t lpr, set lpr-command to the appropriate value.) The variable lpr-switches has its standard meaning when lpr-command is not "". If the variable printer-name has a string value, it is used as the value for the -P option to lpr, as on Unix.

A parallel set of variables, ps-lpr-command, ps-lpr-switches, and ps-printer-name (see Variables for PostScript Hardcopy), defines how PostScript files should be printed. These variables are used in the same way as the corresponding variables described above for non-PostScript printing. Thus, the value of ps-printer-name is used as the name of the device (or file) to which PostScript output is sent, just as printer-name is used for non-PostScript printing. (There are two distinct sets of variables in case you have two printers attached to two different ports, and only one of them is a PostScript printer.)

The default value of the variable ps-lpr-command is "", which causes PostScript output to be sent to the printer port specified by ps-printer-name; but ps-lpr-command can also be set to the name of a program which will accept PostScript files. Thus, if you have a non-PostScript printer, you can set this variable to the name of a PostScript interpreter program (such as Ghostscript). Any switches that need to be passed to the interpreter program are specified using ps-lpr-switches. (If the value of ps-printer-name is a string, it will be added to the list of switches as the value for the -P option. This is probably only useful if you are using lpr, so when using an interpreter typically you would set ps-printer-name to something other than a string so it is ignored.)

For example, to use Ghostscript for printing on the system’s default printer, put this in your .emacs file:

(setq ps-printer-name t)
(setq ps-lpr-command "D:/gs6.01/bin/gswin32c.exe")
(setq ps-lpr-switches '("-q" "-dNOPAUSE" "-dBATCH"
                        "-sDEVICE=mswinpr2"
                        "-sPAPERSIZE=a4"))

(This assumes that Ghostscript is installed in the D:/gs6.01 directory.)

H.10 Specifying Fonts on MS-Windows

Fonts are specified by their name, size and optional properties. The format for specifying fonts comes from the fontconfig library used in modern Free desktops:

  [Family[-PointSize]][:Option1=Value1[:Option2=Value2[...]]]

The old XLFD based format is also supported for backwards compatibility.

Emacs on MS-Windows supports a number of font backends. Currently, the gdi, uniscribe, and harfbuzz backends are available. The gdi font backend is available on all versions of Windows, and supports all fonts that are natively supported by Windows. The uniscribe font backend is available on Windows 2000 and later, and supports TrueType and OpenType fonts. The harfbuzz font backend is available if Emacs was built with HarfBuzz support, and if the HarfBuzz DLL is installed on your system; like uniscribe, this backend supports only TrueType and OpenType fonts. Some languages requiring complex layout can only be properly supported by the Uniscribe or HarfBuzz backends. By default, two backends are enabled for each frame: gdi and either harfbuzz or uniscribe, depending on which one is available (if both are available, only harfbuzz is enabled by default). The harfbuzz and uniscribe backends take priority over gdi when Emacs looks for a suitable font. To override that and use the GDI backend even if Uniscribe is available, invoke Emacs with the -xrm Emacs.fontBackend:gdi command-line argument, or add a Emacs.fontBackend resource with the value gdi in the Registry under either the ‘HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\GNU\Emacs’ or the ‘HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\GNU\Emacs’ key (see X Resources). Similarly, to use the Uniscribe backend even if HarfBuzz is available, use -xrm Emacs.fontBackend:uniscribe on the command line that invokes Emacs. You can also request all the 3 backends via the font-backend frame parameter, but be warned that in that case font searches for characters for which no fonts are available on the system will take longer.

Alternatively, you could specify a font backend for a frame via the font-backend frame parameter, using modify-frame-parameters (see Parameter Access in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). You can also request specific font backend(s) for all your frames via default-frame-alist and initial-frame-alist (see Frame Parameters). Note that the value of the font-backend parameter should be a list of symbols, as in (uniscribe) or (harfbuzz uniscribe gdi) .

Optional font properties supported on MS-Windows are:

weight

Specifies the weight of the font. Special values light, medium, demibold, bold, and black can be specified without weight= (e.g., Courier New-12:bold). Otherwise, the weight should be a numeric value between 100 and 900, or one of the named weights in font-weight-table. If unspecified, a regular font is assumed.

slant

Specifies whether the font is italic. Special values roman, italic and oblique can be specified without slant= (e.g., Courier New-12:italic). Otherwise, the slant should be a numeric value, or one of the named slants in font-slant-table. On Windows, any slant above 150 is treated as italics, and anything below as roman.

family

Specifies the font family, but normally this will be specified at the start of the font name.

pixelsize

Specifies the font size in pixels. This can be used instead of the point size specified after the family name.

adstyle

Specifies additional style information for the font. On MS-Windows, the values mono, sans, serif, script and decorative are recognized. These are most useful as a fallback with the font family left unspecified.

registry

Specifies the character set registry that the font is expected to cover. Most TrueType and OpenType fonts will be Unicode fonts that cover several national character sets, but you can narrow down the selection of fonts to those that support a particular character set by using a specific registry from w32-charset-info-alist here.

spacing

Specifies how the font is spaced. The p spacing specifies a proportional font, and m or c specify a monospaced font.

foundry

Not used on Windows, but for informational purposes and to prevent problems with code that expects it to be set, is set internally to raster for bitmapped fonts, outline for scalable fonts, or unknown if the type cannot be determined as one of those.

script

Specifies a Unicode subrange the font should support.

All the scripts known to Emacs (which generally means all the scripts defined by the latest Unicode Standard) are recognized on MS-Windows. However, GDI fonts support only a subset of the known scripts: greek, hangul, kana, kanbun, bopomofo, tibetan, yi, mongolian, hebrew, arabic, and thai.

antialias

Specifies the antialiasing method. The value none means no antialiasing, standard means use standard antialiasing, subpixel means use subpixel antialiasing (known as Cleartype on Windows), and natural means use subpixel antialiasing with adjusted spacing between letters. If unspecified, the font will use the system default antialiasing.

The method used by Emacs on MS-Windows to look for fonts suitable for displaying a given non-ASCII character might fail for some rare scripts, specifically those added by Unicode relatively recently, even if you have fonts installed on your system that support those scripts. That is because these scripts have no Unicode Subrange Bits (USBs) defined for them in the information used by Emacs on MS-Windows to look for fonts. You can use the w32-find-non-USB-fonts function to overcome these problems. It needs to be run once at the beginning of the Emacs session, and again if you install new fonts. You can add the following line to your init file to have this function run every time you start Emacs:

(w32-find-non-USB-fonts)

Alternatively, you can run this function manually via M-: (see Evaluating Emacs Lisp Expressions) at any time. On a system that has many fonts installed, running w32-find-non-USB-fonts might take a couple of seconds; if you consider that to be too long to be run during startup, and if you install new fonts only rarely, run this function once via M-:, and then assign the value it returns, if non-nil, to the variable w32-non-USB-fonts in your init file. (If the function returns nil, you have no fonts installed that can display characters from the scripts which need this facility.)

The variable w32-use-w32-font-dialog controls the way fonts can be selected via S-mouse-1 (mouse-appearance-menu). If the value is t, the default, Emacs uses the standard Windows font selection dialog. If the value is nil, Emacs instead pops a menu of a fixed set of fonts. The fonts to appear in the menu are determined by w32-fixed-font-alist.

H.11 Miscellaneous Windows-specific features

This section describes Windows-specific features that don’t fit anywhere else.

The variable w32-use-visible-system-caret is a flag that determines whether to make the system caret visible. The default when no screen reader software is in use is nil, which means Emacs draws its own cursor to indicate the position of point. A non-nil value means Emacs will indicate point location with the system caret; this facilitates use of screen reader software, and is the default when such software is detected when running Emacs. When this variable is non-nil, other variables affecting the cursor display have no effect.

The variable w32-grab-focus-on-raise, if set to a non-nil value causes a frame to grab focus when it is raised. The default is t, which fits well with the Windows default click-to-focus policy.

On Windows 10 (version 1809 and higher) and Windows 11, Emacs title bars and scroll bars will follow the system’s Light or Dark mode, similar to other programs such as Explorer and Command Prompt. To change the color mode, select Personalization from Windows Settings , then Colors->Choose your color (or Choose your default app mode ); then restart Emacs.

H.12 Emacs and MS-DOS

This section briefly describes the peculiarities of using Emacs on MS-DOS. Information about peculiarities common to MS-DOS and Microsoft’s current operating systems Windows is in Emacs and Microsoft Windows/MS-DOS.

If you build Emacs for MS-DOS, the binary will also run on Windows 3.X, Windows NT, Windows 9X/ME, or Windows 2000/XP as a DOS application; all of this chapter applies for all of those systems, if you use an Emacs that was built for MS-DOS.

See Text Files and Binary Files, for information about Emacs’s special handling of text files under MS-DOS (and Windows).

H.12.1 Keyboard Usage on MS-DOS

The key that is called DEL in Emacs (because that’s how it is designated on most workstations) is known as BS (backspace) on a PC. That is why the PC-specific terminal initialization remaps the BS key to act as DEL; the Delete key is remapped to act as C-d for the same reasons.

Emacs built for MS-DOS recognizes C-Break as a quit character, just like C-g. This is because Emacs cannot detect that you have typed C-g until it is ready for more input. As a consequence, you cannot use C-g to stop a running command (see Quitting and Aborting). By contrast, C-Break is detected as soon as you type it (as C-g is on other systems), so it can be used to stop a running command and for emergency escape (see Emergency Escape).

The PC keyboard maps use the left Alt key as the Meta key. You have two choices for emulating the SUPER and Hyper keys: choose either the right Ctrl key or the right Alt key by setting the variables dos-hyper-key and dos-super-key to 1 or 2 respectively. If neither dos-super-key nor dos-hyper-key is 1, then by default the right Alt key is also mapped to the Meta key. However, if the MS-DOS international keyboard support program KEYB.COM is installed, Emacs will not map the right Alt to Meta, since it is used for accessing characters like ~ and @ on non-US keyboard layouts; in this case, you may only use the left Alt as Meta key.

The variable dos-keypad-mode is a flag variable that controls what key codes are returned by keys in the numeric keypad. You can also define the keypad ENTER key to act like C-j, by putting the following line into your _emacs file:

;; Make the ENTER key from the numeric keypad act as C-j.
(keymap-set function-key-map "<kp-enter>" "C-j")

H.12.2 Mouse Usage on MS-DOS

Emacs on MS-DOS supports a mouse (on the default terminal only). The mouse commands work as documented, including those that use menus and the menu bar (see The Menu Bar). Scroll bars don’t work in MS-DOS Emacs. PC mice usually have only two buttons; these act as mouse-1 and mouse-2, but if you press both of them together, that has the effect of mouse-3. If the mouse does have 3 buttons, Emacs detects that at startup, and all the 3 buttons function normally, as on X.

Help strings for menu-bar and pop-up menus are displayed in the echo area when the mouse pointer moves across the menu items. Highlighting of mouse-sensitive text (see Following References with the Mouse) is also supported.

Some versions of mouse drivers don’t report the number of mouse buttons correctly. For example, mice with a wheel report that they have 3 buttons, but only 2 of them are passed to Emacs; the clicks on the wheel, which serves as the middle button, are not passed. In these cases, you can use the M-x msdos-set-mouse-buttons command to tell Emacs how many mouse buttons to expect. You could make such a setting permanent by adding this fragment to your _emacs init file:

;; Treat the mouse like a 2-button mouse.
(msdos-set-mouse-buttons 2)

Emacs built for MS-DOS supports clipboard operations when it runs on Windows. Commands that put text on the kill ring, or yank text from the ring, check the Windows clipboard first, just as Emacs does on the X Window System (see Mouse Commands for Editing). Only the primary selection and the cut buffer are supported by MS-DOS Emacs on Windows; the secondary selection always appears as empty.

Due to the way clipboard access is implemented by Windows, the length of text you can put into the clipboard is limited by the amount of free DOS memory that is available to Emacs. Usually, up to 620KB of text can be put into the clipboard, but this limit depends on the system configuration and is lower if you run Emacs as a subprocess of another program. If the killed text does not fit, Emacs outputs a message saying so, and does not put the text into the clipboard.

Null characters also cannot be put into the Windows clipboard. If the killed text includes null characters, Emacs does not put such text into the clipboard, and displays in the echo area a message to that effect.

The variable dos-display-scancodes, when non-nil, directs Emacs to display the ASCII value and the keyboard scan code of each keystroke; this feature serves as a complement to the view-lossage command, for debugging.

H.12.3 Display on MS-DOS

Display on MS-DOS cannot use font variants, like bold or italic, but it does support multiple faces, each of which can specify a foreground and a background color. Therefore, you can get the full functionality of Emacs packages that use fonts (such as font-lock, Enriched Text mode, and others) by defining the relevant faces to use different colors. Use the list-colors-display command (see Colors for Faces) and the list-faces-display command (see Text Faces) to see what colors and faces are available and what they look like.

See International Support on MS-DOS, later in this chapter, for information on how Emacs displays glyphs and characters that aren’t supported by the native font built into the DOS display.

When Emacs starts, it changes the cursor shape to a solid box. This is for compatibility with other systems, where the box cursor is the default in Emacs. This default shape can be changed to a bar by specifying the cursor-type parameter in the variable default-frame-alist (see Creating Frames). The MS-DOS terminal doesn’t support a vertical-bar cursor, so the bar cursor is horizontal, and the width parameter, if specified by the frame parameters, actually determines its height. For this reason, the bar and hbar cursor types produce the same effect on MS-DOS. As an extension, the bar cursor specification can include the starting scan line of the cursor as well as its width, like this:

 '(cursor-type bar width . start)

In addition, if the width parameter is negative, the cursor bar begins at the top of the character cell.

The MS-DOS terminal can only display a single frame at a time. The Emacs frame facilities work on MS-DOS much as they do on text terminals (see Frames and Graphical Displays). When you run Emacs from a DOS window on MS-Windows, you can make the visible frame smaller than the full screen, but Emacs still cannot display more than a single frame at a time.

The dos-mode4350 command switches the display to 43 or 50 lines, depending on your hardware; the dos-mode25 command switches to the default 80x25 screen size.

By default, Emacs only knows how to set screen sizes of 80 columns by 25, 28, 35, 40, 43 or 50 rows. However, if your video adapter has special video modes that will switch the display to other sizes, you can have Emacs support those too. When you ask Emacs to switch the frame to n rows by m columns dimensions, it checks if there is a variable called screen-dimensions-nxm, and if so, uses its value (which must be an integer) as the video mode to switch to. (Emacs switches to that video mode by calling the BIOS Set Video Mode function with the value of screen-dimensions-nxm in the AL register.) For example, suppose your adapter will switch to 66x80 dimensions when put into video mode 85. Then you can make Emacs support this screen size by putting the following into your _emacs file:

(setq screen-dimensions-66x80 85)

Since Emacs on MS-DOS can only set the frame size to specific supported dimensions, it cannot honor every possible frame resizing request. When an unsupported size is requested, Emacs chooses the next larger supported size beyond the specified size. For example, if you ask for 36x80 frame, you will get 40x80 instead.

The variables screen-dimensions-nxm are used only when they exactly match the specified size; the search for the next larger supported size ignores them. In the above example, even if your VGA supports 38x80 dimensions and you define a variable screen-dimensions-38x80 with a suitable value, you will still get 40x80 screen when you ask for a 36x80 frame. If you want to get the 38x80 size in this case, you can do it by setting the variable named screen-dimensions-36x80 with the same video mode value as screen-dimensions-38x80.

Changing frame dimensions on MS-DOS has the effect of changing all the other frames to the new dimensions.

H.12.4 File Names on MS-DOS

On MS-DOS, file names are case-insensitive and limited to eight characters, plus optionally a period and three more characters. Emacs knows enough about these limitations to handle file names that were meant for other operating systems. For instance, leading dots ‘.’ in file names are invalid in MS-DOS, so Emacs transparently converts them to underscores ‘_’; thus your default init file (see The Emacs Initialization File) is called _emacs on MS-DOS. Excess characters before or after the period are generally ignored by MS-DOS itself; thus, if you visit the file LongFileName.EvenLongerExtension, you will silently get longfile.eve, but Emacs will still display the long file name on the mode line. Other than that, it’s up to you to specify file names which are valid under MS-DOS; the transparent conversion as described above only works on file names built into Emacs.

The above restrictions on the file names on MS-DOS make it almost impossible to construct the name of a backup file (see Single or Numbered Backups) without losing some of the original file name characters. For example, the name of a backup file for docs.txt is docs.tx~ even if single backup is used.

If you run Emacs as a DOS application under Windows 9X, Windows ME, or Windows 2000/XP, you can turn on support for long file names. If you do that, Emacs doesn’t truncate file names or convert them to lower case; instead, it uses the file names that you specify, verbatim. To enable long file name support, set the environment variable LFN to ‘y’ before starting Emacs. Unfortunately, Windows NT doesn’t allow DOS programs to access long file names, so Emacs built for MS-DOS will only see their short 8+3 aliases.

MS-DOS has no notion of home directory, so Emacs on MS-DOS pretends that the directory where it is installed is the value of the HOME environment variable. That is, if your Emacs binary, emacs.exe, is in the directory c:/utils/emacs/bin, then Emacs acts as if HOME were set to ‘c:/utils/emacs’. In particular, that is where Emacs looks for the init file _emacs. With this in mind, you can use ‘~’ in file names as an alias for the home directory, as you would on GNU or Unix. You can also set HOME variable in the environment before starting Emacs; its value will then override the above default behavior.

Emacs on MS-DOS handles the name /dev specially, because of a feature in the emulator libraries of DJGPP that pretends I/O devices have names in that directory. We recommend that you avoid using an actual directory named /dev on any disk.

H.12.5 Printing and MS-DOS

Printing commands, such as lpr-buffer (see Printing Hard Copies) and ps-print-buffer (see PostScript Hardcopy) can work on MS-DOS by sending the output to one of the printer ports, if a POSIX-style lpr program is unavailable. The same Emacs variables control printing on all systems, but in some cases they have different default values on MS-DOS.

See Printing and MS-Windows, for details about setting up printing to a networked printer.

Some printers expect DOS codepage encoding of non-ASCII text, even though they are connected to a Windows machine that uses a different encoding for the same locale. For example, in the Latin-1 locale, DOS uses codepage 850 whereas Windows uses codepage 1252. See International Support on MS-DOS. When you print to such printers from Windows, you can use the C-x RET c (universal-coding-system-argument) command before M-x lpr-buffer; Emacs will then convert the text to the DOS codepage that you specify. For example, C-x RET c cp850-dos RET M-x lpr-region RET will print the region while converting it to the codepage 850 encoding.

For backwards compatibility, the value of dos-printer (dos-ps-printer), if it has a value, overrides the value of printer-name (ps-printer-name), on MS-DOS.

H.12.6 International Support on MS-DOS

Emacs on MS-DOS supports the same international character sets as it does on GNU, Unix and other platforms (see International Character Set Support), including coding systems for converting between the different character sets. However, due to incompatibilities between MS-DOS/MS-Windows and other systems, there are several DOS-specific aspects of this support that you should be aware of. This section describes these aspects.

The description below is largely specific to the MS-DOS port of Emacs, especially where it talks about practical implications for Emacs users.

M-x dos-codepage-setup

Set up Emacs display and coding systems as appropriate for the current DOS codepage.

MS-DOS is designed to support one character set of 256 characters at any given time, but gives you a variety of character sets to choose from. The alternative character sets are known as DOS codepages. Each codepage includes all 128 ASCII characters, but the other 128 characters (codes 128 through 255) vary from one codepage to another. Each DOS codepage is identified by a 3-digit number, such as 850, 862, etc.

In contrast to X, which lets you use several fonts at the same time, MS-DOS normally doesn’t allow use of several codepages in a single session. MS-DOS was designed to load a single codepage at system startup, and require you to reboot in order to change it^30. Much the same limitation applies when you run DOS executables on other systems such as MS-Windows.

For multibyte operation on MS-DOS, Emacs needs to know which characters the chosen DOS codepage can display. So it queries the system shortly after startup to get the chosen codepage number, and stores the number in the variable dos-codepage. Some systems return the default value 437 for the current codepage, even though the actual codepage is different. (This typically happens when you use the codepage built into the display hardware.) You can specify a different codepage for Emacs to use by setting the variable dos-codepage in your init file.

Multibyte Emacs supports only certain DOS codepages: those which can display Far-Eastern scripts, like the Japanese codepage 932, and those that encode a single ISO 8859 character set.

The Far-Eastern codepages can directly display one of the MULE character sets for these countries, so Emacs simply sets up to use the appropriate terminal coding system that is supported by the codepage. The special features described in the rest of this section mostly pertain to codepages that encode ISO 8859 character sets.

For the codepages that correspond to one of the ISO character sets, Emacs knows the character set based on the codepage number. Emacs automatically creates a coding system to support reading and writing files that use the current codepage, and uses this coding system by default. The name of this coding system is cpnnn, where nnn is the codepage number.^31

All the cpnnn coding systems use the letter ‘D’ (for “DOS”) as their mode-line mnemonic. Since both the terminal coding system and the default coding system for file I/O are set to the proper cpnnn coding system at startup, it is normal for the mode line on MS-DOS to begin with ‘-DD\-’. See The Mode Line. Far-Eastern DOS terminals do not use the cpnnn coding systems, and thus their initial mode line looks like the Emacs default.

Since the codepage number also indicates which script you are using, Emacs automatically runs set-language-environment to select the language environment for that script (see Language Environments).

If a buffer contains a character belonging to some other ISO 8859 character set, not the one that the chosen DOS codepage supports, Emacs displays it using a sequence of ASCII characters. For example, if the current codepage doesn’t have a glyph for the letter ‘ò’ (small ‘o’ with a grave accent), it is displayed as ‘{`o}’, where the braces serve as a visual indication that this is a single character. (This may look awkward for some non-Latin characters, such as those from Greek or Hebrew alphabets, but it is still readable by a person who knows the language.) Even though the character may occupy several columns on the screen, it is really still just a single character, and all Emacs commands treat it as one.

MS-Windows provides its own codepages, which are different from the DOS codepages for the same locale. For example, DOS codepage 850 supports the same character set as Windows codepage 1252; DOS codepage 855 supports the same character set as Windows codepage 1251, etc. The MS-Windows version of Emacs uses the current codepage for display when invoked with the ‘-nw’ option.

H.12.7 Subprocesses on MS-DOS

Because MS-DOS is a single-process “operating system”, asynchronous subprocesses are not available. In particular, Shell mode and its variants do not work. Most Emacs features that use asynchronous subprocesses also don’t work on MS-DOS, including Shell mode and GUD. When in doubt, try and see; commands that don’t work output an error message saying that asynchronous processes aren’t supported.

Compilation under Emacs with M-x compile, searching files with M-x grep and displaying differences between files with M-x diff do work, by running the inferior processes synchronously. This means you cannot do any more editing until the inferior process finishes.

Spell checking also works, by means of special support for synchronous invocation of the ispell program. This is slower than the asynchronous invocation on other platforms.

Instead of the Shell mode, which doesn’t work on MS-DOS, you can use the M-x eshell command. This invokes the Eshell package that implements a POSIX-like shell entirely in Emacs Lisp.

By contrast, Emacs compiled as a native Windows application does support asynchronous subprocesses. See Subprocesses on Windows 9X/ME and Windows NT/2K/XP/Vista/7/8/10.

Printing commands, such as lpr-buffer (see Printing Hard Copies) and ps-print-buffer (see PostScript Hardcopy), work in MS-DOS by sending the output to one of the printer ports. See Printing and MS-DOS.

When you run a subprocess synchronously on MS-DOS, make sure the program terminates and does not try to read keyboard input. If the program does not terminate on its own, you will be unable to terminate it, because MS-DOS provides no general way to terminate a process. Pressing C-c or C-Break might sometimes help in these cases.

Accessing files on other machines is not supported on MS-DOS. Other network-oriented commands such as sending mail, Web browsing, remote login, etc., don’t work either, unless network access is built into MS-DOS with some network redirector.

Dired on MS-DOS uses the ls-lisp package (see Emulation of ls on MS-Windows). Therefore, Dired on MS-DOS supports only some of the possible options you can mention in the dired-listing-switches variable. The options that work are ‘-A’, ‘-a’, ‘-c’, ‘-i’, ‘-r’, ‘-S’, ‘-s’, ‘-t’, and ‘-u’.

Footnotes

(27)

Older versions of Emacs didn’t check the application data directory.

(28)

There is one known exception: The combination Windows-L that locks the workstation is handled by the system on a lower level. For this reason, w32-register-hot-key cannot override this key combination - it always locks the computer.

(29)

Note that the ‘net use’ command requires the UNC share name to be typed with the Windows-style backslashes, while the value of printer-name can be set with either forward- or backslashes.

(30)

Normally, one particular codepage is burnt into the display memory, while other codepages can be installed by modifying system configuration files, such as CONFIG.SYS, and rebooting. While there is third-party software that allows changing the codepage without rebooting, we describe here how a stock MS-DOS system behaves.

(31)

The standard Emacs coding systems for ISO 8859 are not quite right for the purpose, because typically the DOS codepage does not match the standard ISO character codes. For example, the letter ‘ç’ (‘c’ with cedilla) has code 231 in the standard Latin-1 character set, but the corresponding DOS codepage 850 uses code 135 for this glyph.

9 The Minibuffer

The minibuffer is where Emacs commands read complicated arguments, such as file names, buffer names, Emacs command names, or Lisp expressions. We call it the “minibuffer” because it’s a special-purpose buffer with a small amount of screen space. You can use the usual Emacs editing commands in the minibuffer to edit the argument text.

9.1 Using the Minibuffer

When the minibuffer is in use, it appears in the echo area, with a cursor. The minibuffer starts with a prompt, usually ending with a colon. The prompt states what kind of input is expected, and how it will be used. The prompt is highlighted using the minibuffer-prompt face (see Text Faces).

The simplest way to enter a minibuffer argument is to type the text, then RET to submit the argument and exit the minibuffer. Alternatively, you can type C-g to exit the minibuffer by canceling the command asking for the argument (see Quitting and Aborting).

Sometimes, the prompt shows a default argument, inside parentheses before the colon. This default will be used as the argument if you just type RET. For example, commands that read buffer names usually show a buffer name as the default; you can type RET to operate on that default buffer. You can customize how the default argument is shown with the user option minibuffer-default-prompt-format.

If you enable Minibuffer Electric Default mode, a global minor mode, Emacs hides the default argument as soon as you modify the contents of the minibuffer (since typing RET would no longer submit that default). If you ever bring back the original minibuffer text, the prompt again shows the default. To enable this minor mode, type M-x minibuffer-electric-default-mode.

Since the minibuffer appears in the echo area, it can conflict with other uses of the echo area. If an error message or an informative message is emitted while the minibuffer is active, the message is displayed in brackets after the minibuffer text for a few seconds, or until you type something; then the message disappears. While the minibuffer is in use, Emacs does not echo keystrokes.

While using the minibuffer, you can switch to a different frame, perhaps to note text you need to enter (see Frame Commands). By default, the active minibuffer moves to this new frame. If you set the user option minibuffer-follows-selected-frame to nil, then the minibuffer stays in the frame where you opened it, and you must switch back to that frame in order to complete (or abort) the current command. If you set that option to a value which is neither nil nor t, the minibuffer moves frame only after a recursive minibuffer has been opened in the current command (see (elisp)Recursive Mini). This option is mainly to retain (approximately) the behavior prior to Emacs 28.1. Note that the effect of the command, when you finally finish using the minibuffer, always takes place in the frame where you first opened it. The sole exception is that when that frame no longer exists, the action takes place in the currently selected frame.

9.2 Minibuffers for File Names

Commands such as C-x C-f (find-file) use the minibuffer to read a file name argument (see Files). When the minibuffer is used to read a file name, it typically starts out with some initial text ending in a slash. This is the default directory. For example, it may start out like this:

Find file: /u2/emacs/src/

Here, ‘Find file: ’ is the prompt and ‘/u2/emacs/src/’ is the default directory. If you now type buffer.c as input, that specifies the file /u2/emacs/src/buffer.c. See File Names, for information about the default directory.

Alternative defaults for the file name you may want are available by typing M-n, see Minibuffer History.

You can specify a file in the parent directory with ..: /a/b/../foo.el is equivalent to /a/foo.el. Alternatively, you can use M-DEL to kill directory names backwards (see Words).

To specify a file in a completely different directory, you can kill the entire default with C-a C-k (see Editing in the Minibuffer). Alternatively, you can ignore the default, and enter an absolute file name starting with a slash or a tilde after the default directory. For example, you can specify /etc/termcap as follows:

Find file: /u2/emacs/src//etc/termcap

A double slash causes Emacs to ignore everything before the second slash in the pair. In the example above, /u2/emacs/src/ is ignored, so the argument you supplied is /etc/termcap. The ignored part of the file name is dimmed if the terminal allows it. (To disable this dimming, turn off File Name Shadow mode with the command M-x file-name-shadow-mode .)

When completing remote file names (see Remote Files), a double slash behaves slightly differently: it causes Emacs to ignore only the file-name part, leaving the rest (method, host and username, etc.) intact. Typing three slashes in a row ignores everything in remote file names. See File name completion in

The Tramp Manual

.

Emacs interprets ~/ as your home directory. Thus, ~/foo/bar.txt specifies a file named bar.txt, inside a directory named foo, which is in turn located in your home directory. In addition, ~user-id/ means the home directory of a user whose login name is user-id. Any leading directory name in front of the ~ is ignored: thus, /u2/emacs/~/foo/bar.txt is equivalent to ~/foo/bar.txt.

On MS-Windows and MS-DOS systems, where a user doesn’t always have a home directory, Emacs uses several alternatives. For MS-Windows, see HOME and Startup Directories on MS-Windows; for MS-DOS, see File Names on MS-DOS. On these systems, the ~user-id/ construct is supported only for the current user, i.e., only if user-id is the current user’s login name.

To prevent Emacs from inserting the default directory when reading file names, change the variable insert-default-directory to nil. In that case, the minibuffer starts out empty. Nonetheless, relative file name arguments are still interpreted based on the same default directory.

You can also enter remote file names in the minibuffer. See Remote Files.

9.3 Editing in the Minibuffer

The minibuffer is an Emacs buffer, albeit a peculiar one, and the usual Emacs commands are available for editing the argument text. (The prompt, however, is read-only, and cannot be changed.)

Since RET in the minibuffer submits the argument, you can’t use it to insert a newline. You can do that with C-q C-j, which inserts a C-j control character, which is formally equivalent to a newline character (see Inserting Text). Alternatively, you can use the C-o (open-line) command (see Blank Lines).

Inside a minibuffer, the keys TAB, SPC, and ? are often bound to completion commands, which allow you to easily fill in the desired text without typing all of it. See Completion. As with RET, you can use C-q to insert a TAB, SPC, or ‘?’ character. If you want to make SPC and ? insert normally instead of starting completion, you can put the following in your init file:

(keymap-unset minibuffer-local-completion-map "SPC")
(keymap-unset minibuffer-local-completion-map "?")

For convenience, C-a (move-beginning-of-line) in a minibuffer moves point to the beginning of the argument text, not the beginning of the prompt. For example, this allows you to erase the entire argument with C-a C-k.

When the minibuffer is active, the echo area is treated much like an ordinary Emacs window. For instance, you can switch to another window (with C-x o), edit text there, then return to the minibuffer window to finish the argument. You can even kill text in another window, return to the minibuffer window, and yank the text into the argument. There are some restrictions on the minibuffer window, however: for instance, you cannot split it. See Multiple Windows.

Normally, the minibuffer window occupies a single screen line. However, if you add two or more lines’ worth of text into the minibuffer, it expands automatically to accommodate the text. The variable resize-mini-windows controls the resizing of the minibuffer. The default value is grow-only, which means the behavior we have just described. If the value is t, the minibuffer window will also shrink automatically if you remove some lines of text from the minibuffer, down to a minimum of one screen line. If the value is nil, the minibuffer window never changes size automatically, but you can use the usual window-resizing commands on it (see Multiple Windows).

The variable max-mini-window-height controls the maximum height for resizing the minibuffer window. A floating-point number specifies a fraction of the frame’s height; an integer specifies the maximum number of lines; nil means do not resize the minibuffer window automatically. The default value is 0.25.

The C-M-v command in the minibuffer scrolls the help text from commands that display help text of any sort in another window. You can also scroll the help text with M-PageUp and M-PageDown (or, equivalently, M-prior and M-next). This is especially useful with long lists of possible completions. See Using Other Windows.

Emacs normally disallows most commands that use the minibuffer while the minibuffer is active. To allow such commands in the minibuffer, set the variable enable-recursive-minibuffers to t. You might need also to enable minibuffer-depth-indicate-mode to show the current recursion depth in the minibuffer prompt on recursive use of the minibuffer.

When active, the minibuffer is usually in minibuffer-mode. This is an internal Emacs mode without any special features.

When not active, the minibuffer is in minibuffer-inactive-mode, and clicking mouse-1 there shows the *Messages* buffer. If you use a dedicated frame for minibuffers, Emacs also recognizes certain keys there, for example, n to make a new frame.

9.4 Completion

You can often use a feature called completion to help enter arguments. This means that after you type part of the argument, Emacs can fill in the rest, or some of it, based on what was typed so far.

When completion is available, certain keys (usually TAB, RET, and SPC) are rebound in the minibuffer to special completion commands (see Completion Commands). These commands attempt to complete the text in the minibuffer, based on a set of completion alternatives provided by the command that requested the argument. You can usually type ? to see a list of completion alternatives.

Although completion is usually done in the minibuffer, the feature is sometimes available in ordinary buffers too. See Completion for Symbol Names.

9.4.1 Completion Example

A simple example may help here. M-x uses the minibuffer to read the name of a command, so completion works by matching the minibuffer text against the names of existing Emacs commands. Suppose you wish to run the command auto-fill-mode. You can do that by typing M-x auto-fill-mode RET, but it is easier to use completion.

If you type M-x a u TAB, the TAB looks for completion alternatives (in this case, command names) that start with ‘au’. There are several, including auto-fill-mode and autoconf-mode, but they all begin with auto, so the ‘au’ in the minibuffer completes to ‘auto’. (More commands may be defined in your Emacs session. For example, if a command called authorize-me was defined, Emacs could only complete as far as ‘aut’.)

If you type TAB again immediately, it cannot determine the next character; it could be ‘-’, ‘a’, or ‘c’. So it does not add any characters; instead, TAB displays a list of all possible completions in another window.

Next, type -f. The minibuffer now contains ‘auto-f’, and the only command name that starts with this is auto-fill-mode. If you now type TAB, completion fills in the rest of the argument ‘auto-fill-mode’ into the minibuffer.

Hence, typing just a u TAB - f TAB allows you to enter ‘auto-fill-mode’.

TAB also works while point is not at the end of the minibuffer. In that case, it will fill in text both at point and at the end of the minibuffer. If you type M-x autocm, then press C-b to move point before the ‘m’, you can type TAB to insert the text ‘onf-’ at point and ‘ode’ at the end of the minibuffer, so that the minibuffer contains ‘autoconf-mode’.

9.4.2 Completion Commands

Here is a list of the completion commands defined in the minibuffer when completion is allowed.

TAB

Complete the text in the minibuffer as much as possible; if unable to complete, display a list of possible completions (minibuffer-complete).

SPC

Complete up to one word from the minibuffer text before point (minibuffer-complete-word). This command is not available for arguments that often include spaces, such as file names.

RET

Submit the text in the minibuffer as the argument, possibly completing first (minibuffer-complete-and-exit). See Completion Exit.

?

Display a list of completions (minibuffer-completion-help).

TAB (minibuffer-complete) is the most fundamental completion command. It searches for all possible completions that match the existing minibuffer text, and attempts to complete as much as it can. See How Completion Alternatives Are Chosen, for how completion alternatives are chosen.

SPC (minibuffer-complete-word) completes like TAB, but only up to the next hyphen or space. If you have ‘auto-f’ in the minibuffer and type SPC, it finds that the completion is ‘auto-fill-mode’, but it only inserts ‘ill-’, giving ‘auto-fill-’. Another SPC at this point completes all the way to ‘auto-fill-mode’.

If TAB or SPC is unable to complete, it displays a list of matching completion alternatives (if there are any) in another window. You can display the same list with ? (minibuffer-completion-help). The following commands can be used with the completion list:

M-DOWN
M-UP

While in the minibuffer, M-DOWN (minibuffer-next-completion and M-UP (minibuffer-previous-completion) navigate through the completions and displayed in the completions buffer. When minibuffer-completion-auto-choose is non-nil (which is the default), using these commands also inserts the current completion candidate into the minibuffer. If minibuffer-completion-auto-choose is nil, you can use the M-RET command (minibuffer-choose-completion) to insert the completion candidates into the minibuffer. By default, that exits the minibuffer, but with a prefix argument, C-u M-RET inserts the currently active candidate without exiting the minibuffer.

M-v
PageUp
prior

Typing M-v, while in the minibuffer, selects the window showing the completion list (switch-to-completions). This paves the way for using the commands below. PageUp, prior and M-g M-c do the same. You can also select the window in other ways (see Multiple Windows).

RET
mouse-1
mouse-2

While in the completion list buffer, this chooses the completion at point (choose-completion). With a prefix argument, C-u RET inserts the completion at point into the minibuffer, but doesn’t exit the minibuffer—thus, you can change your mind and choose another candidate.

TAB
RIGHT
n

While in the completion list buffer, these keys move point to the following completion alternative (next-completion).

S-TAB
LEFT
p

While in the completion list buffer, these keys move point to the previous completion alternative (previous-completion).

q

While in the completion list buffer, this quits the window showing it and selects the window showing the minibuffer (quit-window).

z

While in the completion list buffer, kill it and delete the window showing it (kill-current-buffer).

9.4.3 Completion Exit

When a command reads an argument using the minibuffer with completion, it also controls what happens when you type RET (minibuffer-complete-and-exit) to submit the argument. There are four types of behavior:

Strict completion accepts only exact completion matches. Typing RET exits the minibuffer only if the minibuffer text is an exact match, or completes to one. Otherwise, Emacs refuses to exit the minibuffer; instead it tries to complete, and if no completion can be done it momentarily displays ‘[No match]’ after the minibuffer text. (You can still leave the minibuffer by typing C-g to cancel the command.)

An example of a command that uses this behavior is M-x, since it is meaningless for it to accept a non-existent command name.

Cautious completion is like strict completion, except RET exits only if the text is already an exact match. If the text completes to an exact match, RET performs that completion but does not exit yet; you must type a second RET to exit.

Cautious completion is used for reading file names for files that must already exist, for example.

Permissive completion allows any input; the completion candidates are just suggestions. Typing RET does not complete, it just submits the argument as you have entered it.
Permissive completion with confirmation is like permissive completion, with an exception: if you typed TAB and this completed the text up to some intermediate state (i.e., one that is not yet an exact completion match), typing RET right afterward does not submit the argument. Instead, Emacs asks for confirmation by momentarily displaying ‘[Confirm]’ after the text; type RET again to confirm and submit the text. This catches a common mistake, in which one types RET before realizing that TAB did not complete as far as desired.

You can tweak the confirmation behavior by customizing the variable confirm-nonexistent-file-or-buffer. The default value, after-completion, gives the behavior we have just described. If you change it to nil, Emacs does not ask for confirmation, falling back on permissive completion. If you change it to any other non-nil value, Emacs asks for confirmation whether or not the preceding command was TAB.

This behavior is used by most commands that read file names, like C-x C-f, and commands that read buffer names, like C-x b.

9.4.4 How Completion Alternatives Are Chosen

Completion commands work by narrowing a large list of possible completion alternatives to a smaller subset that matches what you have typed in the minibuffer. In Completion Example, we gave a simple example of such matching. The procedure of determining what constitutes a match is quite intricate. Emacs attempts to offer plausible completions under most circumstances.

Emacs performs completion using one or more completion styles—sets of criteria for matching minibuffer text to completion alternatives. During completion, Emacs tries each completion style in turn. If a style yields one or more matches, that is used as the list of completion alternatives. If a style produces no matches, Emacs falls back on the next style.

The list variable completion-styles specifies the completion styles to use. Each list element is the name of a completion style (a Lisp symbol). The available style symbols are stored in the variable completion-styles-alist (see Completion Variables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). The default completion styles are (in order):

basic

A matching completion alternative must have the same beginning as the text in the minibuffer before point. Furthermore, if there is any text in the minibuffer after point, the rest of the completion alternative must contain that text as a substring.

partial-completion

This aggressive completion style divides the minibuffer text into words separated by hyphens or spaces, and completes each word separately. (For example, when completing command names, ‘em-l-m’ completes to ‘emacs-lisp-mode’.)

Furthermore, a ‘*’ in the minibuffer text is treated as a wildcard—it matches any string of characters at the corresponding position in the completion alternative.

emacs22

This completion style is similar to basic, except that it ignores the text in the minibuffer after point. It is so-named because it corresponds to the completion behavior in Emacs 22.

The following additional completion styles are also defined, and you can add them to completion-styles if you wish (see Customization):

substring

A matching completion alternative must contain the text in the minibuffer before point, and the text in the minibuffer after point, as substrings (in that same order).

Thus, if the text in the minibuffer is ‘foobar’, with point between ‘foo’ and ‘bar’, that matches ‘afoobbarc’, where a, b, and c can be any string including the empty string.

flex

This aggressive completion style, also known as flx or fuzzy or scatter completion, attempts to complete using in-order substrings. For example, it can consider ‘foo’ to match ‘frodo’ or ‘fbarbazoo’.

initials

This very aggressive completion style attempts to complete acronyms and initialisms. For example, when completing command names, it matches ‘lch’ to ‘list-command-history’.

There is also a very simple completion style called emacs21. In this style, if the text in the minibuffer is ‘foobar’, only matches starting with ‘foobar’ are considered.

You can use different completion styles in different situations, by setting the variable completion-category-overrides. For example, the default setting says to use only basic and substring completion for buffer names.

9.4.5 Completion Options

Case is significant when completing case-sensitive arguments, such as command names. For example, when completing command names, ‘AU’ does not complete to ‘auto-fill-mode’. Case differences are ignored when completing arguments in which case does not matter.

When completing file names, case differences are ignored if the variable read-file-name-completion-ignore-case is non-nil. The default value is nil on systems that have case-sensitive file-names, such as GNU/Linux; it is non-nil on systems that have case-insensitive file-names, such as Microsoft Windows. When completing buffer names, case differences are ignored if the variable read-buffer-completion-ignore-case is non-nil; the default is nil.

When completing file names, Emacs usually omits certain alternatives that are considered unlikely to be chosen, as determined by the list variable completion-ignored-extensions. Each element in the list should be a string; any file name ending in such a string is ignored as a completion alternative. Any element ending in a slash (/) represents a subdirectory name. The standard value of completion-ignored-extensions has several elements including ".o", ".elc", and "~". For example, if a directory contains ‘foo.c’ and ‘foo.elc’, ‘foo’ completes to ‘foo.c’. However, if all possible completions end in otherwise-ignored strings, they are not ignored: in the previous example, ‘foo.e’ completes to ‘foo.elc’. Emacs disregards completion-ignored-extensions when showing completion alternatives in the completion list.

Shell completion is an extended version of filename completion, see Shell Mode Options.

If completion-auto-help is set to nil, the completion commands never display the completion list buffer; you must type ? to display the list. If the value is lazy, Emacs only shows the completion list buffer on the second attempt to complete. In other words, if there is nothing to complete, the first TAB echoes ‘Next char not unique’; the second TAB shows the completion list buffer. If the value is always, the completion list buffer is always shown when completion is attempted.

The display of the completion list buffer after it is shown for the first time is also controlled by completion-auto-help. If the value is t or lazy, the window showing the completions pops down when Emacs is able to complete (and may pop up again if Emacs is again unable to complete after you type some more text); if the value is always, the window pops down only when you exit the completion. The value visible is a hybrid: it behaves like t when it decides whether to pop up the window showing the completion list buffer, and like always when it decides whether to pop it down.

Emacs can optionally select the window showing the completions when it shows that window. To enable this behavior, customize the user option completion-auto-select to t, which changes the behavior of TAB when Emacs pops up the completions: pressing TAB will switch to the completion list buffer, and you can then move to a candidate by cursor motion commands and select it with RET. If the value of completion-auto-select is second-tab, then the first TAB will pop up the completions list buffer, and the second one will switch to it.

If completion-cycle-threshold is non-nil, completion commands can cycle through completion alternatives. Normally, if there is more than one completion alternative for the text in the minibuffer, a completion command completes up to the longest common substring. If you change completion-cycle-threshold to t, the completion command instead completes to the first of those completion alternatives; each subsequent invocation of the completion command replaces that with the next completion alternative, in a cyclic manner. If you give completion-cycle-threshold a numeric value n, completion commands switch to this cycling behavior only when there are n or fewer alternatives.

When displaying completions, Emacs will normally pop up a new buffer to display the completions. The completions will by default be sorted horizontally, using as many columns as will fit in the window-width, but this can be changed by customizing the completions-format user option. If its value is vertical, Emacs will sort the completions vertically instead, and if it’s one-column, Emacs will use just one column.

The completions-sort user option controls the order in which the completions are sorted in the ‘*Completions*’ buffer. The default is alphabetical, which sorts in alphabetical order. The value nil disables sorting. The value can also be a function, which will be called with the list of completions, and should return the list in the desired order.

When completions-max-height is non-nil, it limits the size of the completions window. It is specified in lines and include mode, header line and a bottom divider, if any. For a more complex control of the Completion window display properties, you can use display-buffer-alist (see Action Alists for Buffer Display in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

The variable completions-header-format is a format spec string to control the informative line shown before the completions list of candidates. If it contains a ‘%s’ construct, that get replaced by the number of completions shown in the completion list buffer. To suppress the display of the heading line, customize this variable to nil. The string that is the value of this variable can have text properties to change the visual appearance of the heading line; some useful properties face or cursor-intangible (see Properties with Special Meanings in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

When completions-highlight-face names a face, the current completion candidate, the one that will be selected by typing RET or clicking the mouse, will be highlighted using that face. The default value of this variable is completions-highlight; the value is nil disables this highlighting. This feature uses the special text property cursor-face.

9.5 Minibuffer History

Everything you type in the minibuffer is saved in a minibuffer history list so you can easily use it again later. This includes completion candidates (such as file names, buffer names, command names, etc.) and any other kind of minibuffer input. You can use the following commands to quickly fetch an earlier or alternative response into the minibuffer:

M-p

Move to the previous item in the minibuffer history, an earlier argument (previous-history-element).

M-n

Move to the next item in the minibuffer history (next-history-element).

UP
DOWN

Like M-p and M-n, but move to the previous or next line of a multi-line item before going to the previous history item (previous-line-or-history-element and next-line-or-history-element) .

M-r regexp RET

Move to an earlier item in the minibuffer history that matches regexp (previous-matching-history-element).

M-s regexp RET

Move to a later item in the minibuffer history that matches regexp (next-matching-history-element).

While in the minibuffer, M-p (previous-history-element) moves through the minibuffer history list, one item at a time. Each M-p fetches an earlier item from the history list into the minibuffer, replacing its existing contents. Typing M-n (next-history-element) moves through the minibuffer history list in the opposite direction, fetching later entries into the minibuffer.

If you type M-n in the minibuffer when there are no later entries in the minibuffer history (e.g., if you haven’t previously typed M-p), Emacs tries fetching from a list of default arguments: values that you are likely to enter. You can think of this as moving through the “future history”.

The “future history” for file names includes several possible alternatives you may find useful, such as the file name or the URL at point in the current buffer. The defaults put into the “future history” in this case are controlled by the functions mentioned in the value of the option file-name-at-point-functions. By default, its value invokes the ffap package (see Finding Files and URLs at Point), which tries to guess the default file or URL from the text around point. To disable this guessing, customize the option to a nil value, then the “future history” of file names will include only the file, if any, visited by the current buffer, and the default directory.

The arrow keys UP and DOWN work like M-p and M-n, but if the current history item is longer than a single line, they allow you to move to the previous or next line of the current history item before going to the previous or next history item.

If you edit the text inserted by the M-p or M-n minibuffer history commands, this does not change its entry in the history list. However, the edited argument does go at the end of the history list when you submit it.

You can use M-r (previous-matching-history-element) to search through older elements in the history list, and M-s (next-matching-history-element) to search through newer entries. Each of these commands asks for a regular expression as an argument, and fetches the first matching entry into the minibuffer. See Syntax of Regular Expressions, for an explanation of regular expressions. A numeric prefix argument n means to fetch the nth matching entry. These commands are unusual, in that they use the minibuffer to read the regular expression argument, even though they are invoked from the minibuffer. An upper-case letter in the regular expression makes the search case-sensitive (see Lax Matching During Searching).

You can also search through the history using an incremental search. See Searching the Minibuffer.

Emacs keeps separate history lists for several different kinds of arguments. For example, there is a list for file names, used by all the commands that read file names. Other history lists include buffer names, command names (used by M-x), and command arguments (used by commands like query-replace).

The variable history-length specifies the maximum length of a minibuffer history list; adding a new element deletes the oldest element if the list gets too long. If the value is t, there is no maximum length.

The variable history-delete-duplicates specifies whether to delete duplicates in history. If it is non-nil, adding a new element deletes from the list all other elements that are equal to it. The default is nil.

9.6 Repeating Minibuffer Commands

Every command that uses the minibuffer once is recorded on a special history list, the command history, together with the values of its arguments, so that you can repeat the entire command. In particular, every use of M-x is recorded there, since M-x uses the minibuffer to read the command name.

C-x ESC ESC

Re-execute a recent minibuffer command from the command history (repeat-complex-command).

M-x list-command-history

Display the entire command history, showing all the commands C-x ESC ESC can repeat, most recent first.

C-x ESC ESC re-executes a recent command that used the minibuffer. With no argument, it repeats the last such command. A numeric argument specifies which command to repeat; 1 means the last one, 2 the previous, and so on.

C-x ESC ESC works by turning the previous command into a Lisp expression and then entering a minibuffer initialized with the text for that expression. Even if you don’t know Lisp, it will probably be obvious which command is displayed for repetition. If you type just RET, that repeats the command unchanged. You can also change the command by editing the Lisp expression before you execute it. The executed command is added to the front of the command history unless it is identical to the most recent item.

Once inside the minibuffer for C-x ESC ESC, you can use the usual minibuffer history commands (see Minibuffer History) to move through the history list. After finding the desired previous command, you can edit its expression as usual and then execute it by typing RET.

Incremental search does not, strictly speaking, use the minibuffer. Therefore, although it behaves like a complex command, it normally does not appear in the history list for C-x ESC ESC . You can make incremental search commands appear in the history by setting isearch-resume-in-command-history to a non-nil value. See Incremental Search.

The list of previous minibuffer-using commands is stored as a Lisp list in the variable command-history. Each element is a Lisp expression that describes one command and its arguments. Lisp programs can re-execute a command by calling eval with the command-history element.

9.7 Entering passwords

Sometimes, you may need to enter a password into Emacs. For instance, when you tell Emacs to visit a file on another machine via a network protocol such as FTP, you often need to supply a password to gain access to the machine (see Remote Files).

Entering a password is similar to using a minibuffer. Emacs displays a prompt in the echo area (such as ‘Password: ’); after you type the required password, press RET to submit it. To prevent others from seeing your password, every character you type is displayed as an asterisk (‘*’) instead of its usual form.

Most of the features and commands associated with the minibuffer cannot be used when entering a password. There is no history or completion, and you cannot change windows or perform any other action with Emacs until you have submitted the password.

While you are typing the password, you may press DEL to delete backwards, removing the last character entered. C-u deletes everything you have typed so far. C-g quits the password prompt (see Quitting and Aborting). C-y inserts the current kill into the password (see Killing and Moving Text). You may type either RET or ESC to submit the password. Any other self-inserting character key inserts the associated character into the password, and all other input is ignored.

9.8 Yes or No Prompts

An Emacs command may require you to answer a yes-or-no question during the course of its execution. Such queries come in two main varieties.

For the first type of yes-or-no query, the prompt ends with ‘(y or n)’ . You answer the query by typing a single key, either ‘y’ or ‘n’, which immediately exits the minibuffer and delivers the response. For example, if you type C-x C-w (write-file) to save a buffer, and enter the name of an existing file, Emacs issues a prompt like this:

File ‘foo.el’ exists; overwrite? (y or n)

The second type of yes-or-no query is typically employed if giving the wrong answer would have serious consequences; it thus features a longer prompt ending with ‘(yes or no)’. For example, if you invoke C-x k (kill-buffer) on a file-visiting buffer with unsaved changes, Emacs activates the minibuffer with a prompt like this:

Buffer foo.el modified; kill anyway? (yes or no)

To answer, you must type ‘yes’ or ‘no’ into the minibuffer, followed by RET.

With both types of yes-or-no query the minibuffer behaves as described in the previous sections; you can recenter the selected window with C-l, scroll that window (C-v or PageDown scrolls forward, M-v or PageUp scrolls backward), switch to another window with C-x o, use the history commands M-p and M-n, etc. Type C-g to dismiss the query, and quit the minibuffer and the querying command (see Quitting and Aborting).

24 Major and Minor Modes

Emacs contains many editing modes that alter its basic behavior in useful ways. These are divided into major modes and minor modes.

Major modes provide specialized facilities for working on a particular file type, such as a C source file (see Editing Programs), or a particular type of non-file buffer, such as a shell buffer (see Running Shell Commands from Emacs). Major modes are mutually exclusive; each buffer has one and only one major mode at any time.

Minor modes are optional features which you can turn on or off, not necessarily specific to a type of file or buffer. For example, Auto Fill mode is a minor mode in which SPC breaks lines between words as you type (see Auto Fill Mode). Minor modes are independent of one another, and of the selected major mode.

24.1 Major Modes

Every buffer possesses a major mode, which determines the editing behavior of Emacs while that buffer is current. The mode line normally shows the name of the current major mode, in parentheses (see The Mode Line).

The least specialized major mode is called Fundamental mode. This mode has no mode-specific redefinitions or variable settings, so that each Emacs command behaves in its most general manner, and each user option variable is in its default state.

For editing text of a specific type that Emacs knows about, such as Lisp code or English text, you typically use a more specialized major mode, such as Lisp mode or Text mode. Most major modes fall into three major groups. The first group contains modes for normal text, either plain or with mark-up. It includes Text mode, HTML mode, SGML mode, TeX mode and Outline mode. The second group contains modes for specific programming languages. These include Lisp mode (which has several variants), C mode, Fortran mode, and others. The third group consists of major modes that are not associated directly with files; they are used in buffers created for specific purposes by Emacs. Examples include Dired mode for buffers made by Dired (see Dired, the Directory Editor), Message mode for buffers made by C-x m (see Sending Mail), and Shell mode for buffers used to communicate with an inferior shell process (see Interactive Subshell).

Usually, the major mode is automatically set by Emacs, when you first visit a file or create a buffer (see Choosing File Modes). You can explicitly select a new major mode by using an M-x command. Take the name of the mode and add -mode to get the name of the command to select that mode (e.g., M-x lisp-mode enters Lisp mode). Since every buffer has exactly one major mode, there is no way to “turn off” a major mode; instead you must switch to a different one.

The value of the buffer-local variable major-mode is a symbol with the same name as the major mode command (e.g., lisp-mode). This variable is set automatically; you should not change it yourself.

The default value of major-mode determines the major mode to use for files that do not specify a major mode, and for new buffers created with C-x b. Normally, this default value is the symbol fundamental-mode, which specifies Fundamental mode. You can change this default value via the Customization interface (see Easy Customization Interface), or by adding a line like this to your init file (see The Emacs Initialization File):

(setq-default major-mode 'text-mode)

If the default value of major-mode is nil, the major mode is taken from the previously current buffer.

Specialized major modes often change the meanings of certain keys to do something more suitable for the mode. For instance, programming language modes bind TAB to indent the current line according to the rules of the language (see Indentation). The keys that are commonly changed are TAB, DEL, and C-j. Many modes also define special commands of their own, usually bound to key sequences whose prefix key is C-c (see Keys). Major modes can also alter user options and variables; for instance, programming language modes typically set a buffer-local value for the variable comment-start, which determines how source code comments are delimited (see Manipulating Comments).

To view the documentation for the current major mode, including a list of its key bindings, type C-h m (describe-mode). See Other Help Commands.

Every major mode, apart from Fundamental mode, defines a mode hook, a customizable list of Lisp functions to run each time the mode is enabled in a buffer. See Hooks, for more information about hooks. Each mode hook is named after its major mode, e.g., Fortran mode has fortran-mode-hook. Furthermore, all text-based major modes run text-mode-hook, and many programming language modes ^10 (including all those distributed with Emacs) run prog-mode-hook, prior to running their own mode hooks. Hook functions can look at the value of the variable major-mode to see which mode is actually being entered.

Mode hooks are commonly used to enable minor modes (see Minor Modes). For example, you can put the following lines in your init file to enable Flyspell minor mode in all text-based major modes (see Checking and Correcting Spelling), and ElDoc minor mode in Emacs Lisp mode (see Programming Language Documentation Lookup):

(add-hook 'text-mode-hook 'flyspell-mode)
(add-hook 'emacs-lisp-mode-hook 'eldoc-mode)

24.2 Minor Modes

A minor mode is an optional editing mode that alters the behavior of Emacs in some well-defined way. Unlike major modes, any number of minor modes can be in effect at any time. Some minor modes are buffer-local, and can be turned on (enabled) in certain buffers and off (disabled) in others. Other minor modes are global: while enabled, they affect everything you do in the Emacs session, in all buffers. Most minor modes are disabled by default, but a few are enabled by default.

Most buffer-local minor modes say in the mode line when they are enabled, just after the major mode indicator. For example, ‘Fill’ in the mode line means that Auto Fill mode is enabled. See The Mode Line.

Like major modes, each minor mode is associated with a mode command, whose name consists of the mode name followed by ‘-mode’. For instance, the mode command for Auto Fill mode is auto-fill-mode. But unlike a major mode command, which simply enables the mode, the mode command for a minor mode can either enable or disable it:

If you invoke the mode command directly with no prefix argument (either via M-x, or by binding it to a key and typing that key; see Customizing Key Bindings), that toggles the minor mode. The minor mode is turned on if it was off, and turned off if it was on.
If you invoke the mode command with a prefix argument, the minor mode is unconditionally turned off if that argument is zero or negative; otherwise, it is unconditionally turned on.
If the mode command is called via Lisp, the minor mode is unconditionally turned on if the argument is omitted or nil. This makes it easy to turn on a minor mode from a major mode’s mode hook (see Major Modes). A non-nil argument is handled like an interactive prefix argument, as described above.

Most minor modes also have a mode variable, with the same name as the mode command. Its value is non-nil if the mode is enabled, and nil if it is disabled. In general, you should not try to enable or disable the mode by changing the value of the mode variable directly in Lisp; you should run the mode command instead. However, setting the mode variable through the Customize interface (see Easy Customization Interface) will always properly enable or disable the mode, since Customize automatically runs the mode command for you.

The following is a list of some buffer-local minor modes:

Abbrev mode automatically expands text based on pre-defined abbreviation definitions. See Abbrevs.
Auto Fill mode inserts newlines as you type to prevent lines from becoming too long. See Filling Text.
Auto Save mode saves the buffer contents periodically to reduce the amount of work you can lose in case of a crash. See Auto-Saving: Protection Against Disasters.
Electric Quote mode automatically converts quotation marks. For example, it requotes text typed `like this' to text ‘like this’. You can control what kind of text it operates in, and you can disable it entirely in individual buffers. See Quotation Marks.
Enriched mode enables editing and saving of formatted text. See Enriched Text.
Flyspell mode automatically highlights misspelled words. See Checking and Correcting Spelling.
Font-Lock mode automatically highlights certain textual units found in programs. It is enabled globally by default, but you can disable it in individual buffers. See Text Faces.
Display Line Numbers mode is a convenience wrapper around display-line-numbers, setting it using the value of display-line-numbers-type. See Customization of Display.
Outline minor mode provides similar facilities to the major mode called Outline mode. See Outline Mode.
Overwrite mode causes ordinary printing characters to replace existing text instead of shoving it to the right. For example, if point is in front of the ‘B’ in ‘FOOBAR’, then in Overwrite mode typing a G changes it to ‘FOOGAR’, instead of producing ‘FOOGBAR’ as usual. In Overwrite mode, the command C-q inserts the next character whatever it may be, even if it is a digit—this gives you a way to insert a character instead of replacing an existing character. The mode command, overwrite-mode, is bound to the Insert key.
Binary Overwrite mode is a variant of Overwrite mode for editing binary files; it treats newlines and tabs like other characters, so that they overwrite other characters and can be overwritten by them. In Binary Overwrite mode, digits after C-q specify an octal character code, as usual.
Visual Line mode performs word wrapping, causing long lines to be wrapped at word boundaries. See Visual Line Mode.

And here are some useful global minor modes:

Column Number mode enables display of the current column number in the mode line. See The Mode Line.
Delete Selection mode causes text insertion to first delete the text in the region, if the region is active. See Operating on the Region.
Icomplete mode displays an indication of available completions when you are in the minibuffer and completion is active. See Fast minibuffer selection.
Line Number mode enables display of the current line number in the mode line. It is enabled by default. See The Mode Line.
Menu Bar mode gives each frame a menu bar. It is enabled by default. See Menu Bars.
Scroll Bar mode gives each window a scroll bar. It is enabled by default, but the scroll bar is only displayed on graphical terminals. See Scroll Bars.
Tool Bar mode gives each frame a tool bar. It is enabled by default, but the tool bar is only displayed on graphical terminals. See Tool Bars.
Tab Bar mode gives each frame a tab bar. See Tab Bars.
Tab Line mode gives each window a tab line. See Window Tab Line.
Transient Mark mode highlights the region, and makes many Emacs commands operate on the region when the mark is active. It is enabled by default. See The Mark and the Region.

24.3 Choosing File Modes

When you visit a file, Emacs chooses a major mode automatically. Normally, it makes the choice based on the file name—for example, files whose names end in ‘.c’ are normally edited in C mode—but sometimes it chooses the major mode based on special text in the file. This special text can also be used to enable buffer-local minor modes.

Here is the exact procedure:

First, Emacs checks whether the file contains file-local mode variables. See Local Variables in Files. If there is a file-local variable that specifies a major mode, then Emacs uses that major mode, ignoring all other criteria. There are several methods to specify a major mode using a file-local variable; the simplest is to put the mode name in the first nonblank line, preceded and followed by ‘-*-’. Other text may appear on the line as well. For example,

; -*-Lisp-*-

tells Emacs to use Lisp mode. Note how the semicolon is used to make Lisp treat this line as a comment. You could equivalently write

; -*- mode: Lisp;-*-

You can also use file-local variables to specify buffer-local minor modes, by using eval specifications. For example, this first nonblank line puts the buffer in Lisp mode and enables Auto-Fill mode:

; -*- mode: Lisp; eval: (auto-fill-mode 1); -*-

Note, however, that it is usually inappropriate to enable minor modes this way, since most minor modes represent individual user preferences. If you personally want to use a minor mode for a particular file type, it is better to enable the minor mode via a major mode hook (see Major Modes).

Second, Emacs checks whether the file’s extension matches an entry in any directory-local auto-mode-alist. These are found using the .dir-locals.el facility (see Per-Directory Local Variables).

Third, if there is no file variable specifying a major mode, Emacs checks whether the file’s contents begin with ‘#!’. If so, that indicates that the file can serve as an executable shell command, which works by running an interpreter named on the file’s first line (the rest of the file is used as input to the interpreter). Therefore, Emacs tries to use the interpreter name to choose a mode. For instance, a file that begins with ‘#!/usr/bin/perl’ is opened in Perl mode. The variable interpreter-mode-alist specifies the correspondence between interpreter program names and major modes.

When the first line starts with ‘#!’, you usually cannot use the ‘-*-’ feature on the first line, because the system would get confused when running the interpreter. So Emacs looks for ‘-*-’ on the second line in such files as well as on the first line. The same is true for man pages which start with the magic string ‘'\"’ to specify a list of troff preprocessors.

Fourth, Emacs tries to determine the major mode by looking at the text at the start of the buffer, based on the variable magic-mode-alist. By default, this variable is nil (an empty list), so Emacs skips this step; however, you can customize it in your init file (see The Emacs Initialization File). The value should be a list of elements of the form

(regexp . mode-function)

where regexp is a regular expression (see Syntax of Regular Expressions), and mode-function is a major mode command. If the text at the beginning of the file matches regexp, Emacs chooses the major mode specified by mode-function.

Alternatively, an element of magic-mode-alist may have the form

(match-function . mode-function)

where match-function is a Lisp function that is called at the beginning of the buffer; if the function returns non-nil, Emacs set the major mode with mode-function.

Fifth—if Emacs still hasn’t found a suitable major mode—it looks at the file’s name. The correspondence between file names and major modes is controlled by the variable auto-mode-alist. Its value is a list in which each element has this form,

(regexp . mode-function)

or this form,

(regexp mode-function flag)

For example, one element normally found in the list has the form ("\\.c\\'" . c-mode), and it is responsible for selecting C mode for files whose names end in .c. (Note that ‘\\’ is needed in Lisp syntax to include a ‘\’ in the string, which must be used to suppress the special meaning of ‘.’ in regexps.)

If the element has the form (regexp mode-function flag) and flag is non-nil, then after calling mode-function (if it is non-nil), Emacs discards the suffix that matched regexp and searches the list again for another match. This “recursive extension stripping” is used for files which have multiple extensions, and the “outer” extension hides the “inner” one that actually specifies the right mode. For example, backup files and GPG-encrypted files with .gpg extension use this feature.

On GNU/Linux and other systems with case-sensitive file names, Emacs performs a case-sensitive search through auto-mode-alist; if this search fails, it performs a second case-insensitive search through the alist. To suppress the second search, change the variable auto-mode-case-fold to nil. On systems with case-insensitive file names, such as Microsoft Windows, Emacs performs a single case-insensitive search through auto-mode-alist.

Finally, if Emacs still hasn’t found a major mode to use, it compares the text at the start of the buffer to the variable magic-fallback-mode-alist. This variable works like magic-mode-alist, described above, except that it is consulted only after auto-mode-alist. By default, magic-fallback-mode-alist contains forms that check for image files, HTML/XML/SGML files, PostScript files, and Unix style Conf files.

Once a major mode is found, Emacs does a final check to see if the mode has been remapped by major-mode-remap-alist, in which case it uses the remapped mode instead. This is used when several different major modes can be used for the same file type, so you can specify which mode you prefer.

If you have changed the major mode of a buffer, you can return to the major mode Emacs would have chosen automatically, by typing M-x normal-mode. This is the same function that find-file calls to choose the major mode. If the buffer is visiting a file, this command also processes the file’s ‘-*-’ line and file-local variables list (if any). See Local Variables in Files. If the buffer doesn’t visit a file, the command processes only the major mode specification, if any, in the ‘-*-’ line and in the file-local variables list.

The commands C-x C-w and set-visited-file-name change to a new major mode if the new file name implies a mode (see Saving Files). (C-x C-s does this too, if the buffer wasn’t visiting a file.) However, this does not happen if the buffer contents specify a major mode, and certain special major modes do not allow the mode to change. You can turn off this mode-changing feature by setting change-major-mode-with-file-name to nil.

Footnotes

(10)

More specifically, the modes which are “derived” from prog-mode (see Derived Modes in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

37 Network Security

Whenever Emacs establishes any network connection, it passes the established connection to the Network Security Manager (NSM). NSM is responsible for enforcing the network security under your control. Currently, this works by using the Transport Layer Security (TLS) features.

The network-security-level variable determines the security level that NSM enforces. If its value is low, no security checks are performed. This is not recommended, and will basically mean that your network connections can’t be trusted. However, the setting can be useful in limited circumstances, as when testing network issues.

If this variable is medium (which is the default), a number of checks will be performed. If as result NSM determines that the network connection might not be trustworthy, it will make you aware of that, and will ask you what to do about the network connection.

You can decide to register a permanent security exception for an unverified connection, a temporary exception, or refuse the connection entirely.

In addition to the basic certificate correctness checks, several TLS algorithm checks are available. Some encryption technologies that were previously thought to be secure have shown themselves to be fragile, so Emacs (by default) warns you about some of these problems.

The protocol network checks is controlled via the network-security-protocol-checks variable.

It’s an alist where the first element of each association is the name of the check, and the second element is the security level where the check should be used.

An element like (rc4 medium) will result in the function nsm-protocol-check--rc4 being called like thus: (nsm-protocol-check--rc4 host port status settings) . The function should return non-nil if the connection should proceed and nil otherwise.

Below is a list of the checks done on the default medium level.

unable to verify a TLS certificate

If the connection is a TLS, SSL or STARTTLS connection, NSM will check whether the certificate used to establish the identity of the server we’re connecting to can be verified.

While an invalid certificate is often the cause for concern (there could be a Man-in-the-Middle hijacking your network connection and stealing your password), there may be valid reasons for going ahead with the connection anyway. For instance, the server may be using a self-signed certificate, or the certificate may have expired. It’s up to you to determine whether it’s acceptable to continue with the connection.

a self-signed certificate has changed

If you’ve previously accepted a self-signed certificate, but it has now changed, that could mean that the server has just changed the certificate, but it might also mean that the network connection has been hijacked.

previously encrypted connection now unencrypted

If the connection is unencrypted, but it was encrypted in previous sessions, this might mean that there is a proxy between you and the server that strips away STARTTLS announcements, leaving the connection unencrypted. This is usually very suspicious.

talking to an unencrypted service when sending a password

When connecting to an IMAP or POP3 server, these should usually be encrypted, because it’s common to send passwords over these connections. Similarly, if you’re sending email via SMTP that requires a password, you usually want that connection to be encrypted. If the connection isn’t encrypted, NSM will warn you.

Diffie-Hellman low prime bits

When doing the public key exchange, the number of prime bits should be high enough to ensure that the channel can’t be eavesdropped on by third parties. If this number is too low, Emacs will warn you. (This is the diffie-hellman-prime-bits check in network-security-protocol-checks).

RC4 stream cipher

The RC4 stream cipher is believed to be of low quality and may allow eavesdropping by third parties. (This is the rc4 check in network-security-protocol-checks).

SHA1 in the host certificate or in intermediate certificates

It is believed that if an intermediate certificate uses the SHA1 hashing algorithm, then third parties can issue certificates pretending to be that issuing instance. These connections are therefore vulnerable to man-in-the-middle attacks. (These are the signature-sha1 and intermediate-sha1 checks in network-security-protocol-checks).

SSL1, SSL2 and SSL3

The protocols older than TLS1.0 are believed to be vulnerable to a variety of attacks, and you may want to avoid using these if what you’re doing requires higher security. (This is the ssl check in network-security-protocol-checks).

If network-security-level is high, the following checks will be made, in addition to the above:

3DES cipher

The 3DES stream cipher provides at most 112 bits of effective security, which is considered to be towards the low end. (This is the 3des check in network-security-protocol-checks).

a validated certificate changes the public key

Servers change their keys occasionally, and that is normally nothing to be concerned about. However, if you are worried that your network connections are being hijacked by agencies who have access to pliable Certificate Authorities which issue new certificates for third-party services, you may want to keep track of these changes.

Finally, if network-security-level is paranoid, you will also be notified the first time NSM sees any new certificate. This will allow you to inspect all the certificates from all the connections that Emacs makes.

The following additional variables can be used to control details of NSM operation:

nsm-settings-file

This is the file where NSM stores details about connections. It defaults to ~/.emacs.d/network-security.data.

nsm-save-host-names

By default, host names will not be saved for non-STARTTLS connections. Instead a host/port hash is used to identify connections. This means that one can’t casually read the settings file to see what servers the user has connected to. If this variable is t, NSM will also save host names in the nsm-settings-file.

49 Emacs Lisp Packages

Emacs is extended by implementing additional features in packages, which are Emacs Lisp libraries. These could be written by you or provided by someone else. If you want to install such a package so it is available in your future Emacs session, you need to compile it and put it in a directory where Emacs looks for Lisp libraries. See Libraries of Lisp Code for Emacs, for more details about this manual installation method. Many packages provide installation and usage instructions in the large commentary near the beginning of the Lisp file; you can use those instructions for installing and fine-tuning your use of the package.

Packages can also be provided by package archives, which are large collections of Emacs Lisp packages. Each package is a separate Emacs Lisp program, sometimes including other components such as an Info manual. Emacs includes a facility that lets you easily download and install packages from such archives. The rest of this chapter describes this facility.

To list the packages available for installation from package archives, type M-x list-packages RET . It brings up a buffer named *Packages* with a list of all packages. You can install or uninstall packages via this buffer. See The Package Menu Buffer.

The command C-h P (describe-package) prompts for the name of a package, and displays a help buffer describing the attributes of the package and the features that it implements.

By default, Emacs downloads packages from a package archive maintained by the Emacs developers and hosted by the GNU project. Optionally, you can also download packages from archives maintained by third parties. See Package Installation.

For information about turning an Emacs Lisp program into an installable package, See Packaging in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

49.1 The Package Menu Buffer

The command M-x list-packages brings up the package menu. This is a buffer listing all the packages that Emacs knows about, one on each line, with the following information:

The package name (e.g., ‘auctex’).
The package’s version number (e.g., ‘11.86’).
The package’s status—normally one of ‘available’ (can be downloaded from the package archive), ‘installed’, or ‘built-in’ (included in Emacs by default). See Package Statuses.
Which package archive this package is from, if you have more than one package archive enabled.
A short description of the package.

The list-packages command accesses the network, to retrieve the list of available packages from package archive servers. If the network is unavailable, it falls back on the most recently retrieved list.

The main command to use in the package list buffer is the x command. If the package under point isn’t installed already, this command will install it. If the package under point is already installed, this command will delete it.

The following commands are available in the package menu:

h

Print a short message summarizing how to use the package menu (package-menu-quick-help).

?
RET

Display a help buffer for the package on the current line (package-menu-describe-package), similar to the help window displayed by the C-h P command (see Emacs Lisp Packages).

i

Mark the package on the current line for installation (package-menu-mark-install). If the package status is ‘available’, this adds an ‘I’ character to the start of the line; typing x (see below) will download and install the package.

d

Mark the package on the current line for deletion (package-menu-mark-delete). If the package status is ‘installed’, this adds a ‘D’ character to the start of the line; typing x (see below) will delete the package. See Package Files and Directory Layout, for information about what package deletion entails.

w

Open the package website on the current line in a browser (package-browse-url). browse-url is used to open the browser.

~

Mark all obsolete packages for deletion (package-menu-mark-obsolete-for-deletion). This marks for deletion all the packages whose status is ‘obsolete’.

u
DEL

Remove any installation or deletion mark previously added to the current line by an i or d command (package-menu-mark-unmark).

U

Mark all package with a newer available version for upgrading (package-menu-mark-upgrades). This places an installation mark on the new available versions, and a deletion mark on the old installed versions (marked with status ‘obsolete’). By default, this won’t mark built-in packages for which a newer version is available, but customizing package-install-upgrade-built-in can change that. See Package Installation. If you customize package-install-upgrade-built-in to a non-nil value, be sure to review all the built-in packages the U command marks, to avoid updating built-in packages you don’t want to overwrite.

x

Download and install all packages marked with i, and their dependencies; also, delete all packages marked with d (package-menu-execute). This also removes the marks. If no packages are marked, this command will install the package under point (if it isn’t installed already), or delete the package under point (if it’s already installed).

g
r

Refresh the package list (revert-buffer). This fetches the list of available packages from the package archive again, and redisplays the package list.

H

Hide packages whose names match a regexp (package-menu-hide-package). This prompts for a regexp, and then hides the packages with matching names. The default value of the regexp will hide only the package whose name is at point, so just pressing RET to the prompt will hide the current package.

(

Toggle visibility of old versions of packages and also of versions from lower-priority archives (package-menu-toggle-hiding).

/ a

Filter package list by archive (package-menu-filter-by-archive). This prompts for a package archive (e.g., ‘gnu’), then shows only packages from that archive. You can specify several archives by typing their names separated by commas.

/ d

Filter package list by description (package-menu-filter-by-description). This prompts for a regular expression, then shows only packages with descriptions matching that regexp.

/ k

Filter package list by keyword (package-menu-filter-by-keyword). This prompts for a keyword (e.g., ‘games’), then shows only packages with that keyword. You can specify several keywords by typing them separated by commas.

/ N

Filter package list by name or description (package-menu-filter-by-name-or-description). This prompts for a regular expression, then shows only packages with a name or description matching that regexp.

/ n

Filter package list by name (package-menu-filter-by-name). This prompts for a regular expression, then shows only packages with names matching that regexp.

/ s

Filter package list by status (package-menu-filter-by-status). This prompts for one or more statuses (e.g., ‘available’, see Package Statuses), then shows only packages with matching status. You can specify several status values by typing them separated by commas.

/ v

Filter package list by version (package-menu-filter-by-version). This prompts first for one of the comparison symbols ‘<’, ‘>’ or ‘=’ and for a version string, and then shows packages whose versions are correspondingly lower, equal or higher than the version you typed.

/ m

Filter package list by non-empty mark (package-menu-filter-marked). This shows only the packages that have been marked to be installed or deleted.

/ u

Filter package list to show only packages for which there are available upgrades (package-menu-filter-upgradable). By default, this filter excludes the built-in packages for which a newer version is available, but customizing package-install-upgrade-built-in can change that. See Package Installation.

/ /

Clear filter currently applied to the package list (package-menu-filter-clear).

For example, you can install a package by typing i on the line listing that package, followed by x.

49.2 Package Statuses

A package can have one of the following statuses:

‘available’

The package is not installed, but can be downloaded and installed from the package archive.

‘avail-obso’

The package is available for installation, but a newer version is also available. Packages with this status are hidden by default.

‘built-in’

The package is included in Emacs by default. It cannot be deleted through the package menu, and by default is not considered for upgrading (but you can change that by customizing package-install-upgrade-built-in, see Package Installation).

‘dependency’

The package was installed automatically to satisfy a dependency of another package.

‘disabled’

The package has been disabled using the package-load-list variable.

‘external’

The package is not built-in and not from the directory specified by package-user-dir (see Package Files and Directory Layout). External packages are treated much like ‘built-in’ packages and cannot be deleted.

‘held’

The package is held, See Package Installation.

‘incompat’

The package cannot be installed for some reason, for example because it depends on uninstallable packages.

‘installed’

The package is installed.

‘new’

Equivalent to ‘available’, except that the package became newly available on the package archive after your last invocation of M-x list-packages.

‘obsolete’

The package is an outdated installed version; in addition to this version of the package, a newer version is also installed.

49.3 Package Installation

Packages are most conveniently installed using the package menu (see The Package Menu Buffer), but you can also use the command M-x package-install. This prompts for the name of a package with the ‘available’ status, then downloads and installs it. Similarly, if you want to upgrade a package, you can use the M-x package-upgrade command, and if you want to upgrade all the packages, you can use the M-x package-upgrade-all command.

By default, package-install doesn’t consider built-in packages for which new versions are available from the archives. (A package is built-in if it is included in the Emacs distribution.) In particular, it will not show built-in packages in the list of completion candidates when you type at its prompt. But if you invoke package-install with a prefix argument, it will also consider built-in packages that can be upgraded. You can make this behavior the default by customizing the variable package-install-upgrade-built-in: if its value is non-nil, package-install will consider built-in packages even when invoked without a prefix argument. Note that the package-menu commands (see The Package Menu Buffer) are also affected by package-install-upgrade-built-in.

By contrast, package-upgrade and package-upgrade-all never consider built-in packages. If you want to use these commands for upgrading some built-in packages, you need to upgrade each of those packages, once, either via C-u M-x package-install RET, or by customizing package-install-upgrade-built-in to a non-nil value, and then upgrading the package once via the package menu or by package-install.

If you customize package-install-upgrade-built-in to a non-nil value, be very careful when using commands that update many packages at once, like package-upgrade-all and U in the package menu: those might overwrite built-in packages that you didn’t intent to replace with newer versions from the archives. Don’t use these bulk commands if you want to update only a small number of built-in packages.

A package may require certain other packages to be installed, because it relies on functionality provided by them. When Emacs installs such a package, it also automatically downloads and installs any required package that is not already installed. (If a required package is somehow unavailable, Emacs signals an error and stops installation.) A package’s requirements list is shown in its help buffer.

By default, packages are downloaded from a single package archive maintained by the Emacs developers. This is controlled by the variable package-archives, whose value is a list of package archives known to Emacs. Each list element must have the form (id . location), where id is the name of a package archive and location is the URL or name of the package archive directory. You can alter this list if you wish to use third party package archives—but do so at your own risk, and use only third parties that you think you can trust!

The maintainers of package archives can increase the trust that you can have in their packages by signing them. They generate a private/public pair of cryptographic keys, and use the private key to create a signature file for each package. With the public key, you can use the signature files to verify the package creator and make sure the package has not been tampered with. Signature verification uses the GnuPG package via the EasyPG interface (see EasyPG in

Emacs EasyPG Assistant Manual

). A valid signature is not a cast-iron guarantee that a package is not malicious, so you should still exercise caution. Package archives should provide instructions on how you can obtain their public key. One way is to download the key from a server such as https://pgp.mit.edu/. Use M-x package-import-keyring to import the key into Emacs. Emacs stores package keys in the directory specified by the variable package-gnupghome-dir, by default in the gnupg subdirectory of package-user-dir, which causes Emacs to invoke GnuPG with the option ‘--homedir’ when verifying signatures. If package-gnupghome-dir is nil, GnuPG’s option ‘--homedir’ is omitted. The public key for the GNU package archive is distributed with Emacs, in the etc/package-keyring.gpg. Emacs uses it automatically.

If the user option package-check-signature is non-nil, Emacs attempts to verify signatures when you install packages. If the option has the value allow-unsigned, and a usable OpenPGP configuration is found, signed packages will be checked, but you can still install a package that is not signed. If you use some archives that do not sign their packages, you can add them to the list package-unsigned-archives. (If the value is allow-unsigned and no usable OpenPGP is found, this option is treated as if its value was nil.) If the value is t, at least one signature must be valid; if the value is all, all of them must be valid.

For more information on cryptographic keys and signing, see GnuPG in

The GNU Privacy Guard Manual

. Emacs comes with an interface to GNU Privacy Guard, see EasyPG in

Emacs EasyPG Assistant Manual

.

If you have more than one package archive enabled, and some of them offer different versions of the same package, you may find the option package-pinned-packages useful. You can add package/archive pairs to this list, to ensure that the specified package is only ever downloaded from the specified archive.

Another option that is useful when you have several package archives enabled is package-archive-priorities. It specifies the priority of each archive (higher numbers specify higher priority archives). By default, archives have the priority of zero, unless specified otherwise by this option’s value. Packages from lower-priority archives will not be shown in the menu, if the same package is available from a higher-priority archive. (This is controlled by the value of package-menu-hide-low-priority.)

Once a package is downloaded, byte-compiled and installed, it is made available to the current Emacs session. Making a package available adds its directory to load-path and loads its autoloads. The effect of a package’s autoloads varies from package to package. Most packages just make some new commands available, while others have more wide-ranging effects on the Emacs session. For such information, consult the package’s help buffer.

Installed packages are automatically made available by Emacs in all subsequent sessions. This happens at startup, before processing the init file but after processing the early init file (see The Early Init File). As an exception, Emacs does not make packages available at startup if invoked with the ‘-q’ or ‘--no-init-file’ options (see Initial Options).

To keep Emacs from automatically making packages available at startup, change the variable package-enable-at-startup to nil. You must do this in the early init file, as the variable is read before loading the regular init file. Currently this variable cannot be set via Customize.

If you have many packages installed, you can improve startup times by setting the user option package-quickstart to t. Setting this option will make Emacs precompute many things instead of re-computing them on every Emacs startup. However, if you do this, then you have to manually run the command package-quickstart-refresh when the activations need to be changed, such as when you change the value of package-load-list.

If you have set package-enable-at-startup to nil, you can still make packages available either during or after startup. To make installed packages available during startup, call the function package-activate-all in your init file. To make installed packages available after startup, invoke the command M-: (package-activate-all) RET.

For finer control over which packages are made available at startup, you can use the variable package-load-list. Its value should be a list. A list element of the form (name version) tells Emacs to make available version version of the package named name. Here, version should be a version string (corresponding to a specific version of the package), or t (which means to make available any installed version), or nil (which means no version; this disables the package, preventing it from being made available). A list element can also be the symbol all, which means to make available the latest installed version of any package not named by the other list elements. The default value is just '(all).

For example, if you set package-load-list to '((muse "3.20") all) , then Emacs only makes available version 3.20 of the ‘muse’ package, plus any installed version of packages other than ‘muse’. Any other version of ‘muse’ that happens to be installed will be ignored. The ‘muse’ package will be listed in the package menu with the ‘held’ status.

Emacs byte code is quite stable, but it’s possible for byte code to become outdated, or for the compiled files to rely on macros that have changed in new versions of Emacs. You can use the command M-x package-recompile to recompile a particular package, or M-x package-recompile-all to recompile all the packages. (The latter command might take quite a while to run if you have many installed packages.)

49.4 Package Files and Directory Layout

Each package is downloaded from the package archive in the form of a single package file—either an Emacs Lisp source file, or a tar file containing multiple Emacs Lisp source and other files. Package files are automatically retrieved, processed, and disposed of by the Emacs commands that install packages. Normally, you will not need to deal directly with them, unless you are making a package (see Packaging in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). Should you ever need to install a package directly from a package file, use the command M-x package-install-file.

Once installed, the contents of a package are placed in a subdirectory of ~/.emacs.d/elpa/ (you can change the name of that directory by changing the variable package-user-dir). The package subdirectory is named name-version, where name is the package name and version is its version string.

In addition to package-user-dir, Emacs looks for installed packages in the directories listed in package-directory-list. These directories are meant for system administrators to make Emacs packages available system-wide; Emacs itself never installs packages there. The package subdirectories for package-directory-list are laid out in the same way as in package-user-dir.

Deleting a package (see The Package Menu Buffer) involves deleting the corresponding package subdirectory. This only works for packages installed in package-user-dir; if told to act on a package in a system-wide package directory, the deletion command signals an error.

49.5 Fetching Package Sources

By default package-install downloads a Tarball from a package archive and installs its files. This might be inadequate if you wish to hack on the package sources and share your changes with others. In that case, you may prefer to directly fetch and work on the upstream source. This often makes it easier to develop patches and report bugs.

One way to do this is to use package-vc-install, to fetch the source code for a package directly from source. The command will also automatically ensure that all files are byte-compiled and auto-loaded, just like with a regular package. Packages installed this way behave just like any other package. You can upgrade them using package-upgrade or package-upgrade-all and delete them again using package-delete. They are even displayed in the regular package listing. If you just wish to clone the source of a package, without adding it to the package list, use package-vc-checkout.

With the source checkout, you might want to reproduce a bug against the current development head or implement a new feature to scratch an itch. If the package metadata indicates how to contact the maintainer, you can use the command package-report-bug to report a bug via Email. This report will include all the user options that you have customized. If you have made a change you wish to share with the maintainers, first commit your changes then use the command package-vc-prepare-patch to share it. See Preparing Patches.

If you maintain your own packages you might want to use a local checkout instead of cloning a remote repository. You can do this by using package-vc-install-from-checkout, which creates a symbolic link from the package directory (see Package Files and Directory Layout) to your checkout and initializes the code. Note that you might have to use package-vc-rebuild to repeat the initialization and update the autoloads.

49.5.1 Specifying Package Sources

To install a package from source, Emacs must know where to get the package’s source code (such as a code repository) and basic information about the structure of the code (such as the main file in a multi-file package). A package specification describes these properties.

When supported by a package archive (see Package Archives in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

), Emacs can automatically download a package’s specification from said archive. If the first argument passed to package-vc-install is a symbol naming a package, then Emacs will use the specification provided by the archive for that package.

;; Emacs will download BBDB's specification from GNU ELPA:
(package-vc-install 'bbdb)

The first argument to package-vc-install may also be a package specification. This allows you to install source packages from locations other than the known archives listed in the user option package-archives. A package specification is a list of the form (name . spec), in which spec should be a property list using any of the keys in the table below.

For definitions of basic terms for working with code repositories and version control systems, see VCS Concepts in

The GNU Emacs Manual

.

:url

A string providing the URL that specifies the repository from which to fetch the package’s source code.

:branch

A string providing the revision of the code to install. Do not confuse this with a package’s version number.

:lisp-dir

A string providing the repository-relative name of the directory to use for loading the Lisp sources, which defaults to the root directory of the repository.

:main-file

A string providing the main file of the project, from which to gather package metadata. If not given, the default is the package name with ".el" appended to it.

:doc

A string providing the repository-relative name of the documentation file from which to build an Info file. This can be a Texinfo file or an Org file.

:vc-backend

A symbol naming the VC backend to use for downloading a copy of the package’s repository (see Version Control Systems in

The GNU Emacs Manual

). If omitted, Emacs will attempt to make a guess based on the provided URL, or, failing that, the process will fall back onto the value of package-vc-default-backend.

;; Specifying information manually:
(package-vc-install
  '(bbdb :url "https://git.savannah.nongnu.org/git/bbdb.git"
         :lisp-dir "lisp"
         :doc "doc/bbdb.texi"))

43 Editing Pictures

To edit a picture made out of text characters (for example, a picture of the division of a register into fields, as a comment in a program), use the command M-x picture-mode to enter Picture mode.

In Picture mode, editing is based on the quarter-plane model of text, according to which the text characters lie studded on an area that stretches infinitely far to the right and downward. The concept of the end of a line does not exist in this model; the most you can say is where the last nonblank character on the line is found.

Of course, Emacs really always considers text as a sequence of characters, and lines really do have ends. But Picture mode replaces the most frequently-used commands with variants that simulate the quarter-plane model of text. They do this by inserting spaces or by converting tabs to spaces.

Most of the basic editing commands of Emacs are redefined by Picture mode to do essentially the same thing but in a quarter-plane way. In addition, Picture mode defines various keys starting with the C-c prefix to run special picture editing commands.

One of these keys, C-c C-c, is particularly important. Often a picture is part of a larger file that is usually edited in some other major mode. Picture mode records the name of the previous major mode so you can use the C-c C-c command (picture-mode-exit) later to go back to that mode. C-c C-c also deletes spaces from the ends of lines, unless given a numeric argument.

The special commands of Picture mode all work in other modes (provided the picture library is loaded), but are not bound to keys except in Picture mode. The descriptions below talk of moving “one column” and so on, but all the picture mode commands handle numeric arguments as their normal equivalents do.

Turning on Picture mode runs the hook picture-mode-hook. Additional extensions to Picture mode can be found in artist.el.

43.1 Basic Editing in Picture Mode

Most keys do the same thing in Picture mode that they usually do, but do it in a quarter-plane style. For example, C-f is rebound to run picture-forward-column, a command which moves point one column to the right, inserting a space if necessary so that the actual end of the line makes no difference. C-b is rebound to run picture-backward-column, which always moves point left one column, converting a tab to multiple spaces if necessary. C-n and C-p are rebound to run picture-move-down and picture-move-up, which can either insert spaces or convert tabs as necessary to make sure that point stays in exactly the same column. C-e runs picture-end-of-line, which moves to after the last nonblank character on the line. C-a runs picture-beginning-of-line. (The choice of screen model does not affect beginnings of lines; the only extra thing this command does is update the current picture column to 0.)

Insertion of text is adapted to the quarter-plane screen model through the use of Overwrite mode (see Minor Modes.) Self-inserting characters replace existing text, column by column, rather than pushing existing text to the right. RET runs picture-newline, which just moves to the beginning of the following line so that new text will replace that line.

In Picture mode, the commands that normally delete or kill text, instead erase text (replacing it with spaces). DEL (picture-backward-clear-column) replaces the preceding character with a space rather than removing it; this moves point backwards. C-d (picture-clear-column) replaces the next character or characters with spaces, but does not move point. (If you want to clear characters to spaces and move forward over them, use SPC.) C-k (picture-clear-line) really kills the contents of lines, but does not delete the newlines from the buffer.

To do actual insertion, you must use special commands. C-o (picture-open-line) creates a blank line after the current line; it never splits a line. C-M-o (split-line) makes sense in Picture mode, so it is not changed. C-j (picture-duplicate-line) inserts another line with the same contents below the current line.

To do actual deletion in Picture mode, use C-w, C-c C-d (which is defined as delete-char, as C-d is in other modes), or one of the picture rectangle commands (see Picture Mode Rectangle Commands).

43.2 Controlling Motion after Insert

Since self-inserting characters in Picture mode overwrite and move point, there is no essential restriction on how point should be moved. Normally point moves right, but you can specify any of the eight orthogonal or diagonal directions for motion after a self-inserting character. This is useful for drawing lines in the buffer.

C-c <
C-c LEFT

Move left after insertion (picture-movement-left).

C-c >
C-c RIGHT

Move right after insertion (picture-movement-right).

C-c ^
C-c UP

Move up after insertion (picture-movement-up).

C-c .
C-c DOWN

Move down after insertion (picture-movement-down).

C-c `
C-c Home

Move up and left (“northwest”) after insertion (picture-movement-nw).

C-c '
C-c PageUp
C-c prior

Move up and right (“northeast”) after insertion (picture-movement-ne).

C-c /
C-c End

Move down and left (“southwest”) after insertion
(picture-movement-sw).

C-c \
C-c PageDown
C-c next

Move down and right (“southeast”) after insertion
(picture-movement-se).

Two motion commands move based on the current Picture insertion direction. The command C-c C-f (picture-motion) moves in the same direction as motion after insertion currently does, while C-c C-b (picture-motion-reverse) moves in the opposite direction.

43.3 Picture Mode Tabs

Two kinds of tab-like action are provided in Picture mode. Use M-TAB (picture-tab-search) for context-based tabbing. With no argument, it moves to a point underneath the next “interesting” character that follows whitespace in the previous nonblank line. “Next” here means “appearing at a horizontal position greater than the one point starts out at”. With prefix argument, as in C-u M-TAB, this command moves to the next such interesting character in the current line. M-TAB does not change the text; it only moves point. “Interesting” characters are defined by the variable picture-tab-chars, which should define a set of characters. The syntax for this variable is like the syntax used inside of ‘[…]’ in a regular expression—but without the ‘[’ and the ‘]’. Its default value is "!-~".

TAB itself runs picture-tab, which operates based on the current tab stop settings; it is the Picture mode equivalent of tab-to-tab-stop. Normally it just moves point, but with a numeric argument it clears the text that it moves over.

The context-based and tab-stop-based forms of tabbing are brought together by the command C-c TAB (picture-set-tab-stops). This command sets the tab stops to the positions which M-TAB would consider significant in the current line. The use of this command, together with TAB, can get the effect of context-based tabbing. But M-TAB is more convenient in the cases where it is sufficient.

It may be convenient to prevent use of actual tab characters in pictures. For example, this prevents C-x TAB from messing up the picture. You can do this by setting the variable indent-tabs-mode to nil.

43.4 Picture Mode Rectangle Commands

Picture mode defines commands for working on rectangular pieces of the text in ways that fit with the quarter-plane model. The standard rectangle commands may also be useful. See Rectangles.

C-c C-k

Clear out the region-rectangle with spaces (picture-clear-rectangle). With a prefix argument, delete the text.

C-c C-w r

Similar, but save rectangle contents in register r first (picture-clear-rectangle-to-register). See Registers.

C-c C-y

Copy last killed rectangle into the buffer by overwriting, with upper left corner at point (picture-yank-rectangle). With argument, insert instead.

C-c C-x r

Similar, but use the rectangle in register r (picture-yank-rectangle-from-register).

The picture rectangle commands C-c C-k (picture-clear-rectangle) and C-c C-w (picture-clear-rectangle-to-register) differ from the standard rectangle commands in that they normally clear the rectangle instead of deleting it; this is analogous with the way C-d is changed in Picture mode.

However, deletion of rectangles can be useful in Picture mode, so these commands delete the rectangle if given a numeric argument. C-c C-k either with or without a numeric argument saves the rectangle for C-c C-y.

The Picture mode commands for yanking rectangles differ from the standard ones in that they overwrite instead of inserting. This is the same way that Picture mode insertion of other text differs from other modes. C-c C-y (picture-yank-rectangle) inserts (by overwriting) the rectangle that was most recently killed, while C-c C-x (picture-yank-rectangle-from-register) does likewise for the rectangle found in a specified register.

41 Printing Hard Copies

Emacs provides commands for printing hardcopies of either an entire buffer or part of one. You can invoke the printing commands directly, as detailed below, or using the ‘File’ menu on the menu bar.

Aside from the commands described in this section, you can also print hardcopies from Dired (see Operating on Files) and the diary (see Displaying the Diary). You can also “print” an Emacs buffer to HTML with the command M-x htmlfontify-buffer, which converts the current buffer to a HTML file, replacing Emacs faces with CSS-based markup. Furthermore, Org mode allows you to print Org files to a variety of formats, such as PDF (see Org Mode).

M-x print-buffer

Print hardcopy of current buffer with page headings containing the file name and page number.

M-x lpr-buffer

Print hardcopy of current buffer without page headings.

M-x print-region

Like print-buffer but print only the current region.

M-x lpr-region

Like lpr-buffer but print only the current region.

On most operating systems, the above hardcopy commands submit files for printing by calling the lpr program. To change the printer program, customize the variable lpr-command. To specify extra switches to give the printer program, customize the list variable lpr-switches. Its value should be a list of option strings, each of which should start with ‘-’ (e.g., the option string "-w80" specifies a line width of 80 columns). The default is the empty list, nil.

To specify the printer to use, set the variable printer-name. The default, nil, specifies the default printer. If you set it to a printer name (a string), that name is passed to lpr with the ‘-P’ switch; if you are not using lpr, you should specify the switch with lpr-printer-switch.

The variable lpr-headers-switches similarly specifies the extra switches to use to make page headers. The variable lpr-add-switches controls whether to supply ‘-T’ and ‘-J’ options (suitable for lpr) to the printer program: nil means don’t add them (this should be the value if your printer program is not compatible with lpr).

41.1 PostScript Hardcopy

These commands convert buffer contents to PostScript, either printing it or leaving it in another Emacs buffer.

M-x ps-print-buffer

Print hardcopy of the current buffer in PostScript form.

M-x ps-print-region

Print hardcopy of the current region in PostScript form.

M-x ps-print-buffer-with-faces

Print hardcopy of the current buffer in PostScript form, showing the faces used in the text by means of PostScript features.

M-x ps-print-region-with-faces

Print hardcopy of the current region in PostScript form, showing the faces used in the text.

M-x ps-spool-buffer

Generate and spool a PostScript image for the current buffer text.

M-x ps-spool-region

Generate and spool a PostScript image for the current region.

M-x ps-spool-buffer-with-faces

Generate and spool a PostScript image for the current buffer, showing the faces used.

M-x ps-spool-region-with-faces

Generate and spool a PostScript image for the current region, showing the faces used.

M-x ps-despool

Send the spooled PostScript to the printer.

M-x handwrite

Generate/print PostScript for the current buffer as if handwritten.

The ps-print-buffer and ps-print-region commands print buffer contents in PostScript form. One command prints the entire buffer; the other, just the region. The commands ps-print-buffer-with-faces and ps-print-region-with-faces behave similarly, but use PostScript features to show the faces (fonts and colors) of the buffer text.

Interactively, when you use a prefix argument (C-u), these commands prompt the user for a file name, and save the PostScript image in that file instead of sending it to the printer.

The commands whose names have ‘spool’ instead of ‘print’, generate the PostScript output in an Emacs buffer instead of sending it to the printer.

Use the command ps-despool to send the spooled images to the printer. This command sends the PostScript generated by ‘-spool-’ commands (see commands above) to the printer. With a prefix argument (C-u), it prompts for a file name, and saves the spooled PostScript image in that file instead of sending it to the printer.

M-x handwrite is more frivolous. It generates a PostScript rendition of the current buffer as a cursive handwritten document. It can be customized in group handwrite. This function only supports ISO 8859-1 characters.

41.2 Variables for PostScript Hardcopy

All the PostScript hardcopy commands use the variables ps-lpr-command and ps-lpr-switches to specify how to print the output. ps-lpr-command specifies the command name to run, ps-lpr-switches specifies command line options to use, and ps-printer-name specifies the printer. If you don’t set the first two variables yourself, they take their initial values from lpr-command and lpr-switches. If ps-printer-name is nil, printer-name is used.

The variable ps-print-header controls whether these commands add header lines to each page—set it to nil to turn headers off.

If your printer doesn’t support colors, you should turn off color processing by setting ps-print-color-p to nil. By default, if the display supports colors, Emacs produces hardcopy output with color information; on black-and-white printers, colors are emulated with shades of gray. This might produce barely-readable or even illegible output, even if your screen colors only use shades of gray.

Alternatively, you can set ps-print-color-p to black-white to have colors display better on black/white printers. This works by using information in ps-black-white-faces to express colors by customizable list of shades of gray, augmented by bold and italic face attributes.

By default, PostScript printing ignores the background colors of the faces, unless the variable ps-use-face-background is non-nil. This is to avoid unwanted interference with the zebra stripes and background image/text.

The variable ps-paper-type specifies which size of paper to format for; legitimate values include a4, a3, a4small, b4, b5, executive, ledger, legal, letter, letter-small, statement, tabloid. The default is letter. You can define additional paper sizes by changing the variable ps-page-dimensions-database.

The variable ps-landscape-mode specifies the orientation of printing on the page. The default is nil, which stands for portrait mode. Any non-nil value specifies landscape mode.

The variable ps-number-of-columns specifies the number of columns; it takes effect in both landscape and portrait mode. The default is 1.

The variable ps-font-family specifies which font family to use for printing ordinary text. Legitimate values include Courier, Helvetica, NewCenturySchlbk, Palatino and Times. The variable ps-font-size specifies the size of the font for ordinary text and defaults to 8.5 points. The value of ps-font-size can also be a cons of 2 floats: one for landscape mode, the other for portrait mode.

Emacs supports more scripts and characters than a typical PostScript printer. Thus, some of the characters in your buffer might not be printable using the fonts built into your printer. You can augment the fonts supplied with the printer with those from the GNU Intlfonts package, or you can instruct Emacs to use Intlfonts exclusively. The variable ps-multibyte-buffer controls this: the default value, nil, is appropriate for printing ASCII and Latin-1 characters; a value of non-latin-printer is for printers which have the fonts for ASCII, Latin-1, Japanese, and Korean characters built into them. A value of bdf-font arranges for the BDF fonts from the Intlfonts package to be used for all characters. Finally, a value of bdf-font-except-latin instructs the printer to use built-in fonts for ASCII and Latin-1 characters, and Intlfonts BDF fonts for the rest.

To be able to use the BDF fonts, Emacs needs to know where to find them. The variable bdf-directory-list holds the list of directories where Emacs should look for the fonts; the default value includes a single directory /usr/local/share/emacs/fonts/bdf.

Many other customization variables for these commands are defined and described in the Lisp files ps-print.el and ps-mule.el.

41.3 Printing Package

The basic Emacs facilities for printing hardcopy can be extended using the Printing package. This provides an easy-to-use interface for choosing what to print, previewing PostScript files before printing, and setting various printing options such as print headers, landscape or portrait modes, duplex modes, and so forth. On GNU/Linux or Unix systems, the Printing package relies on the gs and gv utilities, which are distributed as part of the GhostScript program. On MS-Windows, the gstools port of Ghostscript can be used.

To use the Printing package, add (require 'printing) to your init file (see The Emacs Initialization File), followed by (pr-update-menus). This function replaces the usual printing commands in the menu bar with a ‘Printing’ submenu that contains various printing options. You can also type M-x pr-interface RET; this creates a *Printing Interface* buffer, similar to a customization buffer, where you can set the printing options. After selecting what and how to print, you start the print job using the ‘Print’ button (click mouse-2 on it, or move point over it and type RET). For further information on the various options, use the ‘Interface Help’ button.

27 Editing Programs

This chapter describes Emacs features for facilitating editing programs. Some of the things these features can do are:

Find or move over top-level definitions (see Top-Level Definitions, or Defuns).
Apply the usual indentation conventions of the language (see Indentation for Programs).
Balance parentheses (see Commands for Editing with Parentheses).
Insert, kill or align comments (see Manipulating Comments).
Highlight program syntax (see Font Lock mode).

27.1 Major Modes for Programming Languages

Emacs has specialized major modes (see Major Modes) for many programming languages. A programming language mode typically specifies the syntax of expressions, the customary rules for indentation, how to do syntax highlighting for the language, and how to find the beginning or end of a function definition. It often has features for compiling and debugging programs as well. The major mode for each language is named after the language; for instance, the major mode for the C programming language is c-mode.

Emacs has programming language modes for Lisp, Scheme, the Scheme-based DSSSL expression language, Ada, ASM, AWK, C, C++, C#, Fortran, Icon, IDL (CORBA), IDLWAVE, Java, Javascript, M4, Makefiles, Metafont (TeX’s companion for font creation), Modula2, Object Pascal, Objective-C, Octave, Pascal, Perl, Pike, PostScript, Prolog, Python, Ruby, Simula, SQL, Tcl, TypeScript, Verilog, and VHDL. An alternative mode for Perl is called CPerl mode. Modes are also available for the scripting languages of the common GNU and Unix shells, and MS-DOS/MS-Windows ‘BAT’ files, JSON, DNS master files, CSS (Cascading Style Sheets), Dockerfiles, CMake files, and various sorts of configuration files.

Ideally, Emacs should have a major mode for each programming language that you might want to edit. If it doesn’t have a mode for your favorite language, the mode might be implemented in a package not distributed with Emacs (see Emacs Lisp Packages); or you can contribute one.

If Emacs has been compiled with the ‘tree-sitter’ library, it offers several optional editing modes based on that library, which utilize the incremental parsing capabilities provided by ‘tree-sitter’. These modes have ‘-ts-’ in their names; for example c-ts-mode, python-ts-mode, etc.

In most programming languages, indentation should vary from line to line to illustrate the structure of the program. Therefore, in most programming language modes, typing TAB updates the indentation of the current line (see Indentation for Programs). Furthermore, DEL is usually bound to backward-delete-char-untabify, which deletes backward treating each tab as if it were the equivalent number of spaces, so that you can delete one column of indentation without worrying whether the whitespace consists of spaces or tabs.

Entering a programming language mode runs the custom Lisp functions specified in the hook variable prog-mode-hook, followed by those specified in the mode’s own mode hook (see Major Modes). For instance, entering C mode runs the hooks prog-mode-hook and c-mode-hook. See Hooks, for information about hooks.

Separate manuals are available for the modes for Ada (see Ada Mode in

Ada Mode

), C/C++/Objective C/Java/Corba IDL/Pike/AWK (see CC Mode in

CC Mode

), Octave, VHDL, and IDLWAVE (see IDLWAVE in

IDLWAVE User Manual

).

27.2 Top-Level Definitions, or Defuns

In Emacs, a major definition at the top level in the buffer, such as a function, is called a defun. The name comes from Lisp, but in Emacs we use it for all languages.

27.2.1 Left Margin Convention

Many programming-language modes have traditionally assumed that any opening parenthesis or brace found at the left margin is the start of a top-level definition, or defun. So, by default, commands which seek the beginning of a defun accept such a delimiter as signifying that position.

If you want to override this convention, you can do so by setting the user option open-paren-in-column-0-is-defun-start to nil. If this option is set to t (the default), commands seeking the start of a defun will stop at opening parentheses or braces at column zero which aren’t in a comment or string. When it is nil, defuns are found by searching for parens or braces at the outermost level. Since low-level Emacs routines no longer depend on this convention, you usually won’t need to change open-paren-in-column-0-is-defun-start from its default.

27.2.2 Moving by Defuns

These commands move point or set up the region based on top-level major definitions, also called defuns.

C-M-a

Move to beginning of current or preceding defun (beginning-of-defun).

C-M-e

Move to end of current or following defun (end-of-defun).

C-M-h

Put region around whole current or following defun (mark-defun).

The commands to move to the beginning and end of the current defun are C-M-a (beginning-of-defun) and C-M-e (end-of-defun). If you repeat one of these commands, or use a positive numeric argument, each repetition moves to the next defun in the direction of motion.

C-M-a with a negative argument −n moves forward n times to the next beginning of a defun. This is not exactly the same place that C-M-e with argument n would move to; the end of this defun is not usually exactly the same place as the beginning of the following defun. (Whitespace, comments, and perhaps declarations can separate them.) Likewise, C-M-e with a negative argument moves back to an end of a defun, which is not quite the same as C-M-a with a positive argument.

To operate on the current defun, use C-M-h (mark-defun), which sets the mark at the end of the current defun and puts point at its beginning. See Commands to Mark Textual Objects. This is the easiest way to get ready to kill the defun in order to move it to a different place in the file. If the defun is directly preceded by comments (with no intervening blank lines), they are marked, too. If you use the command while point is between defuns, it uses the following defun. If you use the command while the mark is already active, it extends the end of the region to include one more defun. With a prefix argument, it marks that many defuns or extends the region by the appropriate number of defuns. With negative prefix argument it marks defuns in the opposite direction and also changes the direction of selecting for subsequent uses of mark-defun.

In C mode, C-M-h runs the function c-mark-function, which is almost the same as mark-defun; the difference is that it backs up over the argument declarations, function name and returned data type so that the entire C function is inside the region. This is an example of how major modes adjust the standard key bindings so that they do their standard jobs in a way better fitting a particular language. Other major modes may replace any or all of these key bindings for that purpose.

Some programming languages supported nested defuns, whereby a defun (such as a function or a method or a class) can be defined inside (i.e., as part of the body) of another defun. The commands described above by default find the beginning and the end of the innermost defun around point. Major modes based on the tree-sitter library provide control of this behavior: if the variable treesit-defun-tactic is set to the value top-level, the defun commands will find the outermost defuns instead.

27.2.3 Imenu

The Imenu facility offers a way to find the major definitions in a file by name. It is also useful in text formatter major modes, where it treats each chapter, section, etc., as a definition. (See Find Identifier References, for a more powerful feature that handles multiple files together.)

If you type M-g i (imenu), it reads the name of a definition using the minibuffer, then moves point to that definition. You can use completion to specify the name; the command always displays the whole list of valid names.

Alternatively, you can bind the command imenu to a mouse click. Then it displays mouse menus for you to select a definition name. You can also add the buffer’s index to the menu bar by calling imenu-add-menubar-index. If you want to have this menu bar item available for all buffers in a certain major mode, you can do this by adding imenu-add-menubar-index to its mode hook. But if you have done that, you will have to wait a little while each time you visit a file in that mode, while Emacs finds all the definitions in that buffer.

When you change the contents of a buffer, if you add or delete definitions, you can update the buffer’s index based on the new contents by invoking the ‘*Rescan*’ item in the menu. Rescanning happens automatically if you set imenu-auto-rescan to a non-nil value. There is no need to rescan because of small changes in the text.

imenu-auto-rescan will be disabled in buffers that are larger than imenu-auto-rescan-maxout in bytes, and scanning is stopped if it takes more than imenu-max-index-time seconds.

You can customize the way the menus are sorted by setting the variable imenu-sort-function. By default, names are ordered as they occur in the buffer; if you want alphabetic sorting, use the symbol imenu--sort-by-name as the value. You can also define your own comparison function by writing Lisp code.

If Eglot is activated for the current buffer’s project (see Working with Projects) and the current buffer’s major mode, Eglot provides its own facility for producing the buffer’s index based on the analysis of the program source by the language-server which manages the current buffer. See Eglot Features in

Eglot: The Emacs LSP Client

.

Imenu provides the information to guide Which Function mode (see Which Function Mode). The Speedbar can also use it (see Speedbar Frames).

27.2.4 Which Function Mode

Which Function mode is a global minor mode (see Minor Modes) which displays the current function name in the mode line, updating it as you move around in a buffer.

To either enable or disable Which Function mode, use the command M-x which-function-mode. Which Function mode is a global minor mode. By default, it takes effect in all major modes that know how to support it (i.e., all the major modes that support Imenu). You can restrict it to a specific list of major modes by changing the value of the variable which-func-modes from t (which means to support all available major modes) to a list of major mode names.

27.3 Indentation for Programs

The best way to keep a program properly indented is to use Emacs to reindent it as you change it. Emacs has commands to indent either a single line, a specified number of lines, or all of the lines inside a single parenthetical grouping.

See Indentation, for general information about indentation. This section describes indentation features specific to programming language modes.

Emacs also provides a Lisp pretty-printer in the pp package, which reformats Lisp objects with nice-looking indentation. See pp in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

27.3.1 Basic Program Indentation Commands

TAB

Adjust indentation of current line (indent-for-tab-command).

RET

Insert a newline, then adjust indentation of following line (newline).

The basic indentation command is TAB (indent-for-tab-command), which was documented in Indentation. In programming language modes, TAB indents the current line, based on the indentation and syntactic content of the preceding lines; if the region is active, TAB indents each line within the region, not just the current line.

The command RET (newline), which was documented in Inserting Text, does the same as C-j followed by TAB: it inserts a new line, then adjusts the line’s indentation.

When indenting a line that starts within a parenthetical grouping, Emacs usually places the start of the line under the preceding line within the group, or under the text after the parenthesis. If you manually give one of these lines a nonstandard indentation (e.g., for aesthetic purposes), the lines below will follow it.

The indentation commands for most programming language modes assume that an open-parenthesis, open-brace or other opening delimiter at the left margin is the start of a function. If the code you are editing violates this assumption—even if the delimiters occur in strings or comments—you must set open-paren-in-column-0-is-defun-start to nil for indentation to work properly. See Left Margin Convention.

27.3.2 Indenting Several Lines

Sometimes, you may want to reindent several lines of code at a time. One way to do this is to use the mark; when the mark is active and the region is non-empty, TAB indents every line in the region. Alternatively, the command C-M-\ (indent-region) indents every line in the region, whether or not the mark is active (see Indentation Commands).

In addition, Emacs provides the following commands for indenting large chunks of code:

C-M-q

Reindent all the lines within one parenthetical grouping.

C-u TAB

Shift an entire parenthetical grouping rigidly sideways so that its first line is properly indented.

M-x indent-code-rigidly

Shift all the lines in the region rigidly sideways, but do not alter lines that start inside comments and strings.

To reindent the contents of a single parenthetical grouping, position point before the beginning of the grouping and type C-M-q. This changes the relative indentation within the grouping, without affecting its overall indentation (i.e., the indentation of the line where the grouping starts). The function that C-M-q runs depends on the major mode; it is indent-pp-sexp in Lisp mode, c-indent-exp in C mode, etc. To correct the overall indentation as well, type TAB first.

If you like the relative indentation within a grouping but not the indentation of its first line, move point to that first line and type C-u TAB. In Lisp, C, and some other major modes, TAB with a numeric argument reindents the current line as usual, then reindents by the same amount all the lines in the parenthetical grouping starting on the current line. It is clever, though, and does not alter lines that start inside strings. Neither does it alter C preprocessor lines when in C mode, but it does reindent any continuation lines that may be attached to them.

The command M-x indent-code-rigidly rigidly shifts all the lines in the region sideways, like indent-rigidly does (see Indentation Commands). It doesn’t alter the indentation of lines that start inside a string, unless the region also starts inside that string. The prefix arg specifies the number of columns to indent.

27.3.3 Customizing Lisp Indentation

The indentation pattern for a Lisp expression can depend on the function called by the expression. For each Lisp function, you can choose among several predefined patterns of indentation, or define an arbitrary one with a Lisp program.

The standard pattern of indentation is as follows: the second line of the expression is indented under the first argument, if that is on the same line as the beginning of the expression; otherwise, the second line is indented underneath the function name. Each following line is indented under the previous line whose nesting depth is the same.

If the variable lisp-indent-offset is non-nil, it overrides the usual indentation pattern for the second line of an expression, so that such lines are always indented lisp-indent-offset more columns than the containing list.

Certain functions override the standard pattern. Functions whose names start with def treat the second lines as the start of a body, by indenting the second line lisp-body-indent additional columns beyond the open-parenthesis that starts the expression.

You can override the standard pattern in various ways for individual functions, according to the lisp-indent-function property of the function name. This is normally done for macro definitions, using the declare construct. See Defining Macros in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

In Emacs Lisp, lists are usually indented as if they are function-like forms:

(setq foo '(bar zot
                gazonk))

However, if you add a space after the opening parenthesis, this tells Emacs that it’s a data list instead of a piece of code, and Emacs will then indent it like this:

(setq foo '( bar zot
             gazonk))

27.3.4 Commands for C Indentation

Here are special features for indentation in C mode and related modes:

C-c C-q

Reindent the current top-level function definition or aggregate type declaration (c-indent-defun in CC mode, c-ts-mode-indent-defun in c-ts-mode based on tree-sitter).

C-M-q

Reindent each line in the balanced expression (see Expressions with Balanced Parentheses), also known as “sexp”, that follows point. In CC mode, this invokes c-indent-exp; in tree-sitter based c-ts-mode this invokes a more general prog-indent-sexp. A prefix argument inhibits warning messages about invalid syntax.

TAB

Reindent the current line, active region, or block starting on this line (c-indent-line-or-region). With prefix argument, rigidly reindent the balanced expression which starts on the current line, if the current line needs reindentation.

If c-tab-always-indent is t, this command always reindents the current line and does nothing else. This is the default.

If that variable is nil, this command reindents the current line only if point is at the left margin or in the line’s indentation; otherwise, it inserts a tab (or the equivalent number of spaces, if indent-tabs-mode is nil).

Any other value (not nil or t) means always reindent the line, and also insert a tab if within a comment or a string.

To reindent the whole current buffer, type C-x h C-M-\. This first selects the whole buffer as the region, then reindents that region.

To reindent the current block, use C-M-u C-M-q. This moves to the front of the block and then reindents it all.

27.3.5 Customizing C Indentation

C mode and related modes use a flexible mechanism for customizing indentation. C mode indents a source line in two steps: first it classifies the line syntactically according to its contents and context; second, it determines the indentation offset associated by your selected style with the syntactic construct and adds this onto the indentation of the anchor statement.

C-c . style RET

Select a predefined style style (c-set-style in CC mode, c-ts-mode-set-style in c-ts-mode based on tree-sitter).

A style is a named collection of customizations that can be used in C mode and the related modes. Styles in

The CC Mode Manual

, for a complete description. Emacs comes with several predefined styles, including gnu, k&r, bsd, stroustrup, linux, python, java, whitesmith, ellemtel, and awk. Some of these styles are primarily intended for one language, but any of them can be used with any of the languages supported by these modes. To find out what a style looks like, select it and reindent some code, e.g., by typing C-M-q at the start of a function definition.

To choose a style for the current buffer, use the command C-c . . Specify a style name as an argument (case is not significant). This command affects the current buffer only, and it affects only future invocations of the indentation commands; it does not reindent the code already in the buffer. To reindent the whole buffer in the new style, you can type C-x h C-M-\.

When using CC mode, you can also set the variable c-default-style to specify the default style for various major modes. Its value should be either the style’s name (a string) or an alist, in which each element specifies one major mode and which indentation style to use for it. For example,

(setq c-default-style
      '((java-mode . "java")
        (awk-mode . "awk")
        (other . "gnu")))

specifies explicit choices for Java and AWK modes, and the default ‘gnu’ style for the other C-like modes. (These settings are actually the defaults.) This variable takes effect when you select one of the C-like major modes; thus, if you specify a new default style for Java mode, you can make it take effect in an existing Java mode buffer by typing M-x java-mode there.

When using the tree-sitter based c-ts-mode, you can set the default indentation style by customizing the variable c-ts-mode-indent-style.

The gnu style specifies the formatting recommended by the GNU Project for C; it is the default, so as to encourage use of our recommended style.

See Indentation Engine Basics in

the CC Mode Manual

, and Customizing Indentation in

the CC Mode Manual

, for more information on customizing indentation for C and related modes, including how to override parts of an existing style and how to define your own styles.

As an alternative to specifying a style, you can tell Emacs to guess a style by typing M-x c-guess in a sample code buffer. You can then apply the guessed style to other buffers with M-x c-guess-install. See Guessing the Style in

the CC Mode Manual

, for details.

27.4 Commands for Editing with Parentheses

This section describes the commands and features that take advantage of the parenthesis structure in a program, or help you keep it balanced.

When talking about these facilities, the term “parenthesis” also includes braces, brackets, or whatever delimiters are defined to match in pairs. The major mode controls which delimiters are significant, through the syntax table (see Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). In Lisp, only parentheses count; in C, these commands apply to braces and brackets too.

You can use M-x check-parens to find any unbalanced parentheses and unbalanced string quotes in the buffer.

27.4.1 Expressions with Balanced Parentheses

Each programming language mode has its own definition of a balanced expression. Balanced expressions typically include individual symbols, numbers, and string constants, as well as pieces of code enclosed in a matching pair of delimiters. The following commands deal with balanced expressions (in Emacs, such expressions are referred to internally as sexps^13).

C-M-f

Move forward over a balanced expression (forward-sexp).

C-M-b

Move backward over a balanced expression (backward-sexp).

C-M-k

Kill balanced expression forward (kill-sexp).

C-M-t

Transpose expressions (transpose-sexps).

C-M-@
C-M-SPC

Put mark after following expression (mark-sexp).

To move forward over a balanced expression, use C-M-f (forward-sexp). If the first significant character after point is an opening delimiter (e.g., ‘(’, ‘[’ or ‘{’ in C), this command moves past the matching closing delimiter. If the character begins a symbol, string, or number, the command moves over that.

The command C-M-b (backward-sexp) moves backward over a balanced expression—like C-M-f, but in the reverse direction. If the expression is preceded by any prefix characters (single-quote, backquote and comma, in Lisp), the command moves back over them as well.

C-M-f or C-M-b with an argument repeats that operation the specified number of times; with a negative argument means to move in the opposite direction. In most modes, these two commands move across comments as if they were whitespace. Note that their keys, C-M-f and C-M-b, are analogous to C-f and C-b, which move by characters (see Changing the Location of Point), and M-f and M-b, which move by words (see Words).

To kill a whole balanced expression, type C-M-k (kill-sexp). This kills the text that C-M-f would move over.

C-M-t (transpose-sexps) switches the positions of the previous balanced expression and the next one. It is analogous to the C-t command, which transposes characters (see Transposing Text). An argument to C-M-t serves as a repeat count, moving the previous expression over that many following ones. A negative argument moves the previous balanced expression backwards across those before it. An argument of zero, rather than doing nothing, transposes the balanced expressions ending at or after point and the mark.

To operate on balanced expressions with a command which acts on the region, type C-M-SPC (mark-sexp). This sets the mark where C-M-f would move to. While the mark is active, each successive call to this command extends the region by shifting the mark by one expression. Positive or negative numeric arguments move the mark forward or backward by the specified number of expressions. The alias C-M-@ is equivalent to C-M-SPC. See Commands to Mark Textual Objects, for more information about this and related commands.

In languages that use infix operators, such as C, it is not possible to recognize all balanced expressions because there can be multiple possibilities at a given position. For example, C mode does not treat ‘foo + bar’ as a single expression, even though it is one C expression; instead, it recognizes ‘foo’ as one expression and ‘bar’ as another, with the ‘+’ as punctuation between them. However, C mode recognizes ‘(foo + bar)’ as a single expression, because of the parentheses.

27.4.2 Moving in the Parenthesis Structure

The following commands move over groupings delimited by parentheses (or whatever else serves as delimiters in the language you are working with). They ignore strings and comments, including any parentheses within them, and also ignore parentheses that are quoted with an escape character. These commands are mainly intended for editing programs, but can be useful for editing any text containing parentheses. They are referred to internally as “list commands” because in Lisp these groupings are lists.

These commands assume that the starting point is not inside a string or a comment. If you invoke them from inside a string or comment, the results are unreliable.

C-M-n

Move forward over a parenthetical group (forward-list).

C-M-p

Move backward over a parenthetical group (backward-list).

C-M-u

Move up in parenthesis structure (backward-up-list).

C-M-d

Move down in parenthesis structure (down-list).

The list commands C-M-n (forward-list) and C-M-p (backward-list) move forward or backward over one (or n) parenthetical groupings.

C-M-n and C-M-p try to stay at the same level in the parenthesis structure. To move up one (or n) levels, use C-M-u (backward-up-list). C-M-u moves backward up past one unmatched opening delimiter. A positive argument serves as a repeat count; a negative argument reverses the direction of motion, so that the command moves forward and up one or more levels.

To move down in the parenthesis structure, use C-M-d (down-list). In Lisp mode, where ‘(’ is the only opening delimiter, this is nearly the same as searching for a ‘(’. An argument specifies the number of levels to go down.

27.4.3 Matching Parentheses

Emacs has a number of parenthesis matching features, which make it easy to see how and whether parentheses (or other delimiters) match up.

Whenever you type a self-inserting character that is a closing delimiter, Emacs briefly indicates the location of the matching opening delimiter, provided that is on the screen. If it is not on the screen, Emacs displays some of the text near it in the echo area. Either way, you can tell which grouping you are closing off. If the opening delimiter and closing delimiter are mismatched—such as in ‘[x)’—a warning message is displayed in the echo area.

Three variables control the display of matching parentheses:

blink-matching-paren turns the feature on or off: nil disables it, but the default is t to enable it. Set it to jump to make indication work by momentarily moving the cursor to the matching opening delimiter. Set it to jump-offscreen to make the cursor jump, even if the opening delimiter is off screen.
blink-matching-delay says how many seconds to keep indicating the matching opening delimiter. This may be an integer or floating-point number; the default is 1.
blink-matching-paren-distance specifies how many characters back to search to find the matching opening delimiter. If the match is not found in that distance, Emacs stops scanning and nothing is displayed. The default is 102400.

Show Paren mode is a minor mode that provides a more powerful kind of automatic matching. Whenever point is before an opening delimiter or after a closing delimiter, the delimiter, its matching delimiter, and optionally the text between them are highlighted. To toggle Show Paren mode globally, type M-x show-paren-mode. To toggle it only in the current buffer, type M-x show-paren-local-mode.

By default, this mode is switched on in all buffers that are meant for editing, but is not enabled in buffers that show data. This is controlled by the show-paren-predicate user option.

To customize the mode, type M-x customize-group RET paren-showing . The customizable options which control the operation of this mode include:

show-paren-highlight-openparen controls whether to highlight an open paren when point is just before it, and hence its position is marked by the cursor anyway. The default is non-nil (yes).
show-paren-style controls whether just the two parens, or also the text between them get highlighted. The valid options here are parenthesis (show the matching paren), expression (highlight the entire expression enclosed by the parens), and mixed (highlight the matching paren if it is visible in the window, the expression otherwise).
show-paren-when-point-inside-paren, when non-nil, causes highlighting also when point is inside of the parentheses. The default is nil.
show-paren-when-point-in-periphery, when non-nil, causes highlighting also when point is in whitespace at the beginning of a line and there is a paren at the first or last non-whitespace position on the line, or when point is at the end of a line and there is a paren at the last non-whitespace position on the line.
show-paren-context-when-offscreen, when non-nil, shows some context in the echo area when point is in a closing delimiter and the opening delimiter is offscreen. The context is usually the line that contains the opening delimiter, except if the opening delimiter is on its own line, in which case the context includes the previous nonblank line.

Electric Pair mode, a global minor mode, provides a way to easily insert matching delimiters: parentheses, braces, brackets, etc. Whenever you insert an opening delimiter, the matching closing delimiter is automatically inserted as well, leaving point between the two. Conversely, when you insert a closing delimiter over an existing one, no insertion takes places, and that position is simply skipped over. If the region is active (see The Mark and the Region), insertion of a delimiter operates on the region: the characters in the region are enclosed in a pair of matching delimiters, leaving point after the delimiter you typed.

These variables control additional features of Electric Pair mode:

electric-pair-preserve-balance, when non-nil, makes the default pairing logic balance out the number of opening and closing delimiters.
electric-pair-delete-adjacent-pairs, when non-nil, makes backspacing between two adjacent delimiters also automatically delete the closing delimiter.
electric-pair-open-newline-between-pairs, when non-nil, makes inserting a newline between two adjacent pairs also automatically open an extra newline after point.
electric-pair-skip-whitespace, when non-nil, causes the minor mode to skip whitespace forward before deciding whether to skip over the closing delimiter.

To toggle Electric Pair mode, type M-x electric-pair-mode. To toggle the mode in a single buffer, use M-x electric-pair-local-mode.

27.5 Manipulating Comments

Because comments are such an important part of programming, Emacs provides special commands for editing and inserting comments. It can also do spell checking on comments with Flyspell Prog mode (see Checking and Correcting Spelling).

Some major modes have special rules for indenting different kinds of comments. For example, in Lisp code, comments starting with two semicolons are indented as if they were lines of code, while those starting with three semicolons are supposed to be aligned to the left margin and are often used for sectioning purposes. Emacs understands these conventions; for instance, typing TAB on a comment line will indent the comment to the appropriate position.

;; This function is just an example.
;;; Here either two or three semicolons are appropriate.
(defun foo (x)
;;;  And now, the first part of the function:
  ;; The following line adds one.
  (1+ x))           ; This line adds one.

27.5.1 Comment Commands

The following commands operate on comments:

M-;

Insert or realign comment on current line; if the region is active, comment or uncomment the region instead (comment-dwim).

C-x C-;

Comment or uncomment the current line (comment-line). If the region is active, comment or uncomment the lines in the region instead.

C-u M-;

Kill comment on current line (comment-kill).

C-x ;

Set comment column (comment-set-column).

C-M-j
M-j

Like RET followed by inserting and aligning a comment (default-indent-new-line). See Multiple Lines of Comments.

M-x comment-region
C-c C-c (in C-like modes)

Add comment delimiters to all the lines in the region.

The command to create or align a comment is M-; (comment-dwim). The word “dwim” is an acronym for “Do What I Mean”; it indicates that this command can be used for many different jobs relating to comments, depending on the situation where you use it.

When a region is active (see The Mark and the Region), M-; either adds comment delimiters to the region, or removes them. If every line in the region is already a comment, it uncomments each of those lines by removing their comment delimiters. Otherwise, it adds comment delimiters to enclose the text in the region.

If you supply a prefix argument to M-; when a region is active, that specifies the number of comment delimiters to add or delete. A positive argument n adds n delimiters, while a negative argument −n removes n delimiters.

If the region is not active, and there is no existing comment on the current line, M-; adds a new comment to the current line. If the line is blank (i.e., empty or containing only whitespace characters), the comment is indented to the same position where TAB would indent to (see Basic Program Indentation Commands). If the line is non-blank, the comment is placed after the last non-whitespace character on the line. Emacs tries to fit the comment between the columns specified by the variables comment-column and comment-fill-column (see Options Controlling Comments), if possible. Otherwise, it will choose some other suitable position, usually separated from the non-comment text by at least one space. In each case, Emacs places point after the comment’s starting delimiter, so that you can start typing the comment text right away.

You can also use M-; to align an existing comment. If a line already contains the comment-start string, M-; realigns it to the conventional alignment and moves point after the comment’s starting delimiter. As an exception, comments starting in column 0 are not moved. Even when an existing comment is properly aligned, M-; is still useful for moving directly to the start of the comment text.

C-x C-; (comment-line) comments or uncomments complete lines. When a region is active (see The Mark and the Region), C-x C-; either comments or uncomments the lines in the region. If the region is not active, this command comments or uncomments the line point is on. With a positive prefix argument n, it operates on n lines starting with the current one; with a negative argument −n, it affects n preceding lines. After invoking this command with a negative argument, successive invocations with a positive argument will operate on preceding lines as if the argument were negated.

C-u M-; (comment-dwim with a prefix argument) when the region is not active kills any comment on the current line, along with the whitespace before it. Since the comment is saved to the kill ring, you can reinsert it on another line by moving to the end of that line, doing C-y, and then M-; to realign the comment. You can achieve the same effect as C-u M-; by typing M-x comment-kill (comment-dwim actually calls comment-kill as a subroutine when it is given a prefix argument). Invoking comment-dwim with a prefix numeric argument, as in C-u n M-; , when there’s no active region, tells comment-kill to kill comments on n lines.

The command M-x comment-region is equivalent to calling M-; on an active region, except that it always acts on the region, even if the mark is inactive. In C mode and related modes, this command is bound to C-c C-c. The command M-x uncomment-region uncomments each line in the region; a numeric prefix argument specifies the number of comment delimiters to remove (negative arguments specify the number of comment delimiters to add).

For C-like modes, you can configure the exact effect of M-; by setting the variables c-indent-comment-alist and c-indent-comments-syntactically-p. For example, on a line ending in a closing brace, M-; puts the comment one space after the brace rather than at comment-column. For full details see Comment Commands in

The CC Mode Manual

.

27.5.2 Multiple Lines of Comments

If you are typing a comment and wish to continue it to another line, type M-j or C-M-j (default-indent-new-line). This breaks the current line, and inserts the necessary comment delimiters and indentation to continue the comment.

For languages with closing comment delimiters (e.g., ‘*/’ in C), the exact behavior of M-j depends on the value of the variable comment-multi-line. If the value is nil, the command closes the comment on the old line and starts a new comment on the new line. Otherwise, it opens a new line within the current comment delimiters.

When Auto Fill mode is on, going past the fill column while typing a comment also continues the comment, in the same way as an explicit invocation of M-j.

To turn existing lines into comment lines, use M-; with the region active, or use M-x comment-region as described in the preceding section.

You can configure C Mode such that when you type a ‘/’ at the start of a line in a multi-line block comment, this closes the comment. Enable the comment-close-slash clean-up for this. See Clean-ups in

The CC Mode Manual

.

27.5.3 Options Controlling Comments

As mentioned in Comment Commands, when the M-j command adds a comment to a line, it tries to place the comment between the columns specified by the buffer-local variables comment-column and comment-fill-column (or if that is nil, then the value of fill-column, see Explicit Fill Commands). You can set either the local value or the default value of these buffer-local variables in the usual way (see Local Variables). Alternatively, you can type C-x ; (comment-set-column) to set the value of comment-column in the current buffer to the column where point is currently located. C-u C-x ; sets the comment column to match the last comment before point in the buffer, and then does a M-; to align the current line’s comment under the previous one.

The comment commands recognize comments based on the regular expression that is the value of the variable comment-start-skip. Make sure this regexp does not match the null string. It may match more than the comment starting delimiter in the strictest sense of the word; for example, in C mode the value of the variable could be "/\\*+[ \t]*\\|//+[ \t]*" , which matches extra stars and spaces after the ‘/*’ itself, and accepts C++ style (‘//’) comments also. (Note that ‘\\’ is needed in Lisp syntax to include a ‘\’ in the string, which is needed to deny the first star its special meaning in regexp syntax. See Backslash in Regular Expressions.)

When a comment command makes a new comment, it inserts the value of comment-start as an opening comment delimiter. It also inserts the value of comment-end after point, as a closing comment delimiter. For example, in Lisp mode, comment-start is ‘";"’ and comment-end is "" (the empty string). In C mode, comment-start is "/* " and comment-end is " */".

The variable comment-padding specifies a string that the commenting commands should insert between the comment delimiter(s) and the comment text. The default, ‘" "’, specifies a single space. Alternatively, the value can be a number, which specifies that number of spaces, or nil, which means no spaces at all.

The variable comment-multi-line controls how M-j and Auto Fill mode continue comments over multiple lines. See Multiple Lines of Comments.

The variable comment-indent-function should contain a function that will be called to compute the alignment for a newly inserted comment or for aligning an existing comment. It is set differently by various major modes. The function is called with no arguments, but with point at the beginning of the comment, or at the end of a line if a new comment is to be inserted. It should return the column in which the comment ought to start. For example, the default function bases its decision on how many comment characters begin an existing comment.

Emacs also tries to align comments on adjacent lines. To override this, the function may return a cons of two (possibly equal) integers to indicate an acceptable range of indentation.

27.6 Documentation Lookup

Emacs provides several features you can use to look up the documentation of functions, variables and commands that you plan to use in your program.

27.6.1 Info Documentation Lookup

For major modes that apply to languages which have documentation in Info, you can use C-h S (info-lookup-symbol) to view the Info documentation for a symbol used in the program. You specify the symbol with the minibuffer; the default is the symbol appearing in the buffer at point. For example, in C mode this looks for the symbol in the C Library Manual. The command only works if the appropriate manual’s Info files are installed.

Emacs determines where to look for documentation for the symbol—which Info files to look in, and which indices to search—based on the major mode. You can also use M-x info-lookup-file to look for documentation for a file name.

If you use C-h S in a major mode that does not support it, it asks you to specify the symbol help mode. You should enter a command such as c-mode that would select a major mode which C-h S does support.

27.6.2 Man Page Lookup

On Unix, the main form of on-line documentation was the manual page or man page. In the GNU operating system, we aim to replace man pages with better-organized manuals that you can browse with Info (see Other Help Commands). This process is not finished, so it is still useful to read manual pages.

You can read the man page for an operating system command, library function, or system call, with the M-x man command. This prompts for a topic, with completion (see Completion), and runs the man program to format the corresponding man page. If the system permits, it runs man asynchronously, so that you can keep on editing while the page is being formatted. The result goes in a buffer named *Man topic*. These buffers use a special major mode, Man mode, that facilitates scrolling and jumping to other manual pages. For details, type C-h m while in a Man mode buffer.

Each man page belongs to one of ten or more sections, each named by a digit or by a digit and a letter. Sometimes there are man pages with the same name in different sections. To read a man page from a specific section, type ‘topic(section)’ or ‘section topic’ when M-x man prompts for the topic. For example, the man page for the C library function chmod is in section 2, but there is a shell command of the same name, whose man page is in section 1; to view the former, type M-x man RET chmod(2) RET .

If you do not specify a section, M-x man normally displays only the first man page found. On some systems, the man program accepts a ‘-a’ command-line option, which tells it to display all the man pages for the specified topic. To make use of this, change the value of the variable Man-switches to ‘"-a"’. Then, in the Man mode buffer, you can type M-n and M-p to switch between man pages in different sections. The mode line shows how many manual pages are available.

An alternative way of reading manual pages is the M-x woman command. Unlike M-x man, it does not run any external programs to format and display the man pages; the formatting is done by Emacs, so it works on systems such as MS-Windows where the man program may be unavailable. It prompts for a man page, and displays it in a buffer named *WoMan section topic.

M-x woman computes the completion list for manpages the first time you invoke the command. With a numeric argument, it recomputes this list; this is useful if you add or delete manual pages.

If you type a name of a manual page and M-x woman finds that several manual pages by the same name exist in different sections, it pops up a window with possible candidates asking you to choose one of them.

Note that M-x woman doesn’t yet support the latest features of modern man pages, so we recommend using M-x man if that is available on your system.

For more information about setting up and using M-x woman, see the WoMan Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs.

27.6.3 Programming Language Documentation Lookup

When editing Emacs Lisp code, you can use the commands C-h f (describe-function) and C-h v (describe-variable) to view the built-in documentation for the Lisp functions and variables that you want to use. See Help by Command or Variable Name.

ElDoc^14 is a buffer-local minor mode that helps with looking up documentation of symbols (functions, methods, classes, variables, etc.) in your program. When this mode is enabled, the echo area displays useful information whenever there is a documented symbol at point. For example, in buffers under the Emacs Lisp mode, it shows the argument list of a function at point, and for a Lisp variable it shows the first line of the variable’s documentation string.

To toggle ElDoc mode, type M-x eldoc-mode. There’s also a Global ElDoc mode, which is turned on by default, and turns on the ElDoc mode in buffers whose major mode sets the variables described below. Use M-x global-eldoc-mode to turn it off globally.

Various major modes configure the Global ElDoc mode to use their documentation functions. Examples include Emacs Lisp mode, Python mode, and Cfengine mode. In addition, Emacs features that provide support for several major modes configure ElDoc to use their facilities for retrieving the documentation. Examples include Eglot (see Eglot Features in

Eglot: The Emacs LSP Client

), which provides documentation based on information from language servers; Semantic’s Idle Summary mode (see Idle Summary Mode in

Semantic Manual

); and Flymake, which uses ElDoc to show diagnostics at point (see Finding diagnostics in

GNU Flymake manual

).

The ElDoc mode works by scheduling the display of the available documentation for the symbol at point after Emacs has been idle for some short time. This avoids annoying flickering of documentation messages in the echo area or the mode line when you type quickly and without delay.

You can also trigger the display of documentation for a symbol at point by using the command M-x eldoc-print-current-symbol-info.

The following variables can be used to configure ElDoc mode:

eldoc-idle-delay

The value of this user option controls the amount of idle time before the at-point documentation is displayed. It should be set to the number of seconds to wait; the value of zero means to display without any delay. The default is 0.5 sec.

eldoc-print-after-edit

If this user option is non-nil, ElDoc will show documentation only after some editing command, like inserting or deleting some text. This comes in handy if you want Emacs to display documentation only about symbols that you type, but not about symbols that are already in the buffer (so just reading the source code will not show documentation). The default value is nil. If you change the value, you need to toggle eldoc-mode off and on again.

eldoc-echo-area-use-multiline-p

This user option controls whether and how to truncate documentation text if it is longer than the echo-area can display as a single screen line. If the value is a positive number, it specifies the number of screen lines that ElDoc is allowed to display in the echo area without truncating the documentation. A positive integer specifies the absolute maximum number of screen lines to use; a floating-point number specifies the number of screen lines as a fraction of the frame’s height. The value of t means never truncate the documentation (the echo-area will be resized up to the height allowed by max-mini-window-height, see Editing in the Minibuffer), whereas the value of nil means truncate if the documentation is longer than a single screen line. Finally, the special value truncate-sym-name-if-fit (the default) means to truncate the part of the documentation that represents a symbol’s name if doing that will allow the documentation to fit on a single screen line.

eldoc-echo-area-display-truncation-message

If non-nil (the default), and documentation shown in the echo area is truncated because it’s too long, follow the documentation by instructions about how to view the complete documentation text. If nil, just indicate with ‘…’ that the documentation was truncated.

eldoc-echo-area-prefer-doc-buffer

If the value of this user option is t, ElDoc will not show the documentation in the echo area if the ElDoc buffer with the documentation is already displayed in some window. (You can use the command M-x eldoc-doc-buffer any time to show the ElDoc buffer.) If the value of this option is the symbol maybe, the documentation will not be displayed in the echo area if the ElDoc buffer is shown in some window, and the documentation text has to be truncated if displayed in the echo area. Finally, the value of nil (the default) means always show the documentation in the echo area.

eldoc-documentation-strategy

This customizable variable’s value is the function which is used to retrieve and display documentation for the symbol at point. The documentation is produced by the functions in the hook eldoc-documentation-functions. The default value of eldoc-documentation-strategy specifies that ElDoc should display the first documentation text produced by functions in the eldoc-documentation-functions hook, but you can customize eldoc-documentation-strategy to work in other ways, such as displaying all of the documentation texts concatenated together.

eldoc-documentation-functions

This abnormal hook’s value is a list of functions that can produce documentation for the symbol at point as appropriate for the current buffer’s major-mode. These functions act as a collection of backends for ElDoc. Major modes register their documentation lookup functions with ElDoc by adding their functions to the buffer-local value of this variable.

27.7 Hideshow minor mode

Hideshow mode is a buffer-local minor mode that allows you to selectively display portions of a program, which are referred to as blocks. Type M-x hs-minor-mode to toggle this minor mode (see Minor Modes).

When you use Hideshow mode to hide a block, the block disappears from the screen, to be replaced by an ellipsis (three periods in a row). Just what constitutes a block depends on the major mode. In C mode and related modes, blocks are delimited by braces, while in Lisp mode they are delimited by parentheses. Multi-line comments also count as blocks.

Hideshow mode provides the following commands:

C-c @ C-h
C-c @ C-d

Hide the current block (hs-hide-block).

C-c @ C-s

Show the current block (hs-show-block).

C-c @ C-c
C-c @ C-e
S-mouse-2

Either hide or show the current block (hs-toggle-hiding).

C-c @ C-M-h
C-c @ C-t

Hide all top-level blocks (hs-hide-all).

C-c @ C-M-s
C-c @ C-a

Show all blocks in the buffer (hs-show-all).

C-u n C-c @ C-l

Hide all blocks n levels below this block (hs-hide-level).

These variables can be used to customize Hideshow mode:

hs-hide-comments-when-hiding-all

If non-nil, C-c @ C-M-h (hs-hide-all) hides comments too.

hs-isearch-open

This variable specifies the conditions under which incremental search should unhide a hidden block when matching text occurs within the block. Its value should be either code (unhide only code blocks), comment (unhide only comments), t (unhide both code blocks and comments), or nil (unhide neither code blocks nor comments). The default value is code.

27.8 Completion for Symbol Names

Completion is normally done in the minibuffer (see Completion), but you can also complete symbol names in ordinary Emacs buffers.

In most programming language modes, C-M-i (or M-TAB^15) invokes the command completion-at-point, which generates the list of possible completions for the symbol at point. This command uses the available support facilities to come up with the completion candidates:

If Eglot is activated for the current buffer’s project (see Working with Projects) and the current buffer’s major mode, the command tries to use the corresponding language server for producing the list of completion candidates. See Eglot Features in

Eglot: The Emacs LSP Client

.
If Semantic mode is enabled (see Semantic), the command tries to use the Semantic parser data for completion.
If Semantic mode is not enabled or fails at performing completion, the command tries to complete using the selected tags table (see Tags Tables); you need to visit the tags table with M-x visit-tags-table for that to work.
In Emacs Lisp mode, the command performs completion using the function, variable, or property names defined in the current Emacs session.

In all other respects, in-buffer symbol completion behaves like minibuffer completion. For instance, if Emacs cannot complete to a unique symbol, it displays a list of completion alternatives in another window. Then you can use the keys M-DOWN and M-UP to navigate through the completions displayed in the completions buffer without leaving the original buffer, and the key M-RET to insert the currently highlighted completion to the buffer. See Completion.

In Text mode and related modes, M-TAB completes words based on the spell-checker’s dictionary. See Checking and Correcting Spelling.

27.9 MixedCase Words

Some programming styles make use of mixed-case (or “CamelCase”) symbols like ‘unReadableSymbol’. (In the GNU project, we recommend using underscores to separate words within an identifier, rather than using case distinctions.) Emacs has various features to make it easier to deal with such symbols.

Glasses mode is a buffer-local minor mode that makes it easier to read such symbols, by altering how they are displayed. By default, it displays extra underscores between each lower-case letter and the following capital letter. This does not alter the buffer text, only how it is displayed.

To toggle Glasses mode, type M-x glasses-mode (see Minor Modes). When Glasses mode is enabled, the minor mode indicator ‘o^o’ appears in the mode line. For more information about Glasses mode, type C-h P glasses RET.

Subword mode is another buffer-local minor mode. In subword mode, Emacs’s word commands recognize upper case letters in ‘StudlyCapsIdentifiers’ as word boundaries. When Subword mode is enabled, the minor mode indicator ‘,’ appears in the mode line. See also the similar superword-mode (see Other Features Useful for Editing Programs).

27.10 Semantic

Semantic is a package that provides language-aware editing commands based on source code parsers. This section provides a brief description of Semantic; for full details, see Semantic in

Semantic

.

Most of the language-aware features in Emacs, such as Font Lock mode (see Font Lock mode), rely on rules of thumb^16 that usually give good results but are never completely exact. In contrast, the parsers used by Semantic have an exact understanding of programming language syntax. This allows Semantic to provide search, navigation, and completion commands that are powerful and precise.

To begin using Semantic, type M-x semantic-mode or click on the menu item named ‘Source Code Parsers (Semantic)’ in the ‘Tools’ menu. This enables Semantic mode, a global minor mode.

When Semantic mode is enabled, Emacs automatically attempts to parse each file you visit. Currently, Semantic understands C, C++, HTML, Java, Javascript, Make, Python, Scheme, SRecode, and Texinfo. Within each parsed buffer, the following commands are available:

C-c , j

Prompt for the name of a function defined in the current file, and move point there (semantic-complete-jump-local).

C-c , J

Prompt for the name of a function defined in any file Emacs has parsed, and move point there (semantic-complete-jump).

C-c , SPC

Display a list of possible completions for the symbol at point (semantic-complete-analyze-inline). This also activates a set of special key bindings for choosing a completion: RET accepts the current completion, M-n and M-p cycle through possible completions, TAB completes as far as possible and then cycles, and C-g or any other key aborts completion.

C-c , l

Display a list of the possible completions of the symbol at point, in another window (semantic-analyze-possible-completions).

In addition to the above commands, the Semantic package provides a variety of other ways to make use of parser information. For instance, you can use it to display a list of completions when Emacs is idle. See Semantic in

Semantic

, for details.

27.11 Other Features Useful for Editing Programs

Some Emacs commands that aren’t designed specifically for editing programs are useful for that nonetheless.

The Emacs commands that operate on words, sentences and paragraphs are useful for editing code. Most symbol names contain words (see Words), while sentences can be found in strings and comments (see Sentences). As for paragraphs, they are defined in most programming language modes to begin and end at blank lines (see Paragraphs). Therefore, judicious use of blank lines to make the program clearer will also provide useful chunks of text for the paragraph commands to work on. Auto Fill mode, if enabled in a programming language major mode, indents the new lines which it creates.

Superword mode is a buffer-local minor mode that causes editing and motion commands to treat symbols (e.g., ‘this_is_a_symbol’) as words. When Superword mode is enabled, the minor mode indicator ‘²’ appears in the mode line. See also the similar subword-mode (see MixedCase Words).

Electric Layout mode (M-x electric-layout-mode) is a global minor mode that automatically inserts newlines when you type certain characters; for example, ‘{’, ‘}’ and ‘;’ in Javascript mode.

Apart from Hideshow mode (see Hideshow minor mode), another way to selectively display parts of a program is to use the selective display feature (see Selective Display). Programming modes often also support Outline minor mode (see Outline Mode), which can be used with the Foldout package (see Folding Editing).

Prettify Symbols mode is a buffer-local minor mode that replaces certain strings with more attractive versions for display purposes. For example, in Emacs Lisp mode, it replaces the string ‘lambda’ with the Greek lambda character ‘λ’. In a TeX buffer, it will replace ‘\alpha’ … ‘\omega’ and other math macros with their Unicode characters. You may wish to use this in non-programming modes as well. You can customize the mode by adding more entries to prettify-symbols-alist. More elaborate customization is available via customizing prettify-symbols-compose-predicate if its default value prettify-symbols-default-compose-p is not appropriate. There is also a global version, global-prettify-symbols-mode, which enables the mode in all buffers that support it.

The symbol at point can be shown in its original form. This is controlled by the variable prettify-symbols-unprettify-at-point: if non-nil, the original form of symbol at point will be restored for as long as point is at it.

27.12 C and Related Modes

This section gives a brief description of the special features available in C, C++, Objective-C, Java, CORBA IDL, Pike and AWK modes. (These are called “C mode and related modes”.) For more details, see the CC mode Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs.

27.12.1 C Mode Motion Commands

This section describes commands for moving point, in C mode and related modes.

C-M-a
C-M-e

Move point to the beginning or end of the current function or top-level definition. In languages with enclosing scopes (such as C++’s classes) the current function is the immediate one, possibly inside a scope. Otherwise it is the one defined by the least enclosing braces. (By contrast, beginning-of-defun and end-of-defun search for braces in column zero.) See Moving by Defuns.

C-c C-u

Move point back to the containing preprocessor conditional, leaving the mark behind. A prefix argument acts as a repeat count. With a negative argument, move point forward to the end of the containing preprocessor conditional.

‘#elif’ is equivalent to ‘#else’ followed by ‘#if’, so the function will stop at a ‘#elif’ when going backward, but not when going forward.

C-c C-p

Move point back over a preprocessor conditional, leaving the mark behind. A prefix argument acts as a repeat count. With a negative argument, move forward.

C-c C-n

Move point forward across a preprocessor conditional, leaving the mark behind. A prefix argument acts as a repeat count. With a negative argument, move backward.

M-a

Move point to the beginning of the innermost C statement (c-beginning-of-statement). If point is already at the beginning of a statement, move to the beginning of the preceding statement. With prefix argument n, move back n − 1 statements.

In comments or in strings which span more than one line, this command moves by sentences instead of statements.

M-e

Move point to the end of the innermost C statement or sentence; like M-a except that it moves in the other direction (c-end-of-statement).

27.12.2 Electric C Characters

In C mode and related modes, certain printing characters are electric—in addition to inserting themselves, they also reindent the current line, and optionally also insert newlines. The electric characters are {, }, :, #, ;, ,, <, >, /, *, (, and ).

You might find electric indentation inconvenient if you are editing chaotically indented code. If you are new to CC Mode, you might find it disconcerting. You can toggle electric action with the command C-c C-l; when it is enabled, ‘/cl’ appears in the mode line after the mode name (where c, if present, is ‘*’ or ‘/’, depending on whether the comment style is block or line). See Minor Modes in

The CC Mode Manual

, for more about mode-line indicators in CC Mode.

C-c C-l

Toggle electric action (c-toggle-electric-state). With a positive prefix argument, this command enables electric action, with a negative one it disables it.

Electric characters insert newlines only when, in addition to the electric state, the auto-newline feature is enabled (indicated by ‘/cla’ in the mode line after the mode name). You can turn this feature on or off with the command C-c C-a:

C-c C-a

Toggle the auto-newline feature (c-toggle-auto-newline). With a prefix argument, this command turns the auto-newline feature on if the argument is positive, and off if it is negative.

Usually the CC Mode style configures the exact circumstances in which Emacs inserts auto-newlines. You can also configure this directly. See Custom Auto-newlines in

The CC Mode Manual

.

27.12.3 Hungry Delete Feature in C

If you want to delete an entire block of whitespace at point, you can use hungry deletion. This deletes all the contiguous whitespace either before point or after point in a single operation. Whitespace here includes tabs and newlines, but not comments or preprocessor commands.

C-c C-DEL
C-c DEL

Delete the entire block of whitespace preceding point (c-hungry-delete-backwards).

C-c C-d
C-c C-Delete
C-c Delete

Delete the entire block of whitespace after point (c-hungry-delete-forward).

As an alternative to the above commands, you can enable hungry delete mode. When this feature is enabled (indicated by ‘h’ after a ‘/’ in the mode line after the mode name), a single DEL deletes all preceding whitespace, not just one space, and a single C-d (but not plain Delete) deletes all following whitespace.

M-x c-toggle-hungry-state

Toggle the hungry-delete feature (c-toggle-hungry-state). With a prefix argument, this command turns the hungry-delete feature on if the argument is positive, and off if it is negative.

The variable c-hungry-delete-key controls whether the hungry-delete feature is enabled.

27.12.4 Other Commands for C Mode

M-x c-context-line-break

This command inserts a line break and indents the new line in a manner appropriate to the context. In normal code, it does the work of RET (newline), in a C preprocessor line it additionally inserts a ‘\’ at the line break, and within comments it’s like M-j (c-indent-new-comment-line).

c-context-line-break isn’t bound to a key by default, but it needs a binding to be useful. The following code will bind it to RET. We use c-initialization-hook here to make sure the keymap is loaded before we try to change it.

(defun my-bind-clb ()
  (keymap-set c-mode-base-map "RET"
              'c-context-line-break))
(add-hook 'c-initialization-hook 'my-bind-clb)

C-M-h

Put mark at the end of a function definition, and put point at the beginning (c-mark-function).

M-q

Fill a paragraph, handling C and C++ comments (c-fill-paragraph). If any part of the current line is a comment or within a comment, this command fills the comment or the paragraph of it that point is in, preserving the comment indentation and comment delimiters.

C-c C-e

Run the C preprocessor on the text in the region, and show the result, which includes the expansion of all the macro calls (c-macro-expand). The buffer text before the region is also included in preprocessing, for the sake of macros defined there, but the output from this part isn’t shown.

When you are debugging C code that uses macros, sometimes it is hard to figure out precisely how the macros expand. With this command, you don’t have to figure it out; you can see the expansions.

C-c C-\

Insert or align ‘\’ characters at the ends of the lines of the region (c-backslash-region). This is useful after writing or editing a C macro definition.

If a line already ends in ‘\’, this command adjusts the amount of whitespace before it. Otherwise, it inserts a new ‘\’. However, the last line in the region is treated specially; no ‘\’ is inserted on that line, and any ‘\’ there is deleted.

M-x cpp-highlight-buffer

Highlight parts of the text according to its preprocessor conditionals. This command displays another buffer named *CPP Edit*, which serves as a graphic menu for selecting how to display particular kinds of conditionals and their contents. After changing various settings, click on ‘[A]pply these settings’ (or go to that buffer and type a) to rehighlight the C mode buffer accordingly.

C-c C-s

Display the syntactic information about the current source line (c-show-syntactic-information). This information directs how the line is indented.

M-x cwarn-mode
M-x global-cwarn-mode

CWarn minor mode highlights certain suspicious C and C++ constructions:

Assignments inside expressions.
Semicolon following immediately after ‘if’, ‘for’, and ‘while’ (except after a ‘do … while’ statement);
C++ functions with reference parameters.

You can enable the mode for one buffer with the command M-x cwarn-mode, or for all suitable buffers with the command M-x global-cwarn-mode or by customizing the variable global-cwarn-mode. You must also enable Font Lock mode to make it work.

M-x hide-ifdef-mode

Hide-ifdef minor mode hides selected code within ‘#if’ and ‘#ifdef’ preprocessor blocks. If you change the variable hide-ifdef-shadow to t, Hide-ifdef minor mode shadows preprocessor blocks by displaying them with a less prominent face, instead of hiding them entirely. See the documentation string of hide-ifdef-mode for more information.

M-x ff-find-related-file

Find a file related in a special way to the file visited by the current buffer. Typically this will be the header file corresponding to a C/C++ source file, or vice versa. The variable ff-related-file-alist specifies how to compute related file names.

27.13 Asm Mode

Asm mode is a major mode for editing files of assembler code. It defines these commands:

TAB

tab-to-tab-stop.

C-j

Insert a newline and then indent using tab-to-tab-stop.

:

Insert a colon and then remove the indentation from before the label preceding colon. Then do tab-to-tab-stop.

;

Insert or align a comment.

The variable asm-comment-char specifies which character starts comments in assembler syntax.

27.14 Fortran Mode

Fortran mode is meant for editing fixed form (and also tab format) source code (normally Fortran 77). For editing more modern free-form source code (Fortran 90, 95, 2003, 2008), use F90 mode (f90-mode). Emacs normally uses Fortran mode for files with extension ‘.f’, ‘.F’ or ‘.for’, and F90 mode for the extensions ‘.f90’, ‘.f95’, ‘.f03’ and ‘.f08’. Customize auto-mode-alist to add more extensions. GNU Fortran supports both free and fixed form. This manual mainly documents Fortran mode, but the corresponding F90 mode features are mentioned when relevant.

Fortran mode provides special motion commands for Fortran statements and subprograms, and indentation commands that understand Fortran conventions of nesting, line numbers and continuation statements. Fortran mode has support for Auto Fill mode that breaks long lines into proper Fortran continuation lines. Fortran mode also supports Hideshow minor mode (see Hideshow minor mode), and Imenu (see Imenu).

Special commands for comments are provided because Fortran comments are unlike those of other languages. Built-in abbrevs optionally save typing when you insert Fortran keywords.

Use M-x fortran-mode to switch to this major mode. This command runs the hook fortran-mode-hook. See Hooks.

27.14.1 Motion Commands

In addition to the normal commands for moving by and operating on defuns (Fortran subprograms—functions and subroutines, as well as modules for F90 mode, using the commands fortran-end-of-subprogram and fortran-beginning-of-subprogram), Fortran mode provides special commands to move by statements and other program units.

C-c C-n

Move to the beginning of the next statement (fortran-next-statement/f90-next-statement).

C-c C-p

Move to the beginning of the previous statement (fortran-previous-statement/f90-previous-statement). If there is no previous statement (i.e., if called from the first statement in the buffer), move to the start of the buffer.

C-c C-e

Move point forward to the start of the next code block, or the end of the current one, whichever comes first (f90-next-block). A code block is a subroutine, if–endif statement, and so forth. This command exists for F90 mode only, not Fortran mode. With a numeric argument, it moves forward that many blocks.

C-c C-a

Move point backward to the previous block (f90-previous-block). This is like f90-next-block, but moves backwards.

C-M-n

Move to the end of the current code block (fortran-end-of-block/f90-end-of-block). With a numeric argument, move forward that number of blocks. The mark is set before moving point. The F90 mode version of this command checks for consistency of block types and labels (if present), but it does not check the outermost block since that may be incomplete.

C-M-p

Move to the start of the current code block (fortran-beginning-of-block/f90-beginning-of-block). This is like fortran-end-of-block, but moves backwards.

The commands fortran-beginning-of-subprogram and fortran-end-of-subprogram move to the start or end of the current subprogram, respectively. The commands fortran-mark-do and fortran-mark-if mark the end of the current do or if block, and move point to the start.

27.14.2 Fortran Indentation

Special commands and features are needed for indenting fixed (or tab) form Fortran code in order to make sure various syntactic entities (line numbers, comment line indicators and continuation line flags) appear in the required columns.

27.14.2.1 Fortran Indentation and Filling Commands

C-M-j

Break the current line at point and set up a continuation line (fortran-split-line).

M-^

Join this line to the previous line (fortran-join-line).

C-M-q

Indent all the lines of the subprogram that point is in (fortran-indent-subprogram).

M-q

Fill a comment block or statement (using fortran-fill-paragraph or fortran-fill-statement).

The key C-M-q runs fortran-indent-subprogram, a command to reindent all the lines of the Fortran subprogram (function or subroutine) containing point.

The key C-M-j runs fortran-split-line, which splits a line in the appropriate fashion for Fortran. In a non-comment line, the second half becomes a continuation line and is indented accordingly. In a comment line, both halves become separate comment lines.

M-^ or C-c C-d run the command fortran-join-line, which joins a continuation line back to the previous line, roughly as the inverse of fortran-split-line. The point must be on a continuation line when this command is invoked.

M-q in Fortran mode fills the comment block or statement that point is in. This removes any excess statement continuations.

27.14.2.2 Continuation Lines

Most Fortran 77 compilers allow two ways of writing continuation lines. If the first non-space character on a line is in column 5, then that line is a continuation of the previous line. We call this fixed form. (In GNU Emacs we always count columns from 0; but note that the Fortran standard counts from 1. You can customize the variable column-number-indicator-zero-based to make the column display Fortran-like; see Optional Mode Line Features.) The variable fortran-continuation-string specifies what character to put in column 5. A line that starts with a tab character followed by any digit except ‘0’ is also a continuation line. We call this style of continuation tab format. (Fortran 90 introduced free-form continuation lines.)

Fortran mode can use either style of continuation line. When you enter Fortran mode, it tries to deduce the proper continuation style automatically from the buffer contents. It does this by scanning up to fortran-analyze-depth (default 100) lines from the start of the buffer. The first line that begins with either a tab character or six spaces determines the choice. If the scan fails (for example, if the buffer is new and therefore empty), the value of fortran-tab-mode-default (nil for fixed form, and non-nil for tab format) is used. ‘/t’ (fortran-tab-mode-string) in the mode line indicates tab format is selected. Fortran mode sets the value of indent-tabs-mode accordingly.

If the text on a line starts with the Fortran continuation marker ‘$’, or if it begins with any non-whitespace character in column 5, Fortran mode treats it as a continuation line. When you indent a continuation line with TAB, it converts the line to the current continuation style. When you split a Fortran statement with C-M-j, the continuation marker on the newline is created according to the continuation style.

The setting of continuation style affects several other aspects of editing in Fortran mode. In fixed form mode, the minimum column number for the body of a statement is 6. Lines inside of Fortran blocks that are indented to larger column numbers must use only the space character for whitespace. In tab format mode, the minimum column number for the statement body is 8, and the whitespace before column 8 must consist of one tab character.

27.14.2.3 Line Numbers

If a number is the first non-whitespace in the line, Fortran indentation assumes it is a line number and moves it to columns 0 through 4. (Columns always count from 0 in Emacs, but setting column-number-indicator-zero-based to nil can change that, see Optional Mode Line Features.)

Line numbers of four digits or less are normally indented one space. The variable fortran-line-number-indent controls this; it specifies the maximum indentation a line number can have. The default value of the variable is 1. Fortran mode tries to prevent line number digits passing column 4, reducing the indentation below the specified maximum if necessary. If fortran-line-number-indent has the value 5, line numbers are right-justified to end in column 4.

Simply inserting a line number is enough to indent it according to these rules. As each digit is inserted, the indentation is recomputed. To turn off this feature, set the variable fortran-electric-line-number to nil.

27.14.2.4 Syntactic Conventions

Fortran mode assumes that you follow certain conventions that simplify the task of understanding a Fortran program well enough to indent it properly:

Two nested ‘do’ loops never share a ‘continue’ statement.
Fortran keywords such as ‘if’, ‘else’, ‘then’, ‘do’ and others are written without embedded whitespace or line breaks.

Fortran compilers generally ignore whitespace outside of string constants, but Fortran mode does not recognize these keywords if they are not contiguous. Constructs such as ‘else if’ or ‘end do’ are acceptable, but the second word should be on the same line as the first and not on a continuation line.

If you fail to follow these conventions, the indentation commands may indent some lines unaesthetically. However, a correct Fortran program retains its meaning when reindented even if the conventions are not followed.

27.14.2.5 Variables for Fortran Indentation

Several additional variables control how Fortran indentation works:

fortran-do-indent

Extra indentation within each level of ‘do’ statement (default 3).

fortran-if-indent

Extra indentation within each level of ‘if’, ‘select case’, or ‘where’ statements (default 3).

fortran-structure-indent

Extra indentation within each level of ‘structure’, ‘union’, ‘map’, or ‘interface’ statements (default 3).

fortran-continuation-indent

Extra indentation for bodies of continuation lines (default 5).

fortran-check-all-num-for-matching-do

In Fortran 77, a numbered ‘do’ statement is terminated by any statement with a matching line number. It is common (but not compulsory) to use a ‘continue’ statement for this purpose. If this variable has a non-nil value, indenting any numbered statement must check for a ‘do’ that ends there. If you always end ‘do’ statements with a ‘continue’ line (or if you use the more modern ‘enddo’), then you can speed up indentation by setting this variable to nil (the default).

fortran-blink-matching-if

If this is t, indenting an ‘endif’ (or ‘enddo’) statement moves the cursor momentarily to the matching ‘if’ (or ‘do’) statement to show where it is. The default is nil.

fortran-minimum-statement-indent-fixed

Minimum indentation for Fortran statements when using fixed form continuation line style. Statement bodies are never indented by less than this. The default is 6.

fortran-minimum-statement-indent-tab

Minimum indentation for Fortran statements for tab format continuation line style. Statement bodies are never indented by less than this. The default is 8.

The following section describes the variables controlling the indentation of comments.

27.14.3 Fortran Comments

The usual Emacs comment commands assume that a comment can follow a line of code. In Fortran 77, the standard comment syntax requires an entire line to be just a comment. Therefore, Fortran mode replaces the standard Emacs comment commands and defines some new variables.

Fortran mode can also handle the Fortran 90 comment syntax where comments start with ‘!’ and can follow other text. Because only some Fortran 77 compilers accept this syntax, Fortran mode will not insert such comments unless you have said in advance to do so. To do this, set the variable fortran-comment-line-start to ‘"!"’. If you use an unusual value, you may need to change fortran-comment-line-start-skip.

M-;

Align comment or insert new comment (comment-dwim).

C-x ;

Applies to nonstandard ‘!’ comments only (comment-set-column).

C-c ;

Turn all lines of the region into comments, or (with argument) turn them back into real code (fortran-comment-region).

M-; in Fortran mode runs the standard comment-dwim. This recognizes any kind of existing comment and aligns its text appropriately; if there is no existing comment, a comment is inserted and aligned. Inserting and aligning comments are not the same in Fortran mode as in other modes.

When a new comment must be inserted, if the current line is blank, a full-line comment is inserted. On a non-blank line, a nonstandard ‘!’ comment is inserted if you have said you want to use them. Otherwise, a full-line comment is inserted on a new line before the current line.

Nonstandard ‘!’ comments are aligned like comments in other languages, but full-line comments are different. In a standard full-line comment, the comment delimiter itself must always appear in column zero. What can be aligned is the text within the comment. You can choose from three styles of alignment by setting the variable fortran-comment-indent-style to one of these values:

fixed

Align the text at a fixed column, which is the sum of fortran-comment-line-extra-indent and the minimum statement indentation. This is the default.

The minimum indentation is fortran-minimum-statement-indent-tab for tab format continuation line style and fortran-minimum-statement-indent-fixed for fixed form style.

relative

Align the text as if it were a line of code, but with an additional fortran-comment-line-extra-indent columns of indentation.

nil

Don’t move text in full-line comments automatically.

In addition, you can specify the character to be used to indent within full-line comments by setting the variable fortran-comment-indent-char to the single-character string you want to use.

Compiler directive lines, or preprocessor lines, have much the same appearance as comment lines. It is important, though, that such lines never be indented at all, no matter what the value of fortran-comment-indent-style. The variable fortran-directive-re is a regular expression that specifies which lines are directives. Matching lines are never indented, and receive distinctive font-locking.

The normal Emacs comment command C-x ; (comment-set-column) has not been redefined. If you use ‘!’ comments, this command can be used with them. Otherwise, it is useless in Fortran mode.

The command C-c ; (fortran-comment-region) turns all the lines of the region into comments by inserting the string ‘c$$$’ at the front of each one. With a numeric argument, it turns the region back into live code by deleting ‘c$$$’ from the front of each line in it. The string used for these comments can be controlled by setting the variable fortran-comment-region. Note that here we have an example of a command and a variable with the same name; these two uses of the name never conflict because in Lisp and in Emacs it is always clear from the context which one is meant.

27.14.4 Auto Fill in Fortran Mode

Fortran mode has specialized support for Auto Fill mode, which is a minor mode that automatically splits statements as you insert them when they become too wide. Splitting a statement involves making continuation lines using fortran-continuation-string (see Continuation Lines). This splitting happens when you type SPC, RET, or TAB, and also in the Fortran indentation commands. You activate Auto Fill in Fortran mode in the normal way. See Auto Fill Mode.

Auto Fill breaks lines at spaces or delimiters when the lines get longer than the desired width (the value of fill-column). The delimiters (besides whitespace) that Auto Fill can break at are ‘+’, ‘-’, ‘/’, ‘*’, ‘=’, ‘<’, ‘>’, and ‘,’. The line break comes after the delimiter if the variable fortran-break-before-delimiters is nil. Otherwise (and by default), the break comes before the delimiter.

To enable Auto Fill in all Fortran buffers, add auto-fill-mode to fortran-mode-hook. See Hooks.

27.14.5 Checking Columns in Fortran

In standard Fortran 77, anything beyond column 72 is ignored. Most compilers provide an option to change this (for example, ‘-ffixed-line-length-N’ in gfortran). Customize the variable fortran-line-length to change the line length in Fortran mode. Anything beyond this point is font-locked as a comment. (Unless it is inside a string: strings that extend beyond fortran-line-length will confuse font-lock.)

C-c C-r

Display a column ruler momentarily above the current line (fortran-column-ruler).

C-c C-w

Split the current window horizontally temporarily so that it is fortran-line-length columns wide (fortran-window-create-momentarily). This may help you avoid making lines longer than the limit imposed by your Fortran compiler.

C-u C-c C-w

Split the current window horizontally so that it is fortran-line-length columns wide (fortran-window-create). You can then continue editing.

M-x fortran-strip-sequence-nos

Delete all text in column fortran-line-length and beyond.

The command C-c C-r (fortran-column-ruler) shows a column ruler momentarily above the current line. The comment ruler is two lines of text that show you the locations of columns with special significance in Fortran programs. Square brackets show the limits of the columns for line numbers, and curly brackets show the limits of the columns for the statement body. Column numbers appear above them.

Note that the column numbers count from zero, as always in GNU Emacs (but customizing column-number-indicator-zero-based can change column display to match that of Fortran; see Optional Mode Line Features.) As a result, the numbers may be one less than those you are familiar with; but the positions they indicate in the line are standard for Fortran.

The text used to display the column ruler depends on the value of the variable indent-tabs-mode. If indent-tabs-mode is nil, then the value of the variable fortran-column-ruler-fixed is used as the column ruler. Otherwise, the value of the variable fortran-column-ruler-tab is displayed. By changing these variables, you can change the column ruler display.

C-c C-w (fortran-window-create-momentarily) temporarily splits the current window horizontally, making a window fortran-line-length columns wide, so you can see any lines that are too long. Type a space to restore the normal width.

You can also split the window horizontally and continue editing with the split in place. To do this, use C-u C-c C-w (M-x fortran-window-create). By editing in this window you can immediately see when you make a line too wide to be correct Fortran.

The command M-x fortran-strip-sequence-nos deletes all text in column fortran-line-length and beyond, on all lines in the current buffer. This is the easiest way to get rid of old sequence numbers.

27.14.6 Fortran Keyword Abbrevs

Fortran mode provides many built-in abbrevs for common keywords and declarations. These are the same sort of abbrev that you can define yourself. To use them, you must turn on Abbrev mode. See Abbrevs.

The built-in abbrevs are unusual in one way: they all start with a semicolon. For example, one built-in Fortran abbrev is ‘;c’ for ‘continue’. If you insert ‘;c’ and then insert a punctuation character such as a space or a newline, the ‘;c’ expands automatically to ‘continue’, provided Abbrev mode is enabled.

Type ‘;?’ or ‘;C-h’ to display a list of all the built-in Fortran abbrevs and what they stand for.

Footnotes

(13)

The word “sexp” is used to refer to an expression in Lisp.

(14)

The name “ElDoc” is a historical accident: this mode started by supporting Emacs Lisp buffers.

(15)

On graphical displays, the M-TAB key is usually reserved by the window manager for switching graphical windows, so you should type C-M-i or ESC TAB instead.

(16)

Regular expressions and syntax tables.

51 Quitting and Aborting

C-g
C-Break (MS-DOS only)

Quit: cancel running or partially typed command.

C-]

Abort innermost recursive editing level and cancel the command which invoked it (abort-recursive-edit).

ESC ESC ESC

Either quit or abort, whichever makes sense (keyboard-escape-quit).

M-x top-level

Abort all recursive editing levels that are currently executing.

C-/
C-x u
C-_

Cancel a previously made change in the buffer contents (undo).

There are two ways of canceling a command before it has finished: quitting with C-g, and aborting with C-] or M-x top-level. Quitting cancels a partially typed command, or one which is still running. Aborting exits a recursive editing level and cancels the command that invoked the recursive edit (see Recursive Editing Levels).

Quitting with C-g is the way to get rid of a partially typed command, or a numeric argument that you don’t want. Furthermore, if you are in the middle of a command that is running, C-g stops the command in a relatively safe way. For example, if you quit out of a kill command that is taking a long time, either your text will all still be in the buffer, or it will all be in the kill ring, or maybe both. If the region is active, C-g deactivates the mark, unless Transient Mark mode is off (see Disabling Transient Mark Mode). If you are in the middle of an incremental search, C-g behaves specially; it may take two successive C-g characters to get out of a search. See Incremental Search, for details.

If you type C-g in a minibuffer, this quits the command that opened that minibuffer, closing it. If that minibuffer is not the most recently opened one (which can happen when minibuffer-follows-selected-frame is nil (see Using the Minibuffer)), C-g also closes the more recently opened ones, quitting their associated commands, after asking you for confirmation.

On MS-DOS, the character C-Break serves as a quit character like C-g. The reason is that it is not feasible, on MS-DOS, to recognize C-g while a command is running, between interactions with the user. By contrast, it is feasible to recognize C-Break at all times. See Keyboard Usage on MS-DOS.

C-g works by setting the variable quit-flag to t the instant C-g is typed; Emacs Lisp checks this variable frequently, and quits if it is non-nil. C-g is only actually executed as a command if you type it while Emacs is waiting for input. In that case, the command it runs is keyboard-quit.

On a text terminal, if you quit with C-g a second time before the first C-g is recognized, you activate the emergency-escape feature and return to the shell. See Emergency Escape.

There are some situations where you cannot quit. When Emacs is waiting for the operating system to do something, quitting is impossible unless special pains are taken for the particular system call within Emacs where the waiting occurs. We have done this for the system calls that users are likely to want to quit from, but it’s possible you will encounter a case not handled. In one very common case—waiting for file input or output using NFS—Emacs itself knows how to quit, but many NFS implementations simply do not allow user programs to stop waiting for NFS when the NFS server is hung.

Aborting with C-] (abort-recursive-edit) is used to get out of a recursive editing level and cancel the command which invoked it. Quitting with C-g does not do this, and could not do this, because it is used to cancel a partially typed command within the recursive editing level. Both operations are useful. For example, if you are in a recursive edit and type C-u 8 to enter a numeric argument, you can cancel that argument with C-g and remain in the recursive edit.

The sequence ESC ESC ESC (keyboard-escape-quit) can either quit or abort. (We defined it this way because ESC means “get out” in many PC programs.) It can cancel a prefix argument, clear a selected region, or get out of a Query Replace, like C-g. It can get out of the minibuffer or a recursive edit, like C-]. It can also get out of splitting the frame into multiple windows, as with C-x 1. One thing it cannot do, however, is stop a command that is running. That’s because it executes as an ordinary command, and Emacs doesn’t notice it until it is ready for the next command.

The command M-x top-level is equivalent to enough C-] commands to get you out of all the levels of recursive edits that you are in; it also exits the minibuffer if it is active. C-] gets you out one level at a time, but M-x top-level goes out all levels at once. Both C-] and M-x top-level are like all other commands, and unlike C-g, in that they take effect only when Emacs is ready for a command. C-] is an ordinary key and has its meaning only because of its binding in the keymap. See Recursive Editing Levels.

C-/ (undo) is not strictly speaking a way of canceling a command, but you can think of it as canceling a command that already finished executing. See Undo, for more information about the undo facility.

46 Recursive Editing Levels

A recursive edit is a situation in which you are using Emacs commands to perform arbitrary editing while in the middle of another Emacs command. For example, when you type C-r inside of a query-replace, you enter a recursive edit in which you can change the current buffer. On exiting from the recursive edit, you go back to the query-replace. See Query Replace.

Exiting the recursive edit means returning to the unfinished command, which continues execution. The command to exit is C-M-c (exit-recursive-edit).

You can also abort the recursive edit. This is like exiting, but also quits the unfinished command immediately. Use the command C-] (abort-recursive-edit) to do this. See Quitting and Aborting.

The mode line shows you when you are in a recursive edit by displaying square brackets around the parentheses that always surround the major and minor mode names. Every window’s mode line shows this in the same way, since being in a recursive edit is true of Emacs as a whole rather than any particular window or buffer.

It is possible to be in recursive edits within recursive edits. For example, after typing C-r in a query-replace, you may type a command that enters the debugger. This begins a recursive editing level for the debugger, within the recursive editing level for C-r. Mode lines display a pair of square brackets for each recursive editing level currently in progress.

Exiting the inner recursive edit (such as with the debugger c command) resumes the command running in the next level up. When that command finishes, you can then use C-M-c to exit another recursive editing level, and so on. Exiting applies to the innermost level only. Aborting also gets out of only one level of recursive edit; it returns immediately to the command level of the previous recursive edit. If you wish, you can then abort the next recursive editing level.

Alternatively, the command M-x top-level aborts all levels of recursive edits, returning immediately to the top-level command reader. It also exits the minibuffer, if it is active.

The text being edited inside the recursive edit need not be the same text that you were editing at top level. It depends on what the recursive edit is for. If the command that invokes the recursive edit selects a different buffer first, that is the buffer you will edit recursively. In any case, you can switch buffers within the recursive edit in the normal manner (as long as the buffer-switching keys have not been rebound). You could probably do all the rest of your editing inside the recursive edit, visiting files and all. But this could have surprising effects (such as stack overflow) from time to time. So remember to exit or abort the recursive edit when you no longer need it.

In general, we try to minimize the use of recursive editing levels in GNU Emacs. This is because they constrain you to go back in a particular order—from the innermost level toward the top level. When possible, we present different activities in separate buffers so that you can switch between them as you please. Some commands switch to a new major mode which provides a command to switch back. These approaches give you more flexibility to go back to unfinished tasks in the order you choose.

14 Registers

Emacs registers are compartments where you can save text, rectangles, positions, and other things for later use. Once you save text or a rectangle in a register, you can copy it into the buffer once or many times; once you save a position in a register, you can jump back to that position once or many times.

Each register has a name that consists of a single character, which we will denote by r; r can be a letter (such as ‘a’) or a number (such as ‘1’); case matters, so register ‘a’ is not the same as register ‘A’. You can also set a register in non-alphanumeric characters, for instance ‘*’ or ‘C-d’. Note, it’s not possible to set a register in ‘C-g’ or ‘ESC’, because these keys are reserved for quitting (see Quitting and Aborting).

A register can store a position, a piece of text, a rectangle, a number, a window or frame configuration, a buffer name, or a file name, but only one thing at any given time. Whatever you store in a register remains there until you store something else in that register. To see what register r contains, use M-x view-register:

M-x view-register RET r

Display a description of what register r contains.

All of the commands that prompt for a register will display a preview window that lists the existing registers (if there are any) after a short delay. To change the length of the delay, customize register-preview-delay. To prevent this display, set that option to nil. You can explicitly request a preview window by pressing C-h or F1.

Bookmarks record files and positions in them, so you can return to those positions when you look at the file again. Bookmarks are similar in spirit to registers, so they are also documented in this chapter.

14.1 Saving Positions in Registers

C-x r SPC r

Record the position of point and the current buffer in register r (point-to-register).

C-x r j r

Jump to the position and buffer saved in register r (jump-to-register).

Typing C-x r SPC (point-to-register), followed by a character r, saves both the position of point and the current buffer in register r. The register retains this information until you store something else in it.

The command C-x r j r switches to the buffer recorded in register r, pushes a mark, and moves point to the recorded position. (The mark is not pushed if point was already at the recorded position, or in successive calls to the command.) The contents of the register are not changed, so you can jump to the saved position any number of times.

If you use C-x r j to go to a saved position, but the buffer it was saved from has been killed, C-x r j tries to create the buffer again by visiting the same file. Of course, this works only for buffers that were visiting files.

14.2 Saving Text in Registers

When you want to insert a copy of the same piece of text several times, it may be inconvenient to yank it from the kill ring, since each subsequent kill moves that entry further down the ring. An alternative is to store the text in a register and later retrieve it.

C-x r s r

Copy region into register r (copy-to-register).

C-x r i r

Insert text from register r (insert-register).

M-x append-to-register RET r

Append region to text in register r.

When register r contains text, you can use C-x r + (increment-register) to append to that register. Note that command C-x r + behaves differently if r contains a number. See Keeping Numbers in Registers.

M-x prepend-to-register RET r

Prepend region to text in register r.

C-x r s r stores a copy of the text of the region into the register named r. If the mark is inactive, Emacs first reactivates the mark where it was last set. The mark is deactivated at the end of this command. See The Mark and the Region. C-u C-x r s r, the same command with a prefix argument, copies the text into register r and deletes the text from the buffer as well; you can think of this as moving the region text into the register.

M-x append-to-register RET r appends the copy of the text in the region to the text already stored in the register named r. If invoked with a prefix argument, it deletes the region after appending it to the register. The command prepend-to-register is similar, except that it prepends the region text to the text in the register instead of appending it.

When you are collecting text using append-to-register and prepend-to-register, you may want to separate individual collected pieces using a separator. In that case, configure a register-separator and store the separator text in to that register. For example, to get double newlines as text separator during the collection process, you can use the following setting.

(setq register-separator ?+)
(set-register register-separator "\n\n")

C-x r i r inserts in the buffer the text from register r. Normally it leaves point after the text and sets the mark before, without activating it. With a prefix argument, it instead puts point before the text and the mark after.

14.3 Saving Rectangles in Registers

A register can contain a rectangle instead of linear text. See Rectangles, for basic information on how to specify a rectangle in the buffer.

C-x r r r

Copy the region-rectangle into register r (copy-rectangle-to-register). With prefix argument, delete it as well.

C-x r i r

Insert the rectangle stored in register r (if it contains a rectangle) (insert-register).

The C-x r i r (insert-register) command, previously documented in Saving Text in Registers, inserts a rectangle rather than a text string, if the register contains a rectangle.

14.4 Saving Window and Frame Configurations in Registers

You can save the window configuration of the selected frame in a register, or even the configuration of all windows in all frames, and restore the configuration later. See Convenience Features for Window Handling, for information about window configurations.

C-x r w r

Save the state of the selected frame’s windows in register r (window-configuration-to-register).

C-x r f r

Save the state of all frames, including all their windows (a.k.a. frameset), in register r (frameset-to-register).

Use C-x r j r to restore a window or frame configuration. This is the same command used to restore a cursor position. When you restore a frame configuration, any existing frames not included in the configuration become invisible. If you wish to delete these frames instead, use C-u C-x r j r.

14.5 Keeping Numbers in Registers

There are commands to store a number in a register, to insert the number in the buffer in decimal, and to increment it. These commands can be useful in keyboard macros (see Keyboard Macros).

C-u number C-x r n r

Store number into register r (number-to-register).

C-u number C-x r + r

If r contains a number, increment the number in that register by number. Note that command C-x r + (increment-register) behaves differently if r contains text. See Saving Text in Registers.

C-x r i r

Insert the number from register r into the buffer.

C-x r i is the same command used to insert any other sort of register contents into the buffer. C-x r + with no numeric argument increments the register value by 1; C-x r n with no numeric argument stores zero in the register.

14.6 Keeping File and Buffer Names in Registers

If you visit certain file names frequently, you can visit them more conveniently if you put their names in registers. Here’s the Lisp code used to put a file name into register r:

(set-register r '(file . name))

For example,

(set-register ?z '(file . "/gd/gnu/emacs/19.0/src/ChangeLog"))

puts the file name shown in register ‘z’.

To visit the file whose name is in register r, type C-x r j r. (This is the same command used to jump to a position or restore a frame configuration.)

Similarly, if there are certain buffers you visit frequently, you can put their names in registers. For instance, if you visit the ‘*Messages*’ buffer often, you can use the following snippet to put that buffer into the ‘m’ register:

(set-register ?m '(buffer . "*Messages*"))

To switch to the buffer whose name is in register r, type C-x r j r.

14.7 Keyboard Macro Registers

If you need to execute a keyboard macro (see Keyboard Macros) frequently, it is more convenient to put it in a register or save it (see Naming and Saving Keyboard Macros). C-x C-k x r (kmacro-to-register) stores the last keyboard macro in register r.

To execute the keyboard macro in register r, type C-x r j r. (This is the same command used to jump to a position or restore a frameset.)

14.8 Bookmarks

Bookmarks are somewhat like registers in that they record positions you can jump to. Unlike registers, they have long names, and they persist automatically from one Emacs session to the next. The prototypical use of bookmarks is to record where you were reading in various files.

C-x r m RET

Set the bookmark for the visited file, at point.

C-x r m bookmark RET

Set the bookmark named bookmark at point (bookmark-set).

C-x r M bookmark RET

Like C-x r m, but don’t overwrite an existing bookmark.

C-x r b bookmark RET

Jump to the bookmark named bookmark (bookmark-jump).

C-x r l

List all bookmarks (list-bookmarks).

M-x bookmark-save

Save all the current bookmark values in the default bookmark file.

To record the current position in the visited file, use the command C-x r m, which sets a bookmark using the visited file name as the default for the bookmark name. If you name each bookmark after the file it points to, then you can conveniently revisit any of those files with C-x r b, and move to the position of the bookmark at the same time.

The command C-x r M (bookmark-set-no-overwrite) works like C-x r m , but it signals an error if the specified bookmark already exists, instead of overwriting it.

To display a list of all your bookmarks in a separate buffer, type C-x r l (list-bookmarks). If you switch to that buffer, you can use it to edit your bookmark definitions or annotate the bookmarks. Type C-h m in the bookmark buffer for more information about its special editing commands.

When you kill Emacs, Emacs saves your bookmarks, if you have changed any bookmark values. You can also save the bookmarks at any time with the M-x bookmark-save command. Bookmarks are saved to the file ~/.emacs.d/bookmarks (for compatibility with older versions of Emacs, if you have a file named ~/.emacs.bmk, that is used instead). The bookmark commands load your default bookmark file automatically. This saving and loading is how bookmarks persist from one Emacs session to the next.

If you set the variable bookmark-save-flag to 1, each command that sets a bookmark will also save your bookmarks; this way, you don’t lose any bookmark values even if Emacs crashes. The value, if a number, says how many bookmark modifications should go by between saving. If you set this variable to nil, Emacs only saves bookmarks if you explicitly use M-x bookmark-save.

The variable bookmark-default-file specifies the file in which to save bookmarks by default.

If you set the variable bookmark-use-annotations to t, setting a bookmark will query for an annotation. If a bookmark has an annotation, it is automatically shown in a separate window when you jump to the bookmark.

Bookmark position values are saved with surrounding context, so that bookmark-jump can find the proper position even if the file is modified slightly. The variable bookmark-search-size says how many characters of context to record on each side of the bookmark’s position. (In buffers that are visiting encrypted files, no context is saved in the bookmarks file no matter the value of this variable.)

Here are some additional commands for working with bookmarks:

M-x bookmark-load RET filename RET

Load a file named filename that contains a list of bookmark values. You can use this command, as well as bookmark-write, to work with other files of bookmark values in addition to your default bookmark file.

M-x bookmark-write RET filename RET

Save all the current bookmark values in the file filename.

M-x bookmark-delete RET bookmark RET

Delete the bookmark named bookmark.

M-x bookmark-insert-location RET bookmark RET

Insert in the buffer the name of the file that bookmark bookmark points to.

M-x bookmark-insert RET bookmark RET

Insert in the buffer the contents of the file that bookmark bookmark points to.

34 Reading Mail with Rmail

Rmail is an Emacs subsystem for reading and disposing of mail that you receive. Rmail stores mail messages in files called Rmail files. Reading the messages in an Rmail file is done in a special major mode, Rmail mode, which redefines most letters to run commands for managing mail.

Emacs also comes with a much more sophisticated and flexible subsystem for reading mail, called Gnus. Gnus is a very large package, and is therefore described in its own manual, see

The Gnus Newsreader

.

34.1 Basic Concepts of Rmail

Using Rmail in the simplest fashion, you have one Rmail file ~/RMAIL in which all of your mail is saved. It is called your primary Rmail file. The command M-x rmail reads your primary Rmail file, merges new mail in from your inboxes, displays the first message you haven’t read yet, and lets you begin reading. The variable rmail-file-name specifies the name of the primary Rmail file.

Rmail displays only one message in the Rmail file at a time. The message that is shown is called the current message. Rmail mode’s special commands can do such things as delete the current message, copy it into another file, send a reply, or move to another message. You can also create multiple Rmail files (see File Handling) and use Rmail to move messages between them (see Copying Messages Out to Files).

Within the Rmail file, messages are normally arranged sequentially in order of receipt; you can specify other ways to sort them (see Sorting the Rmail File). Messages are identified by consecutive integers which are their message numbers. The number of the current message is displayed in Rmail’s mode line, followed by the total number of messages in the file. You can move to a message by specifying its message number with the j key (see Moving Among Messages).

Following the usual conventions of Emacs, changes in an Rmail file become permanent only when you save the file. You can save it with s (rmail-expunge-and-save), which also expunges deleted messages from the file first (see Deleting Messages). To save the file without expunging, use C-x C-s. Rmail automatically saves the Rmail file after merging new mail from an inbox file (see Rmail Files and Inboxes).

You can exit Rmail with q (rmail-quit); this expunges and saves the Rmail file, then buries the Rmail buffer as well as its summary buffer, if present (see Summaries). But there is no need to exit formally. If you switch from Rmail to editing in other buffers, and never switch back, you have exited. Just make sure to save the Rmail file eventually (like any other file you have changed). C-x s is a suitable way to do this (see Commands for Saving Files). The Rmail command b, rmail-bury, buries the Rmail buffer and its summary without expunging and saving the Rmail file.

34.2 Scrolling Within a Message

When Rmail displays a message that does not fit on the screen, you must scroll through it to read the rest. You could do this with the usual scrolling commands: C-v, M-v and M-< (see Scrolling), but in Rmail scrolling is so frequent that it deserves to be easier.

SPC

Scroll forward (scroll-up-command).

DEL
S-SPC

Scroll backward (scroll-down-command).

.

Scroll to start of message (rmail-beginning-of-message).

/

Scroll to end of message (rmail-end-of-message).

Since the most common thing to do while reading a message is to scroll through it by screenfuls, Rmail makes SPC and DEL (or S-SPC) do the same as C-v (scroll-up-command) and M-v (scroll-down-command) respectively.

The command . (rmail-beginning-of-message) scrolls back to the beginning of the selected message. This is not quite the same as M-<: for one thing, it does not set the mark; for another, it resets the buffer boundaries of the current message if you have changed them (e.g., by editing, see Editing Within a Message). Similarly, the command / (rmail-end-of-message) scrolls forward to the end of the selected message.

34.3 Moving Among Messages

The most basic thing to do with a message is to read it. The way to do this in Rmail is to make the message current. The usual practice is to move sequentially through the file, since this is the order of receipt of messages. When you enter Rmail, you are positioned at the first message that you have not yet made current (that is, the first one that has the ‘unseen’ attribute; see Rmail Attributes). Move forward to see the other new messages; move backward to re-examine old messages.

n

Move to the next nondeleted message, skipping any intervening deleted messages (rmail-next-undeleted-message).

p

Move to the previous nondeleted message (rmail-previous-undeleted-message).

M-n

Move to the next message, including deleted messages (rmail-next-message).

M-p

Move to the previous message, including deleted messages (rmail-previous-message).

C-c C-n

Move to the next message with the same subject as the current one (rmail-next-same-subject).

C-c C-p

Move to the previous message with the same subject as the current one (rmail-previous-same-subject).

j

Move to the first message. With argument n, move to message number n (rmail-show-message).

>

Move to the last message (rmail-last-message).

<

Move to the first message (rmail-first-message).

M-s regexp RET

Move to the next message containing a match for regexp (rmail-search).

- M-s regexp RET

Move to the previous message containing a match for regexp. (This is M-s with a negative argument.)

n and p are the usual way of moving among messages in Rmail. They move through the messages sequentially, but skip over deleted messages, which is usually what you want to do. Their command definitions are named rmail-next-undeleted-message and rmail-previous-undeleted-message. If you do not want to skip deleted messages—for example, if you want to move to a message to undelete it—use the variants M-n and M-p (rmail-next-message and rmail-previous-message). A numeric argument to any of these commands serves as a repeat count.

In Rmail, you can specify a numeric argument by typing just the digits. You don’t need to type C-u first. You can also specify a negative argument by typing just -.

The M-s (rmail-search) command is Rmail’s version of search. The usual incremental search command C-s works in Rmail, but it searches only within the current message. The purpose of M-s is to search for another message. It reads a regular expression (see Syntax of Regular Expressions) nonincrementally, then searches starting at the beginning of the following message for a match. It then selects that message. If regexp is empty, M-s reuses the regexp used the previous time.

To search backward in the file for another message, give M-s a negative argument. In Rmail you can do this with - M-s. This begins searching from the end of the previous message.

It is also possible to search for a message based on labels. See Labels.

The C-c C-n (rmail-next-same-subject) command moves to the next message with the same subject as the current one. A prefix argument serves as a repeat count. With a negative argument, this command moves backward, acting like C-c C-p (rmail-previous-same-subject). When comparing subjects, these commands ignore the prefixes typically added to the subjects of replies. These commands are useful for reading all of the messages pertaining to the same subject, a.k.a. thread.

To move to a message specified by absolute message number, use j (rmail-show-message) with the message number as argument. With no argument, j selects the first message. < (rmail-first-message) also selects the first message. > (rmail-last-message) selects the last message.

34.4 Deleting Messages

When you no longer need to keep a message, you can delete it. This flags it as ignorable, and some Rmail commands pretend it is no longer present; but it still has its place in the Rmail file, and still has its message number.

Expunging the Rmail file actually removes the deleted messages. The remaining messages are renumbered consecutively.

d

Delete the current message, and move to the next nondeleted message (rmail-delete-forward).

C-d

Delete the current message, and move to the previous nondeleted message (rmail-delete-backward).

u

Undelete the current message, or move back to the previous deleted message and undelete it (rmail-undelete-previous-message).

x

Expunge the Rmail file (rmail-expunge).

There are two Rmail commands for deleting messages. Both delete the current message and select another. d (rmail-delete-forward) moves to the following message, skipping messages already deleted, while C-d (rmail-delete-backward) moves to the previous nondeleted message. If there is no nondeleted message to move to in the specified direction, the message that was just deleted remains current. A numeric prefix argument serves as a repeat count, to allow deletion of several messages in a single command. A negative argument reverses the meaning of d and C-d.

Whenever Rmail deletes a message, it runs the hook rmail-delete-message-hook. When the hook functions are invoked, the message has been marked deleted, but it is still the current message in the Rmail buffer.

To make all the deleted messages finally vanish from the Rmail file, type x (rmail-expunge). Until you do this, you can still undelete the deleted messages. The undeletion command, u (rmail-undelete-previous-message), is designed to cancel the effect of a d command in most cases. It undeletes the current message if the current message is deleted. Otherwise it moves backward to previous messages until a deleted message is found, and undeletes that message. A numeric prefix argument serves as a repeat count, to allow undeletion of several messages in a single command.

You can usually undo a d with a u because the u moves back to and undeletes the message that the d deleted. But this does not work when the d skips a few already-deleted messages that follow the message being deleted; then the u command undeletes the last of the messages that were skipped. There is no clean way to avoid this problem. However, by repeating the u command, you can eventually get back to the message that you intend to undelete. You can also select a particular deleted message with the M-p command, then type u to undelete it.

A deleted message has the ‘deleted’ attribute, and as a result ‘deleted’ appears in the mode line when the current message is deleted. In fact, deleting or undeleting a message is nothing more than adding or removing this attribute. See Rmail Attributes.

34.5 Rmail Files and Inboxes

When you receive mail locally, the operating system places incoming mail for you in a file that we call your inbox. When you start up Rmail, it runs a C program called movemail to copy the new messages from your inbox into your primary Rmail file, which also contains other messages saved from previous Rmail sessions. It is in this file that you actually read the mail with Rmail. This operation is called getting new mail. You can get new mail at any time in Rmail by typing g.

The variable rmail-primary-inbox-list contains a list of the files that are inboxes for your primary Rmail file. If you don’t set this variable explicitly, Rmail uses the MAIL environment variable, or, as a last resort, a default inbox based on rmail-spool-directory. The default inbox file depends on your operating system; often it is /var/mail/username, /var/spool/mail/username, or /usr/spool/mail/username.

You can specify the inbox file(s) for any Rmail file for the current session with the command set-rmail-inbox-list; see Multiple Rmail Files.

There are two reasons for having separate Rmail files and inboxes.

The inbox file format varies between operating systems and according to the other mail software in use. Only one part of Rmail needs to know about the alternatives, and it need only understand how to convert all of them to Rmail’s own format.
It is very cumbersome to access an inbox file without danger of losing mail, because it is necessary to interlock with mail delivery. Moreover, different operating systems use different interlocking techniques. The strategy of moving mail out of the inbox once and for all into a separate Rmail file avoids the need for interlocking in all the rest of Rmail, since only Rmail operates on the Rmail file.

Rmail uses the standard ‘mbox’ format, introduced by Unix and GNU systems for inbox files, as its internal format of Rmail files. (In fact, there are a few slightly different mbox formats. The differences are not very important, but you can set the variable rmail-mbox-format to tell Rmail which form your system uses. See that variable’s documentation for more details.)

When getting new mail, Rmail first copies the new mail from the inbox file to the Rmail file; then it saves the Rmail file; then it clears out the inbox file. This way, a system crash may cause duplication of mail between the inbox and the Rmail file, but cannot lose mail. If rmail-preserve-inbox is non-nil, then Rmail does not clear out the inbox file when it gets new mail. You may wish to set this, for example, on a portable computer you use to check your mail via POP while traveling, so that your mail will remain on the server and you can save it later on your main desktop workstation.

In some cases, Rmail copies the new mail from the inbox file indirectly. First it runs the movemail program to move the mail from the inbox to an intermediate file called .newmail-inboxname, in the same directory as the Rmail file. Then Rmail merges the new mail from that file, saves the Rmail file, and only then deletes the intermediate file. If there is a crash at the wrong time, this file continues to exist, and Rmail will use it again the next time it gets new mail from that inbox.

If Rmail is unable to convert the data in .newmail-inboxname into mbox format, it renames the file to RMAILOSE.n (n is an integer chosen to make the name unique) so that Rmail will not have trouble with the data again. You should look at the file, find whatever message confuses Rmail (probably one that includes the control-underscore character, octal code 037), and delete it. Then you can use 1 g to get new mail from the corrected file.

34.6 Multiple Rmail Files

Rmail operates by default on your primary Rmail file, which is named ~/RMAIL and receives your incoming mail from your system inbox file. But you can also have other Rmail files and edit them with Rmail. These files can receive mail through their own inboxes, or you can move messages into them with explicit Rmail commands (see Copying Messages Out to Files).

i file RET

Read file into Emacs and run Rmail on it (rmail-input).

g

Merge new mail from current Rmail file’s inboxes (rmail-get-new-mail).

C-u g file RET

Merge new mail from inbox file file.

To run Rmail on a file other than your primary Rmail file, you can use the i (rmail-input) command in Rmail. This visits the file in Rmail mode. You can use M-x rmail-input even when not in Rmail, but it is easier to type C-u M-x rmail, which does the same thing.

The file you read with i should normally be a valid mbox file. If it is not, Rmail tries to convert its text to mbox format, and visits the converted text in the buffer. If you save the buffer, that converts the file.

If you specify a file name that doesn’t exist, i initializes a new buffer for creating a new Rmail file.

You can also select an Rmail file from a menu. In the Classify menu, choose the Input Rmail File item; then choose the Rmail file you want. The variables rmail-secondary-file-directory and rmail-secondary-file-regexp specify which files to offer in the menu: the first variable says which directory to find them in; the second says which files in that directory to offer (all those that match the regular expression). If no files match, you cannot select this menu item. These variables also apply to choosing a file for output (see Copying Messages Out to Files).

The inbox files to use are specified by the variable rmail-inbox-list, which is buffer-local in Rmail mode. As a special exception, if you have specified no inbox files for your primary Rmail file, it uses the MAIL environment variable, or your standard system inbox.

The g command (rmail-get-new-mail) merges mail into the current Rmail file from its inboxes. If the Rmail file has no inboxes, g does nothing. The command M-x rmail also merges new mail into your primary Rmail file.

To merge mail from a file that is not the usual inbox, give the g key a numeric argument, as in C-u g. Then it reads a file name and merges mail from that file. The inbox file is not deleted or changed in any way when g with an argument is used. This is, therefore, a general way of merging one file of messages into another.

34.7 Copying Messages Out to Files

These commands copy messages from an Rmail file into another file.

o file RET

Append a full copy of the current message to the file file (rmail-output).

C-o file RET

Append a copy of the current message, as displayed, to the file file (rmail-output-as-seen).

w file RET

Output just the message body to the file file, taking the default file name from the message ‘Subject’ header.

The commands o and C-o copy the current message into a specified file, adding it at the end. A positive prefix argument serves as a repeat count: that many consecutive messages will be copied to the specified file, starting with the current one and ignoring deleted messages.

The two commands differ mainly in how much to copy: o copies the full message headers, even if they are not all visible, while C-o copies exactly the headers currently displayed and no more. See Display of Messages. In addition, o converts the message to Babyl format (used by Rmail in Emacs version 22 and before) if the file is in Babyl format; C-o cannot output to Babyl files at all.

If the output file is currently visited in an Emacs buffer, the output commands append the message to that buffer. It is up to you to save the buffer eventually in its file.

Sometimes you may receive a message whose body holds the contents of a file. You can save the body to a file (excluding the message header) with the w command (rmail-output-body-to-file). Often these messages contain the intended file name in the ‘Subject’ field, so the w command uses the ‘Subject’ field as the default for the output file name (after replacing some characters that cannot be portably used in file names). However, the file name is read using the minibuffer, so you can specify a different name if you wish.

You can also output a message to an Rmail file chosen with a menu. In the Classify menu, choose the Output Rmail File menu item; then choose the Rmail file you want. This outputs the current message to that file, like the o command. The variables rmail-secondary-file-directory and rmail-secondary-file-regexp specify which files to offer in the menu: the first variable says which directory to find them in; the second says which files in that directory to offer (all those that match the regular expression). If no files match, you cannot select this menu item.

Copying a message with o or C-o gives the original copy of the message the ‘filed’ attribute, so that ‘filed’ appears in the mode line when such a message is current.

If you like to keep just a single copy of every mail message, set the variable rmail-delete-after-output to t; then the o, C-o and w commands delete the original message after copying it. (You can undelete it afterward if you wish, see Deleting Messages.)

By default, o will leave the deleted status of a message it outputs as it was on the original message; thus, a message deleted before it was output will appear as deleted in the output file. Setting the variable rmail-output-reset-deleted-flag to a non-nil value countermands that: the copy of the message will have its deleted status reset, so the message will appear as undeleted in the output file. In addition, when this variable is non-nil, specifying a positive argument to o will not ignore deleted messages when looking for consecutive messages to output.

The variable rmail-output-file-alist lets you specify intelligent defaults for the output file, based on the contents of the current message. The value should be a list whose elements have this form:

(regexp . name-exp)

If there’s a match for regexp in the current message, then the default file name for output is name-exp. If multiple elements match the message, the first matching element decides the default file name. The subexpression name-exp may be a string constant giving the file name to use, or more generally it may be any Lisp expression that yields a file name as a string. rmail-output-file-alist applies to both o and C-o.

Rmail can automatically save messages from your primary Rmail file (the one that rmail-file-name specifies) to other files, based on the value of the variable rmail-automatic-folder-directives. This variable is a list of elements (‘directives’) that say which messages to save where. Each directive is a list consisting of an output file, followed by one or more pairs of a header name and a regular expression. If a message has a header matching the specified regular expression, that message is saved to the given file. If the directive has more than one header entry, all must match. Rmail checks directives when it shows a message from the file rmail-file-name, and applies the first that matches (if any). If the output file is nil, the message is deleted, not saved. For example, you can use this feature to save messages from a particular address, or with a particular subject, to a dedicated file.

34.8 Labels

Each message can have various labels assigned to it as a means of classification. Each label has a name; different names are different labels. Any given label is either present or absent on a particular message. A few label names have standard meanings and are given to messages automatically by Rmail when appropriate; these special labels are called attributes. (See Rmail Attributes.) All other labels are assigned only by users.

a label RET

Assign the label label to the current message (rmail-add-label).

k label RET

Remove the label label from the current message (rmail-kill-label).

C-M-n labels RET

Move to the next message that has one of the labels labels (rmail-next-labeled-message).

C-M-p labels RET

Move to the previous message that has one of the labels labels (rmail-previous-labeled-message).

l labels RET
C-M-l labels RET

Make a summary of all messages containing any of the labels labels (rmail-summary-by-labels).

The a (rmail-add-label) and k (rmail-kill-label) commands allow you to assign or remove any label on the current message. If the label argument is empty, it means to assign or remove the label most recently assigned or removed.

Once you have given messages labels to classify them as you wish, there are three ways to use the labels: in moving, in summaries, and in sorting.

C-M-n labels RET (rmail-next-labeled-message) moves to the next message that has one of the labels labels. The argument labels specifies one or more label names, separated by commas. C-M-p (rmail-previous-labeled-message) is similar, but moves backwards to previous messages. A numeric argument to either command serves as a repeat count.

The command C-M-l labels RET (rmail-summary-by-labels) displays a summary containing only the messages that have at least one of a specified set of labels. The argument labels is one or more label names, separated by commas. See Summaries, for information on summaries.

If the labels argument to C-M-n, C-M-p or C-M-l is empty, it means to use the last set of labels specified for any of these commands.

See Sorting the Rmail File, for information on sorting messages with labels.

34.9 Rmail Attributes

Some labels such as ‘deleted’ and ‘filed’ have built-in meanings, and Rmail assigns them to messages automatically at appropriate times; these labels are called attributes. Here is a list of Rmail attributes:

‘unseen’

Means the message has never been current. Assigned to messages when they come from an inbox file, and removed when a message is made current. When you start Rmail, it initially shows the first message that has this attribute.

‘deleted’

Means the message is deleted. Assigned by deletion commands and removed by undeletion commands (see Deleting Messages).

‘filed’

Means the message has been copied to some other file. Assigned by the o and C-o file output commands (see Copying Messages Out to Files).

‘answered’

Means you have mailed an answer to the message. Assigned by the r command (rmail-reply). See Sending Replies.

‘forwarded’

Means you have forwarded the message. Assigned by the f command (rmail-forward). See Sending Replies.

‘edited’

Means you have edited the text of the message within Rmail. See Editing Within a Message.

‘resent’

Means you have resent the message. Assigned by the command M-x rmail-resend. See Sending Replies.

‘retried’

Means you have retried a failed outgoing message. Assigned by the command M-x rmail-retry-failure. See Sending Replies.

All other labels are assigned or removed only by users, and have no standard meaning.

34.10 Sending Replies

Rmail has several commands to send outgoing mail. See Sending Mail, for information on using Message mode, including certain features meant to work with Rmail. What this section documents are the special commands of Rmail for entering the mail buffer used to compose the outgoing message. Note that the usual keys for sending mail—C-x m, C-x 4 m, and C-x 5 m—also work normally in Rmail mode.

m

Send a message (rmail-mail).

c

Continue editing the already started outgoing message (rmail-continue).

r

Send a reply to the current Rmail message (rmail-reply).

f

Forward the current message to other users (rmail-forward).

C-u f

Resend the current message to other users (rmail-resend).

M-m

Try sending a bounced message a second time (rmail-retry-failure).

The most common reason to send a message while in Rmail is to reply to the message you are reading. To do this, type r (rmail-reply). This displays a mail composition buffer in another window, much like C-x 4 m, but preinitializes the ‘Subject’, ‘To’, ‘CC’, ‘In-Reply-To’ and ‘References’ header fields based on the message you are replying to. The ‘To’ field starts out as the address of the person who sent the message you received, and the ‘CC’ field starts out with all the other recipients of that message.

You can exclude certain recipients from being included automatically in replies, using the variable mail-dont-reply-to-names. Its value should be a regular expression; any recipients that match are excluded from the ‘CC’ field. They are also excluded from the ‘To’ field, unless this would leave the field empty. If this variable is nil, then the first time you compose a reply it is initialized to a default value that matches your own address.

To reply only to the sender of the original message, enter the reply command with a numeric argument: C-u r or 1 r. This omits the ‘CC’ field completely for a particular reply.

Once the mail composition buffer has been initialized, editing and sending the mail goes as usual (see Sending Mail). You can edit the presupplied header fields if they are not what you want. You can also use commands such as C-c C-y, which yanks in the message that you are replying to (see Mail Commands). You can also switch to the Rmail buffer, select a different message there, switch back, and yank the new current message.

Sometimes a message does not reach its destination. Mailers usually send the failed message back to you, enclosed in a failure message. The Rmail command M-m (rmail-retry-failure) prepares to send the same message a second time: it sets up a mail composition buffer with the same text and header fields as before. If you type C-c C-c right away, you send the message again exactly the same as the first time. Alternatively, you can edit the text or headers and then send it. The variable rmail-retry-ignored-headers, in the same format as rmail-ignored-headers (see Display of Messages), controls which headers are stripped from the failed message when retrying it.

Another frequent reason to send mail in Rmail is to forward the current message to other users. f (rmail-forward) makes this easy by preinitializing the mail composition buffer with the current message as the text, and a subject of the form [from: subject], where from and subject are the sender and subject of the original message. All you have to do is fill in the recipients and send. When you forward a message, recipients get a message which is from you, and which has the original message in its contents.

Rmail offers two formats for forwarded messages. The default is to use the MIME format (see Display of Messages). This includes the original message as a separate part. You can use a simpler format if you prefer, by setting the variable rmail-enable-mime-composing to nil. In this case, Rmail just includes the original message enclosed between two delimiter lines. It also modifies every line that starts with a dash, by inserting ‘- ’ at the start of the line. When you receive a forwarded message in this format, if it contains something besides ordinary text—for example, program source code—you might find it useful to undo that transformation. You can do this by selecting the forwarded message and typing M-x unforward-rmail-message. This command extracts the original forwarded message, deleting the inserted ‘- ’ strings, and inserts it into the Rmail file as a separate message immediately following the current one.

Resending is an alternative similar to forwarding; the difference is that resending sends a message that is from the original sender, just as it reached you—with a few added header fields (‘Resent-From’ and ‘Resent-To’) to indicate that it came via you. To resend a message in Rmail, use C-u f. (f runs rmail-forward, which invokes rmail-resend if you provide a numeric argument.)

Use the m (rmail-mail) command to start editing an outgoing message that is not a reply. It leaves the header fields empty. Its only difference from C-x 4 m is that it makes the Rmail buffer accessible for C-c C-y, just as r does.

The c (rmail-continue) command resumes editing the mail composition buffer, to finish editing an outgoing message you were already composing, or to alter a message you have sent.

If you set the variable rmail-mail-new-frame to a non-nil value, then all the Rmail commands to start sending a message create a new frame to edit it in. This frame is deleted when you send the message.

All the Rmail commands to send a message use the mail-composition method that you have chosen (see Mail-Composition Methods).

34.11 Summaries

A summary is a buffer containing one line per message to give you an overview of the mail in an Rmail file. Each line shows the message number and date, the sender, the line count, the labels, and the subject. Moving point in the summary buffer selects messages as you move to their summary lines. Almost all Rmail commands are valid in the summary buffer also; when used there, they apply to the message described by the current line of the summary.

A summary buffer applies to a single Rmail file only; if you are editing multiple Rmail files, each one can have its own summary buffer. The summary buffer name is made by appending ‘-summary’ to the Rmail buffer’s name. Normally only one summary buffer is displayed at a time.

34.11.1 Making Summaries

Here are the commands to create a summary for the current Rmail buffer. Once the Rmail buffer has a summary, changes in the Rmail buffer (such as deleting or expunging messages, and getting new mail) automatically update the summary.

h
C-M-h

Summarize all messages (rmail-summary).

l labels RET
C-M-l labels RET

Summarize messages that have one or more of the specified labels (rmail-summary-by-labels).

C-M-r rcpts RET

Summarize messages that match the specified recipients (rmail-summary-by-recipients).

C-M-t topic RET

Summarize messages that have a match for the specified regexp topic in their subjects (rmail-summary-by-topic).

C-M-s regexp RET

Summarize messages whose headers match the specified regular expression regexp (rmail-summary-by-regexp).

C-M-f senders RET

Summarize messages that match the specified senders. (rmail-summary-by-senders).

The h or C-M-h (rmail-summary) command fills the summary buffer for the current Rmail buffer with a summary of all the messages in the buffer. It then displays and selects the summary buffer in another window.

C-M-l labels RET (rmail-summary-by-labels) makes a partial summary mentioning only the messages that have one or more of the labels labels. labels should contain label names separated by commas.

C-M-r rcpts RET (rmail-summary-by-recipients) makes a partial summary mentioning only the messages that have one or more recipients matching the regular expression rcpts. This is matched against the ‘To’, ‘From’, and ‘CC’ headers (supply a prefix argument to exclude the ‘CC’ header).

C-M-t topic RET (rmail-summary-by-topic) makes a partial summary mentioning only the messages whose subjects have a match for the regular expression topic. With a prefix argument, the match is against the whole message, not just the subject.

C-M-s regexp RET (rmail-summary-by-regexp) makes a partial summary that mentions only the messages whose headers (including the date and the subject lines) match the regular expression regexp.

C-M-f senders RET (rmail-summary-by-senders) makes a partial summary that mentions only the messages whose ‘From’ fields match the regular expression senders.

Note that there is only one summary buffer for any Rmail buffer; making any kind of summary discards any previous summary.

The variable rmail-summary-window-size says how many lines to use for the summary window. The variable rmail-summary-line-count-flag controls whether the summary line for a message should include the line count of the message. Setting this option to nil might speed up the generation of summaries.

34.11.2 Editing in Summaries

You can use the Rmail summary buffer to do almost anything you can do in the Rmail buffer itself. In fact, once you have a summary buffer, there’s no need to switch back to the Rmail buffer.

You can select and display various messages in the Rmail buffer, from the summary buffer, just by moving point in the summary buffer to different lines. It doesn’t matter what Emacs command you use to move point; whichever line point is on at the end of the command, that message is selected in the Rmail buffer.

Almost all Rmail commands work in the summary buffer as well as in the Rmail buffer. Thus, d in the summary buffer deletes the current message, u undeletes, and x expunges. (However, in the summary buffer, if there are no more undeleted messages in the relevant direction, the delete commands go to the first or last message, rather than staying on the current message.) o and C-o output the current message to a FILE; r starts a reply to it; etc. You can scroll the current message while remaining in the summary buffer using SPC and DEL. However, in the summary buffer scrolling past the end or the beginning of a message with SPC or DEL goes, respectively, to the next or previous undeleted message. Customize the rmail-summary-scroll-between-messages option to nil to disable scrolling to next/previous messages.

M-u (rmail-summary-undelete-many) undeletes all deleted messages in the summary. A prefix argument means to undelete that many of the previous deleted messages.

The Rmail commands to move between messages also work in the summary buffer, but with a twist: they move through the set of messages included in the summary. They also ensure the Rmail buffer appears on the screen (unlike cursor motion commands, which update the contents of the Rmail buffer but don’t display it in a window unless it already appears). Here is a list of these commands:

n

Move to next line, skipping lines saying “deleted”, and select its message (rmail-summary-next-msg).

p

Move to previous line, skipping lines saying “deleted”, and select its message (rmail-summary-previous-msg).

M-n

Move to next line and select its message (rmail-summary-next-all).

M-p

Move to previous line and select its message (rmail-summary-previous-all).

>

Move to the last line, and select its message (rmail-summary-last-message).

<

Move to the first line, and select its message (rmail-summary-first-message).

j
RET

Select the message on the current line (ensuring that the Rmail buffer appears on the screen; rmail-summary-goto-msg). With argument n, select message number n and move to its line in the summary buffer; this signals an error if the message is not listed in the summary buffer.

M-s pattern RET

Search through messages for pattern starting with the current message; select the message found, and move point in the summary buffer to that message’s line (rmail-summary-search). A prefix argument acts as a repeat count; a negative argument means search backward (equivalent to rmail-summary-search-backward.)

C-M-n labels RET

Move to the next message with at least one of the specified labels (rmail-summary-next-labeled-message). labels is a comma-separated list of labels. A prefix argument acts as a repeat count.

C-M-p labels RET

Move to the previous message with at least one of the specified labels (rmail-summary-previous-labeled-message).

C-c C-n RET

Move to the next message with the same subject as the current message (rmail-summary-next-same-subject). A prefix argument acts as a repeat count.

C-c C-p RET

Move to the previous message with the same subject as the current message (rmail-summary-previous-same-subject).

Deletion, undeletion, and getting new mail, and even selection of a different message all update the summary buffer when you do them in the Rmail buffer. If the variable rmail-redisplay-summary is non-nil, these actions also bring the summary buffer back onto the screen.

When you are finished using the summary, type Q (rmail-summary-wipe) to delete the summary buffer’s window. You can also exit Rmail while in the summary: q (rmail-summary-quit) deletes the summary window, then exits from Rmail by saving the Rmail file and switching to another buffer. Alternatively, b (rmail-summary-bury) simply buries the Rmail summary and buffer.

34.12 Sorting the Rmail File

C-c C-s C-d
M-x rmail-sort-by-date

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by date.

C-c C-s C-s
M-x rmail-sort-by-subject

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by subject.

C-c C-s C-a
M-x rmail-sort-by-author

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by author’s name.

C-c C-s C-r
M-x rmail-sort-by-recipient

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by recipient’s name.

C-c C-s C-c
M-x rmail-sort-by-correspondent

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by the name of the other correspondent.

C-c C-s C-l
M-x rmail-sort-by-lines

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by number of lines.

C-c C-s C-k RET labels RET
M-x rmail-sort-by-labels RET labels RET

Sort messages of current Rmail buffer by labels. The argument labels should be a comma-separated list of labels. The order of these labels specifies the order of messages; messages with the first label come first, messages with the second label come second, and so on. Messages that have none of these labels come last.

The Rmail sort commands perform a stable sort: if there is no reason to prefer either one of two messages, their order remains unchanged. You can use this to sort by more than one criterion. For example, if you use rmail-sort-by-date and then rmail-sort-by-author, messages from the same author appear in order by date.

With a prefix argument, all these commands reverse the order of comparison. This means they sort messages from newest to oldest, from biggest to smallest, or in reverse alphabetical order.

The same keys in the summary buffer run similar functions; for example, C-c C-s C-l runs rmail-summary-sort-by-lines. These commands always sort the whole Rmail buffer, even if the summary is only showing a subset of messages.

Note that you cannot undo a sort, so you may wish to save the Rmail buffer before sorting it.

34.13 Display of Messages

This section describes how Rmail displays mail headers, MIME sections and attachments, URLs, and encrypted messages.

t

Toggle display of complete header (rmail-toggle-header).

Before displaying each message for the first time, Rmail reformats its header, hiding uninteresting header fields to reduce clutter. The t (rmail-toggle-header) command toggles this, switching between showing the reformatted header fields and showing the complete, original header. With a positive prefix argument, the command shows the reformatted header; with a zero or negative prefix argument, it shows the full header. Selecting the message again also reformats it if necessary.

The variable rmail-ignored-headers holds a regular expression specifying the header fields to hide; any matching header line will be hidden. The variable rmail-nonignored-headers overrides this: any header field matching that regular expression is shown even if it matches rmail-ignored-headers too. The variable rmail-displayed-headers is an alternative to these two variables; if non-nil, this should be a regular expression specifying which headers to display (the default is nil).

Rmail highlights certain header fields that are especially interesting—by default, the ‘From’ and ‘Subject’ fields. This highlighting uses the rmail-highlight face. The variable rmail-highlighted-headers holds a regular expression specifying the header fields to highlight; if it matches the beginning of a header field, that whole field is highlighted. To disable this feature, set rmail-highlighted-headers to nil.

If a message is in MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) format and contains multiple parts (MIME entities), Rmail displays each part with a tagline. The tagline summarizes the part’s index, size, and content type. Depending on the content type, it may also contain one or more buttons; these perform actions such as saving the part into a file.

RET

Hide or show the MIME part at point (rmail-mime-toggle-hidden).

TAB

Move point to the next MIME tagline button. (rmail-mime-next-item).

S-TAB

Move point to the previous MIME part (rmail-mime-previous-item).

v

Toggle between MIME display and raw message (rmail-mime).

Each plain-text MIME part is initially displayed immediately after its tagline, as part of the Rmail buffer (unless the message has an HTML part, see below), while MIME parts of other types are represented only by their taglines, with their actual contents hidden. In either case, you can toggle a MIME part between its displayed and hidden states by typing RET anywhere in the part—or anywhere in its tagline (except for buttons for other actions, if there are any). Type RET (or click with the mouse) to activate a tagline button, and TAB to cycle point between tagline buttons.

The v (rmail-mime) command toggles between the default MIME display described above, and a raw display showing the undecoded MIME data. With a prefix argument, this command toggles the display of only an entity at point.

If the message has an HTML MIME part, Rmail displays it in preference to the plain-text part, if Emacs can render HTML^19. To prevent that, and have the plain-text part displayed instead, customize the variable rmail-mime-prefer-html to a nil value.

To prevent Rmail from handling MIME decoded messages, change the variable rmail-enable-mime to nil. When this is the case, the v (rmail-mime) command instead creates a temporary buffer to display the current MIME message.

If the current message is an encrypted one, use the command C-c C-d (rmail-epa-decrypt) to decrypt it, using the EasyPG library (see EasyPG in

EasyPG Assistant User’s Manual

).

You can highlight and activate URLs in the Rmail buffer using Goto Address mode:

(add-hook 'rmail-show-message-hook 'goto-address-mode)

Then you can browse these URLs by clicking on them with mouse-2 (or mouse-1 quickly) or by moving to one and typing C-c RET. See Activating URLs.

34.14 Rmail and Coding Systems

Rmail automatically decodes messages which contain non-ASCII characters, just as Emacs does with files you visit and with subprocess output. Rmail uses the standard ‘charset=charset’ header in the message, if any, to determine how the message was encoded by the sender. It maps charset into the corresponding Emacs coding system (see Coding Systems), and uses that coding system to decode message text. If the message header doesn’t have the ‘charset’ specification, or if charset is not recognized, Rmail chooses the coding system with the usual Emacs heuristics and defaults (see Recognizing Coding Systems).

Occasionally, a message is decoded incorrectly, either because Emacs guessed the wrong coding system in the absence of the ‘charset’ specification, or because the specification was inaccurate. For example, a misconfigured mailer could send a message with a ‘charset=iso-8859-1’ header when the message is actually encoded in koi8-r. When you see the message text garbled, or some of its characters displayed as hex codes or empty boxes, this may have happened.

You can correct the problem by decoding the message again using the right coding system, if you can figure out or guess which one is right. To do this, invoke the M-x rmail-redecode-body command. It reads the name of a coding system, and then redecodes the message using the coding system you specified. If you specified the right coding system, the result should be readable.

When you get new mail in Rmail, each message is translated automatically from the coding system it is written in, as if it were a separate file. This uses the priority list of coding systems that you have specified. If a MIME message specifies a character set, Rmail obeys that specification. For reading and saving Rmail files themselves, Emacs uses the coding system specified by the variable rmail-file-coding-system. The default value is nil, which means that Rmail files are not translated (they are read and written in the Emacs internal character code).

34.15 Editing Within a Message

Most of the usual Emacs key bindings are available in Rmail mode, though a few, such as C-M-n and C-M-h, are redefined by Rmail for other purposes. However, the Rmail buffer is normally read only, and most of the letters are redefined as Rmail commands. If you want to edit the text of a message, you must use the Rmail command e.

e

Edit the current message as ordinary text.

The e command (rmail-edit-current-message) switches from Rmail mode into Rmail Edit mode, another major mode which is nearly the same as Text mode. The mode line indicates this change.

In Rmail Edit mode, letters insert themselves as usual and the Rmail commands are not available. You can edit the message body and header fields. When you are finished editing the message, type C-c C-c (rmail-cease-edit) to switch back to Rmail mode. Alternatively, you can return to Rmail mode but cancel any editing that you have done, by typing C-c C-] (rmail-abort-edit).

Entering Rmail Edit mode runs the hook text-mode-hook; then it runs the hook rmail-edit-mode-hook (see Hooks). Returning to ordinary Rmail mode adds the attribute ‘edited’ to the message, if you have made any changes in it (see Rmail Attributes).

34.16 Digest Messages

A digest message is a message which exists to contain and carry several other messages. Digests are used on some mailing lists; all the messages that arrive for the list during a period of time such as one day are put inside a single digest which is then sent to the subscribers. Transmitting the single digest uses less computer time than transmitting the individual messages even though the total size is the same, because of the per-message overhead in network mail transmission.

When you receive a digest message, the most convenient way to read it is to undigestify it: to turn it back into many individual messages. Then you can read and delete the individual messages as it suits you. To do this, select the digest message and type the command M-x undigestify-rmail-message. This extracts the submessages as separate Rmail messages, and inserts them following the digest. The digest message itself is flagged as deleted.

34.17 Reading Rot13 Messages

Mailing list messages that might offend or annoy some readers are sometimes encoded in a simple code called rot13—so named because it rotates the alphabet by 13 letters. This code is not for secrecy, as it provides none; rather, it enables those who wish to avoid seeing the real text of the message. For example, a review of a film might use rot13 to hide important plot points.

To view a buffer that uses the rot13 code, use the command M-x rot13-other-window. This displays the current buffer in another window which applies the code when displaying the text.

If you are only interested in a region, the command M-x rot13-region might be preferable. This will encrypt/decrypt the active region in-place. If the buffer is read-only, it will attempt to display the plain text in the echo area. If the text is too long for the echo area, the command will pop up a temporary buffer with the encrypted/decrypted text.

34.18 movemail program

Rmail uses the movemail program to move mail from your inbox to your Rmail file (see Rmail Files and Inboxes). When loaded for the first time, Rmail attempts to locate the movemail program and determine its version. There are two versions of the movemail program: the GNU Mailutils version (see movemail in

GNU mailutils

), and an Emacs-specific version that is built and installed unless Emacs was configured --with-mailutils in effect. The two movemail versions support the same command line syntax and the same basic subset of options. However, the Mailutils version offers additional features and is more secure.

The Emacs version of movemail can retrieve mail from the usual Unix mailbox formats. Warning: Although it can also use the POP3 protocol, this is not recommended because it does not support POP3 via encrypted TLS channels.

The Mailutils version is able to handle a wide set of mailbox formats, such as plain Unix mailboxes, maildir and MH mailboxes, etc. It is able to access remote mailboxes using the POP3 or IMAP4 protocol, and can retrieve mail from them using a TLS encrypted channel. It also accepts mailbox arguments in URL form. The detailed description of mailbox URLs can be found in URL in

Mailbox URL Formats

. In short, a URL is:

proto://[user[:password]@]host-or-file-name[:port]

where square brackets denote optional elements.

proto

Specifies the mailbox protocol, or format to use. The exact semantics of the rest of URL elements depends on the actual value of proto (see below).

user

User name to access the remote mailbox.

password

User password to access the remote mailbox.

host-or-file-name

Hostname of the remote server for remote mailboxes or file name of a local mailbox.

port

Optional port number, if not the default for that protocol.

proto can be one of:

mbox

Usual Unix mailbox format. In this case, user, pass and port are not used, and host-or-file-name denotes the file name of the mailbox file, e.g., mbox:///var/spool/mail/smith.

mh

A local mailbox in the MH format. user, pass and port are not used. host-or-file-name denotes the name of MH folder, e.g., mh:///Mail/inbox.

maildir

A local mailbox in the maildir format. user, pass and port are not used, and host-or-file-name denotes the name of maildir mailbox, e.g., maildir:///mail/inbox.

file

Any local file in mailbox format. Its actual format is detected automatically by movemail.

pop
pops

A remote mailbox to be accessed via POP3 protocol. user specifies the remote user name to use, pass may be used to specify the user password, host-or-file-name is the name or IP address of the remote mail server to connect to, and port is the port number; e.g., pop://smith:guessme@remote.server.net:995. If the server supports it, movemail tries to use an encrypted connection—use the ‘pops’ form to require one.

imap
imaps

A remote mailbox to be accessed via IMAP4 protocol. user specifies the remote user name to use, pass may be used to specify the user password, host-or-file-name is the name or IP address of the remote mail server to connect to, and port is the port number; e.g., imap://smith:guessme@remote.server.net:993. If the server supports it, movemail tries to use an encrypted connection—use the ‘imaps’ form to require one.

Alternatively, you can specify the file name of the mailbox to use. This is equivalent to specifying the ‘file’ protocol:

/var/spool/mail/user ≡ file:///var/spool/mail/user

The variable rmail-movemail-program controls which version of movemail to use. If that is a string, it specifies the absolute file name of the movemail executable. If it is nil, Rmail searches for movemail in the directories listed in rmail-movemail-search-path, then in exec-path (see Running Shell Commands from Emacs), then in exec-directory.

34.19 Retrieving Mail from Remote Mailboxes

Some sites use a method called POP3 for accessing users’ inbox data instead of storing the data in inbox files. The Mailutils movemail by default supports POP3 with TLS encryption. Warning: Although the Emacs movemail supports POP3, its use for this is not recommended since it does not support encrypted connections—the Mailutils version does. Both versions of movemail work only with POP3, not with older versions of POP.

You can specify a POP3 inbox by using a POP3 URL (see movemail program). A POP3 URL is of the form ‘pop://username@hostname:port’, where hostname and port are the host name (or IP address) and port number of the remote mail server and username is the user name on that server. Additionally, you may specify the password in the mailbox URL: ‘pop://username:password@hostname:port’. In this case, password takes preference over the one set by rmail-remote-password (see below). This is especially useful if you have several remote mailboxes with different passwords. If using Mailutils movemail, you may wish to use ‘pops’ in place of ‘pop’.

For backward compatibility, Rmail also supports an alternative way of specifying remote POP3 mailboxes. Specifying an inbox name in the form ‘po:username:hostname:port’ is equivalent to ‘pop://username@hostname:port’. If you omit the :hostname part, the MAILHOST environment variable specifies the machine on which to look for the POP3 server.

Another method for accessing remote mailboxes is IMAP. This method is supported only by the Mailutils movemail. To specify an IMAP mailbox in the inbox list, use the following mailbox URL: ‘imap://username[:password]@hostname:port’. The password part is optional, as described above. You may wish to use ‘imaps’ in place of ‘imap’.

Accessing a remote mailbox may require a password. Rmail uses the following algorithm to retrieve it:

If a password is present in the mailbox URL (see above), it is used.
If the variable rmail-remote-password-required is nil, Rmail assumes no password is required.
If the variable rmail-remote-password is non-nil, its value is used.
Otherwise, Rmail will ask you for the password to use.

On some mail servers the usernames include domain information, which can mean they contain the ‘@’ character. The inbox specifier string uses ‘@’ to signal the start of the mailserver name. This creates confusion for movemail. If your username contains ‘@’ and you’re using Mailutils movemail then you can fix this: Replace @ in the user name with its URL encoding ‘%40’.

If you need to pass additional command-line flags to movemail, set the variable rmail-movemail-flags a list of the flags you wish to use. Do not use this variable to pass the ‘-p’ flag to preserve your inbox contents; use rmail-preserve-inbox instead.

The movemail program installed at your site may support Kerberos authentication. If it is supported, it is used by default whenever you attempt to retrieve POP3 mail when rmail-remote-password and rmail-remote-password-required are unset.

Some POP3 servers store messages in reverse order. If your server does this, and you would rather read your mail in the order in which it was received, you can tell movemail to reverse the order of downloaded messages by adding the ‘-r’ flag to rmail-movemail-flags.

Mailutils movemail supports TLS encryption. If you wish to use it, add the ‘--tls’ flag to rmail-movemail-flags.

34.20 Retrieving Mail from Local Mailboxes in Various Formats

If your incoming mail is stored on a local machine in a format other than Unix mailbox, you will need the Mailutils movemail to retrieve it. See movemail program, for the detailed description of movemail versions. For example, to access mail from an inbox in maildir format located in /var/spool/mail/in, you would include the following in the Rmail inbox list:

maildir:///var/spool/mail/in

Footnotes

(19)

This capability requires that Emacs be built with libxml2 support or that you have the Lynx browser installed.

1 The Organization of the Screen

On a graphical display, such as on GNU/Linux using the X Window System, Emacs occupies a graphical window. On a text terminal, Emacs occupies the entire terminal screen. We will use the term frame to mean a graphical window or terminal screen occupied by Emacs. Emacs behaves very similarly on both kinds of frames. It normally starts out with just one frame, but you can create additional frames if you wish (see Frames and Graphical Displays).

Each frame consists of several distinct regions. At the top of the frame is a menu bar, which allows you to access commands via a series of menus. On a graphical display, directly below the menu bar is a tool bar, a row of icons that perform editing commands when you click on them. At the very bottom of the frame is an echo area, where informative messages are displayed and where you enter information when Emacs asks for it.

The main area of the frame, below the tool bar (if one exists) and above the echo area, is called the window. Henceforth in this manual, we will use the word “window” in this sense. Graphical display systems commonly use the word “window” with a different meaning; but, as stated above, we refer to those graphical windows as “frames”.

An Emacs window is where the buffer—the text or other graphics you are editing or viewing—is displayed. On a graphical display, the window possesses a scroll bar on one side, which can be used to scroll through the buffer. The last line of the window is a mode line. This displays various information about what is going on in the buffer, such as whether there are unsaved changes, the editing modes that are in use, the current line number, and so forth.

When you start Emacs, there is normally only one window in the frame. However, you can subdivide this window horizontally or vertically to create multiple windows, each of which can independently display a buffer (see Multiple Windows).

At any time, one window is the selected window. On a graphical display, the selected window shows a more prominent cursor (usually solid and blinking); other windows show a less prominent cursor (usually a hollow box). On a text terminal, there is only one cursor, which is shown in the selected window. The buffer displayed in the selected window is called the current buffer, and it is where editing happens. Most Emacs commands implicitly apply to the current buffer; the text displayed in unselected windows is mostly visible for reference. If you use multiple frames on a graphical display, selecting a particular frame selects a window in that frame.

1.1 Point

The cursor in the selected window shows the location where most editing commands take effect, which is called point^1. Many Emacs commands move point to different places in the buffer; for example, you can place point by clicking mouse button 1 (normally the left button) at the desired location.

By default, the cursor in the selected window is drawn as a solid block and appears to be on a character, but you should think of point as between two characters; it is situated before the character under the cursor. For example, if your text looks like ‘frob’ with the cursor over the ‘b’, then point is between the ‘o’ and the ‘b’. If you insert the character ‘!’ at that position, the result is ‘fro!b’, with point between the ‘!’ and the ‘b’. Thus, the cursor remains over the ‘b’, as before.

If you are editing several files in Emacs, each in its own buffer, each buffer has its own value of point. A buffer that is not currently displayed remembers its value of point if you later display it again. Furthermore, if a buffer is displayed in multiple windows, each of those windows has its own value of point.

See Displaying the Cursor, for options that control how Emacs displays the cursor.

1.2 The Echo Area

The line at the very bottom of the frame is the echo area. It is used to display small amounts of text for various purposes.

The echo area is so-named because one of the things it is used for is echoing, which means displaying the characters of a multi-character command as you type. Single-character commands are not echoed. Multi-character commands (see Keys) are echoed if you pause for more than a second in the middle of a command. Emacs then echoes all the characters of the command so far, to prompt you for the rest. Once echoing has started, the rest of the command echoes immediately as you type it. This behavior is designed to give confident users fast response, while giving hesitant users maximum feedback.

The echo area is also used to display an error message when a command cannot do its job. Error messages may be accompanied by beeping or by flashing the screen.

Some commands display informative messages in the echo area to tell you what the command has done, or to provide you with some specific information. These informative messages, unlike error messages, are not accompanied with a beep or flash. For example, C-x = (hold down Ctrl and type x, then let go of Ctrl and type =) displays a message describing the character at point, its position in the buffer, and its current column in the window. Commands that take a long time often display messages ending in ‘...’ while they are working (sometimes also indicating how much progress has been made, as a percentage), and add ‘done’ when they are finished.

Informative echo area messages are saved in a special buffer named *Messages*. (We have not explained buffers yet; see Using Multiple Buffers, for more information about them.) If you miss a message that appeared briefly on the screen, you can switch to the *Messages* buffer to see it again. The *Messages* buffer is limited to a certain number of lines, specified by the variable message-log-max. (We have not explained variables either; see Variables, for more information about them.) Beyond this limit, one line is deleted from the beginning whenever a new message line is added at the end.

See Customization of Display, for options that control how Emacs uses the echo area.

The echo area is also used to display the minibuffer, a special window where you can input arguments to commands, such as the name of a file to be edited. When the minibuffer is in use, the text displayed in the echo area begins with a prompt string, and the active cursor appears within the minibuffer, which is temporarily considered the selected window. You can always get out of the minibuffer by typing C-g. See The Minibuffer.

1.3 The Mode Line

At the bottom of each window is a mode line, which describes what is going on in the current buffer. When there is only one window, the mode line appears right above the echo area; it is the next-to-last line in the frame. On a graphical display, the mode line is drawn with a 3D box appearance. Emacs also usually draws the mode line of the selected window with a different color from that of unselected windows, in order to make it stand out.

The text displayed in the mode line has the following format:

 cs:ch-fr  buf      pos line   (major minor)

On a text terminal, this text is followed by a series of dashes extending to the right edge of the window. These dashes are omitted on a graphical display.

The cs string and the colon character after it describe the character set and newline convention used for the current buffer. Normally, Emacs automatically handles these settings for you, but it is sometimes useful to have this information.

cs describes the character set of the text in the buffer (see Coding Systems). If it is a dash (‘-’), that indicates no special character set handling (with the possible exception of end-of-line conventions, described in the next paragraph). ‘=’ means no conversion whatsoever, and is usually used for files containing non-textual data. Other characters represent various coding systems—for example, ‘1’ represents ISO Latin-1.

On a text terminal, cs is preceded by two additional characters that describe the coding systems for keyboard input and terminal output. Furthermore, if you are using an input method, cs is preceded by a string that identifies the input method (see Input Methods).

The character after cs is usually a colon. If a different string is displayed, that indicates a nontrivial end-of-line convention for encoding a file. Usually, lines of text are separated by newline characters in a file, but two other conventions are sometimes used. The MS-DOS convention uses a carriage return character followed by a linefeed character; when editing such files, the colon changes to either a backslash (‘\’) or ‘(DOS)’, depending on the operating system. Another convention, employed by older Macintosh systems, uses a carriage return character instead of a newline; when editing such files, the colon changes to either a forward slash (‘/’) or ‘(Mac)’. On some systems, Emacs displays ‘(Unix)’ instead of the colon for files that use newline as the line separator.

On frames created for emacsclient (see Invoking emacsclient), the next character is ‘@’. This indication is typical for frames of an Emacs process running as a daemon (see Using Emacs as a Server).

The next element on the mode line is the string indicated by ch. This shows two dashes (‘--’) if the buffer displayed in the window has the same contents as the corresponding file on the disk; i.e., if the buffer is unmodified. If the buffer is modified, it shows two stars (‘**’). For a read-only buffer, it shows ‘%*’ if the buffer is modified, and ‘%%’ otherwise.

The character after ch is normally a dash (‘-’). However, if default-directory (see File Names) for the current buffer is on a remote machine, ‘@’ is displayed instead.

fr gives the selected frame name (see Frames and Graphical Displays). It appears only on text terminals. The initial frame’s name is ‘F1’.

buf is the name of the buffer displayed in the window. Usually, this is the same as the name of a file you are editing. See Using Multiple Buffers.

pos tells you whether there is additional text above the top of the window, or below the bottom. If your buffer is small and all of it is visible in the window, pos is ‘All’. Otherwise, it is ‘Top’ if you are looking at the beginning of the buffer, ‘Bot’ if you are looking at the end of the buffer, or ‘nn%’, where nn is the percentage of the buffer above the top of the window. With Size Indication mode, you can display the size of the buffer as well. See Optional Mode Line Features.

line is the character ‘L’ followed by the line number at point. (You can display the current column number too, by turning on Column Number mode. See Optional Mode Line Features.)

major is the name of the major mode used in the buffer. A major mode is a principal editing mode for the buffer, such as Text mode, Lisp mode, C mode, and so forth. See Major Modes. Some major modes display additional information after the major mode name. For example, Compilation buffers and Shell buffers display the status of the subprocess.

minor is a list of some of the enabled minor modes, which are optional editing modes that provide additional features on top of the major mode. See Minor Modes.

Some features are listed together with the minor modes whenever they are turned on, even though they are not really minor modes. ‘Narrow’ means that the buffer being displayed has editing restricted to only a portion of its text (see Narrowing). ‘Def’ means that a keyboard macro is currently being defined (see Keyboard Macros).

In addition, if Emacs is inside a recursive editing level, square brackets (‘[…]’) appear around the parentheses that surround the modes. If Emacs is in one recursive editing level within another, double square brackets appear, and so on. Since recursive editing levels affect Emacs globally, such square brackets appear in the mode line of every window. See Recursive Editing Levels.

You can change the appearance of the mode line as well as the format of its contents. See Optional Mode Line Features. In addition, the mode line is mouse-sensitive; clicking on different parts of the mode line performs various commands. See Mode Line Mouse Commands. Also, hovering the mouse pointer above mouse-sensitive portions of the mode line shows tooltips (see Tooltips) with information about commands you can invoke by clicking on the mode line.

1.4 The Menu Bar

Each Emacs frame normally has a menu bar at the top which you can use to perform common operations. There’s no need to list them here, as you can more easily see them yourself.

On a display that supports a mouse, you can use the mouse to choose a command from the menu bar. An arrow on the right edge of a menu item means it leads to a subsidiary menu, or submenu. A ‘...’ at the end of a menu item means that the command will prompt you for further input before it actually does anything.

Some of the commands in the menu bar have ordinary key bindings as well; if so, a key binding is shown after the item itself. To view the full command name and documentation for a menu item, type C-h k, and then select the menu bar with the mouse in the usual way (see Documentation for a Key).

Instead of using the mouse, you can also invoke the first menu bar item by pressing F10 (to run the command menu-bar-open). You can then navigate the menus with the arrow keys or with C-b, C-f (left/right), C-p, and C-n (up/down). To activate a selected menu item, press RET; to cancel menu navigation, press C-g or ESC ESC ESC. (However, note that when Emacs was built with a GUI toolkit, the menus are drawn and controlled by the toolkit, and the key sequences to cancel menu navigation might be different from the above description.)

On a text terminal, you can optionally access the menu-bar menus in the echo area. To this end, customize the variable tty-menu-open-use-tmm to a non-nil value. Then typing F10 will run the command tmm-menubar instead of dropping down the menu. (You can also type M-`, which always invokes tmm-menubar.) tmm-menubar lets you select a menu item with the keyboard. A provisional choice appears in the echo area. You can use the up and down arrow keys to move through the menu to different items, and then you can type RET to select the item. Each menu item is also designated by a letter or digit (usually the initial of some word in the item’s name). This letter or digit is separated from the item name by ‘==>’. You can type the item’s letter or digit to select the item.

Footnotes

(1)

The term “point” comes from the character ‘.’, which was the command in TECO (the language in which the original Emacs was written) for accessing the editing position.

16 Searching and Replacement

Like other editors, Emacs has commands to search for occurrences of a string. Emacs also has commands to replace occurrences of a string with a different string. There are also commands that do the same thing, but search for patterns instead of fixed strings.

You can also search multiple files under the control of xref (see Searching and Replacing with Identifiers) or through the Dired A command (see Operating on Files), or ask the grep program to do it (see Searching with Grep under Emacs).

16.1 Incremental Search

The principal search command in Emacs is incremental: it begins searching as soon as you type the first character of the search string. As you type in the search string, Emacs shows you where the string (as you have typed it so far) would be found. When you have typed enough characters to identify the place you want, you can stop. Depending on what you plan to do next, you may or may not need to terminate the search explicitly with RET.

C-s

Incremental search forward (isearch-forward).

C-r

Incremental search backward (isearch-backward).

You can also invoke incremental search from the menu bar’s ‘Edit->Search’ menu.

16.1.1 Basics of Incremental Search

C-s

Begin incremental search (isearch-forward).

C-r

Begin reverse incremental search (isearch-backward).

C-s (isearch-forward) starts a forward incremental search. It reads characters from the keyboard, and moves point just past the end of the next occurrence of those characters in the buffer.

For instance, if you type C-s and then F, that puts the cursor after the first ‘F’ that occurs in the buffer after the starting point. If you then type O, the cursor moves to just after the first ‘FO’; the ‘F’ in that ‘FO’ might not be the first ‘F’ previously found. After another O, the cursor moves to just after the first ‘FOO’.

At each step, Emacs highlights the current match—the buffer text that matches the search string—using the isearch face (see Text Faces). See Tailoring Search to Your Needs, for various options that customize this highlighting. The current search string is also displayed in the echo area.

If you make a mistake typing the search string, type DEL (isearch-delete-char). Each DEL cancels the last input item entered during the search. Emacs records a new input item whenever you type a command that changes the search string, the position of point, the success or failure of the search, the direction of the search, the position of the other end of the current search result, or the “wrappedness” of the search. See Errors in Incremental Search, for more about dealing with unsuccessful search.

When you are satisfied with the place you have reached, type RET (isearch-exit). This stops searching, leaving the cursor where the search brought it. Also, any command not specially meaningful in searches stops the searching and is then executed. Thus, typing C-a exits the search and then moves to the beginning of the line; typing one of the arrow keys exits the search and performs the respective movement command; etc. RET is necessary only if the next command you want to type is a printing character, DEL, RET, or another character that is special within searches (C-q, C-w, C-r, C-s, C-y, M-y, M-r, M-c, M-e, and some others described below). You can fine-tune the commands that exit the search; see Not Exiting Incremental Search.

As a special exception, entering RET when the search string is empty launches nonincremental search (see Nonincremental Search). (This can be customized; see Tailoring Search to Your Needs.)

To abandon the search and return to the place where you started, type ESC ESC ESC (isearch-cancel) or C-g C-g (isearch-abort).

When you exit the incremental search, it adds the original value of point to the mark ring, without activating the mark; you can thus use C-u C-SPC or C-x C-x to return to where you were before beginning the search. See The Mark Ring. (Emacs only does this if the mark was not already active; if the mark was active when you started the search, both C-u C-SPC and C-x C-x will go to the mark.)

To search backwards, use C-r (isearch-backward) instead of C-s to start the search. A backward search finds matches that end before the starting point, just as a forward search finds matches that begin after it.

16.1.2 Repeating Incremental Search

Suppose you search forward for ‘FOO’ and find a match, but not the one you expected to find: the ‘FOO’ you were aiming for occurs later in the buffer. In this event, type another C-s (isearch-repeat-forward) to move to the next occurrence of the search string, or C-r (isearch-repeat-backward) to move to the previous occurrence. You can repeat these commands any number of times. Alternatively, you can supply a numeric prefix argument of n to C-s and C-r to find the nth next or previous occurrence. If you overshoot, you can cancel some C-s commands with DEL. Similarly, each C-r (isearch-repeat-backward) in a backward incremental search repeats the backward search.

If you pause for a little while during incremental search, Emacs highlights all the other possible matches for the search string that are present on the screen. This helps you anticipate where you can get to by typing C-s or C-r to repeat the search. The other matches are highlighted differently from the current match, using the customizable face lazy-highlight (see Text Faces). If you don’t like this feature, you can disable it by setting isearch-lazy-highlight to nil. For other customizations related to highlighting matches, see Tailoring Search to Your Needs.

After exiting a search, you can search for the same string again by typing just C-s C-s. The first C-s is the key that invokes incremental search, and the second C-s means to search again for the last search string. Similarly, C-r C-r searches backward for the last search string. In determining the last search string, it doesn’t matter whether that string was searched for with C-s or C-r.

If you are searching forward but you realize you were looking for something before the starting point, type C-r to switch to a backward search, leaving the search string unchanged. Similarly, C-s in a backward search switches to a forward search.

When you change the direction of a search, the first command you type will, by default, remain on the same match, and the cursor will move to the other end of the match. To move to another match immediately, customize the variable isearch-repeat-on-direction-change to t.

If a search is failing and you ask to repeat it by typing another C-s, it starts again from the beginning of the buffer. Repeating a failing reverse search with C-r starts again from the end. This is called wrapping around, and ‘Wrapped’ appears in the search prompt once this has happened. If you keep on going past the original starting point of the search, it changes to ‘Overwrapped’, which means that you are revisiting matches that you have already seen.

You can control what happens when there are no more matches by customizing the isearch-wrap-pause user option. If it is t (the default), signal an error. (Repeating the search will wrap around.) If no, issue a ding and wrap immediately after reaching the last match. If no-ding, wrap immediately, but don’t ding. With the values no and no-ding the search will try to wrap around also on typing a character. Finally, if nil, never wrap, but just stop at the last match.

To reuse earlier search strings, use the search ring. The commands M-p (isearch-ring-retreat) and M-n (isearch-ring-advance) move through the ring to pick a search string to reuse. These commands leave the selected search ring element in the minibuffer, where you can edit it. Type C-s/C-r or RET to accept the string and start searching for it. The number of most recently used search strings saved in the search ring is specified by the variable search-ring-max, 16 by default.

To edit the current search string in the minibuffer without replacing it with items from the search ring, type M-e (isearch-edit-string) or click mouse-1 in the minibuffer. Type RET, C-s or C-r to finish editing the string and search for it. Type C-f or RIGHT to add to the search string characters following point from the buffer from which you started the search.

16.1.3 Isearch Yanking

In many cases, you will want to use text at or near point as your search string. The commands described in this subsection let you do that conveniently.

C-w (isearch-yank-word-or-char) appends the next character or word at point to the search string. This is an easy way to search for another occurrence of the text at point. (The decision of whether to copy a character or a word is heuristic.) With a prefix numeric argument of n, append the next n characters or words.

C-M-w (isearch-yank-symbol-or-char) appends the next character or symbol at point to the search string. This is an easy way to search for another occurrence of the symbol at point. (The decision of whether to copy a character or a symbol is heuristic.) With a prefix numeric argument of n, append the next n characters or symbols.

M-s C-e (isearch-yank-line) appends the rest of the current line to the search string. If point is already at the end of a line, it appends the next line. With a prefix argument n, it appends the next n lines.

Similarly, C-M-z (isearch-yank-until-char) appends to the search string everything from point until the next occurrence of a specified character (not including that character). This is especially useful for keyboard macros, for example in programming languages or markup languages in which that character marks a token boundary. With a prefix numeric argument of n, the command appends everything from point to the nth occurrence of the specified character.

Within incremental search, C-y (isearch-yank-kill) appends the current kill to the search string. M-y (isearch-yank-pop), if called after C-y during incremental search, replaces that appended text with an earlier kill, similar to the usual M-y (yank-pop) command. Clicking mouse-2 in the echo area appends the current X selection (see Cut and Paste with Other Window Applications) to the search string (isearch-yank-x-selection).

C-M-d (isearch-del-char) deletes the last character from the search string, and C-M-y (isearch-yank-char) appends the character after point to the search string. An alternative method to add the character after point is to enter the minibuffer with M-e (see Repeating Incremental Search) and type C-f or RIGHT at the end of the search string in the minibuffer. Each C-f or RIGHT you type adds another character following point to the search string.

Normally, when the search is case-insensitive, text yanked into the search string is converted to lower case, so that the search remains case-insensitive (see case folding). However, if the value of the variable search-upper-case (see search-upper-case) is other than not-yanks, that disables this down-casing.

To begin a new incremental search with the text near point yanked into the initial search string, type M-s M-. that runs the command isearch-forward-thing-at-point. If the region was active, then it yanks the text from the region into the search string. Otherwise, it tries to yank a URL, a symbol or an expression found near point. What to yank is defined by the user option isearch-forward-thing-at-point.

16.1.4 Errors in Incremental Search

If your string is not found at all, the echo area says ‘Failing I-Search’, and the cursor moves past the place where Emacs found as much of your string as it could. Thus, if you search for ‘FOOT’, and there is no ‘FOOT’, you might see the cursor after the ‘FOO’ in ‘FOOL’. In the echo area, the part of the search string that failed to match is highlighted using the face isearch-fail.

At this point, there are several things you can do. If your string was mistyped, use DEL to cancel a previous input item (see Basics of Incremental Search), C-M-d to erase one character at a time, or M-e to edit it. If you like the place you have found, you can type RET to remain there. Or you can type C-g, which removes from the search string the characters that could not be found (the ‘T’ in ‘FOOT’), leaving those that were found (the ‘FOO’ in ‘FOOT’). A second C-g at that point cancels the search entirely, returning point to where it was when the search started.

The quit command, C-g, does special things during searches; just what it does depends on the status of the search. If the search has found what you specified and is waiting for input, C-g cancels the entire search, moving the cursor back to where you started the search. If C-g is typed when there are characters in the search string that have not been found—because Emacs is still searching for them, or because it has failed to find them—then the search string characters which have not been found are discarded from the search string. With them gone, the search is now successful and waiting for more input, so a second C-g will cancel the entire search.

16.1.5 Special Input for Incremental Search

In addition to characters described in the previous subsections, some of the other characters you type during incremental search have special effects. They are described here.

To toggle lax space matching (see lax space matching), type M-s SPC.

To toggle case sensitivity of the search, type M-c or M-s c. See case folding. If the search string includes upper-case letters, the search is case-sensitive by default.

To toggle whether or not the search will consider similar and equivalent characters as a match, type M-s '. See character folding. If the search string includes accented characters, that disables character folding during that search.

To toggle whether or not the search will find text made invisible by overlays, type M-s i (isearch-toggle-invisible). See Outline Search. To make all incremental searches find matches inside invisible text, whether due to text properties or overlay properties, customize search-invisible to the value t.

To toggle between non-regexp and regexp incremental search, type M-r or M-s r (isearch-toggle-regexp). See Regular Expression Search.

To toggle symbol mode, type M-s _. See Symbol Search.

To search for a newline character, type C-j as part of the search string.

To search for non-ASCII characters, use one of the following methods during incremental search:

Type C-q (isearch-quote-char), followed by a non-graphic character or a sequence of octal digits. This adds a character to the search string, similar to inserting into a buffer using C-q (see Inserting Text). For example, C-q C-s during incremental search adds the ‘control-S’ character to the search string.
Use an input method (see Input Methods). If an input method is enabled in the current buffer when you start the search, the same method will be active in the minibuffer when you type the search string. While typing the search string, you can toggle the input method with C-\ (isearch-toggle-input-method). You can also turn on a non-default input method with C-^ (isearch-toggle-specified-input-method), which prompts for the name of the input method. When an input method is active during incremental search, the search prompt includes the input method mnemonic, like this:

I-search [im]:

where im is the mnemonic of the active input method. Any input method you enable during incremental search remains enabled in the current buffer afterwards. Finally, you can temporarily enable a transient input method (see transient input method) with C-x \ (isearch-transient-input-method) to insert a single character to the search string using an input method, and automatically disable the input method afterwards.

Type C-x 8 RET (isearch-char-by-name), followed by a Unicode name or code-point in hex. This adds the specified character into the search string, similar to the usual insert-char command (see Inserting Text).

You can also include Emoji sequences in the search string. Type C-x 8 e RET (isearch-emoji-by-name), followed by the Unicode name of an Emoji (for example, smiling face or heart with arrow). This adds the specified Emoji to the search string. If you don’t know the name of the Emoji you want to search for, you can use C-x 8 e l (emoji-list) and C-x 8 e d (emoji-describe) (see Input Methods).

Typing M-s o in incremental search invokes isearch-occur, which runs occur with the current search string. See occur.

Typing M-% (isearch-query-replace) in incremental search invokes query-replace or query-replace-regexp (depending on search mode) with the current search string used as the string to replace. A negative prefix argument means to replace backward. See Query Replace. Typing C-M-% (isearch-query-replace-regexp) invokes query-replace-regexp with the current search string used as the regexp to replace.

Typing M-TAB in incremental search invokes isearch-complete, which attempts to complete the search string using the search ring (the previous search strings you used) as a list of completion alternatives. See Completion. In many operating systems, the M-TAB key sequence is captured by the window manager; you then need to rebind isearch-complete to another key sequence if you want to use it (see Changing Key Bindings Interactively).

You can exit the search while leaving the matches highlighted by typing M-s h r (isearch-highlight-regexp). This runs highlight-regexp (see Interactive Highlighting), passing it the regexp derived from the search string and prompting you for the face to use for highlighting. To highlight whole lines containing matches (rather than just the matches), type M-s h l (isearch-highlight-lines-matching-regexp). In either case, to remove the highlighting, type M-s h u (unhighlight-regexp).

When incremental search is active, you can type C-h C-h (isearch-help-map) to access interactive help options, including a list of special key bindings. These key bindings are part of the keymap isearch-mode-map (see Keymaps).

When incremental search is active, typing M-s M-> will go to the last occurrence of the search string, and M-s M-< will go to the first occurrence. With a prefix numeric argument of n, these commands will go to the nth occurrence of the search string counting from the beginning or end of the buffer, respectively.

16.1.6 Not Exiting Incremental Search

This subsection describes how to control whether typing a command not specifically meaningful in searches exits the search before executing the command. It also describes three categories of commands which you can type without exiting the current incremental search, even though they are not themselves part of incremental search.

Normally, typing a command that is not bound by the incremental search exits the search before executing the command. Thus, the command operates on the buffer from which you invoked the search. However, if you customize the variable search-exit-option to append, the characters which you type that are not interpreted by the incremental search are simply appended to the search string. This is so you could include in the search string control characters, such as C-a, that would normally exit the search and invoke the command bound to them on the buffer.

Prefix Arguments

In incremental search, when you type a command that specifies a prefix argument (see Numeric Arguments), by default it will apply either to the next action in the search or to the command that exits the search. In other words, entering a prefix argument will not by itself terminate the search.

In previous versions of Emacs, entering a prefix argument always terminated the search. You can revert to this behavior by setting the variable isearch-allow-prefix to nil.

When isearch-allow-scroll is non-nil (see below), prefix arguments always have the default behavior described above, i.e., they don’t terminate the search, even if isearch-allow-prefix is nil.

Scrolling Commands

Normally, scrolling commands exit incremental search. But if you change the variable isearch-allow-scroll to a non-nil value, that enables the use of the scroll-bar, as well as keyboard scrolling commands like C-v, M-v, and C-l (see Scrolling), which have a non-nil scroll-command property, without exiting the search. This applies only to calling these commands via their bound key sequences—typing M-x will still exit the search. You can give prefix arguments to these commands in the usual way. This feature normally won’t let you scroll the current match out of visibility; but if you customize isearch-allow-scroll to the special value unlimited, that restriction is lifted.

The isearch-allow-scroll feature also affects some other commands, such as C-x 2 (split-window-below) and C-x ^ (enlarge-window), which don’t exactly scroll but do affect where the text appears on the screen. In fact, it affects any command that has a non-nil isearch-scroll property. So you can control which commands are affected by changing these properties.

For example, to make C-h l usable within an incremental search in all future Emacs sessions, use C-h c to find what command it runs (see Documentation for a Key), which is view-lossage. Then you can put the following line in your init file (see The Emacs Initialization File):

(put 'view-lossage 'isearch-scroll t)

This feature can be applied to any command that doesn’t permanently change point, the buffer contents, the match data, the current buffer, or the selected window and frame. The command must not itself attempt an incremental search. This feature is disabled if isearch-allow-scroll is nil (which it is by default).

Likewise, if you change the variable isearch-allow-motion to a non-nil value, this enables the use of the keyboard motion commands M-<, M->, C-v and M-v, to move respectively to the first occurrence of the current search string in the buffer, the last one, the first one after the current window, and the last one before the current window. The search direction does not change when these motion commands are used, unless you change the variable isearch-motion-changes-direction to a non-nil value, in which case the search direction is forward after M-< and C-v, and backward after M-> and M-v.

Motion Commands

When isearch-yank-on-move is customized to shift, you can extend the search string by holding down the shift key while typing cursor motion commands. It will yank text that ends at the new position after moving point in the current buffer.

When isearch-yank-on-move is t, you can extend the search string without using the shift key for cursor motion commands, but it applies only for certain motion command that have the isearch-move property on their symbols.

16.1.7 Searching the Minibuffer

If you start an incremental search while the minibuffer is active, Emacs searches the contents of the minibuffer. Unlike searching an ordinary buffer, the search string is not shown in the echo area, because that is used to display the minibuffer.

If an incremental search fails in the minibuffer, it tries searching the minibuffer history. See Minibuffer History. You can visualize the minibuffer and its history as a series of pages, with the earliest history element on the first page and the current minibuffer on the last page. A forward search, C-s, searches forward to later pages; a reverse search, C-r, searches backwards to earlier pages. Like in ordinary buffer search, a failing search can wrap around, going from the last page to the first page or vice versa.

When the current match is on a history element, that history element is pulled into the minibuffer. If you exit the incremental search normally (e.g., by typing RET), it remains in the minibuffer afterwards. Canceling the search, with C-g, restores the contents of the minibuffer when you began the search.

16.2 Nonincremental Search

Emacs also has conventional nonincremental search commands, which require you to type the entire search string before searching begins.

C-s RET string RET

Search for string.

C-r RET string RET

Search backward for string.

To start a nonincremental search, first type C-s RET. This enters the minibuffer to read the search string; terminate the string with RET, and then the search takes place. If the string is not found, the search command signals an error.

When you type C-s RET, the C-s invokes incremental search as usual. That command is specially programmed to invoke the command for nonincremental search, if the string you specify is empty. (Such an empty argument would otherwise be useless.) C-r RET does likewise, invoking the nonincremental backward-searching command.

Nonincremental search can also be invoked from the menu bar’s ‘Edit->Search’ menu.

You can also use two simpler commands, M-x search-forward and M-x search-backward. These commands look for the literal strings you specify, and don’t support any of the lax-search features (see Lax Matching During Searching) except case folding.

16.3 Word Search

A word search finds a sequence of words without regard to the type of punctuation between them. For instance, if you enter a search string that consists of two words separated by a single space, the search matches any sequence of those two words separated by one or more spaces, newlines, or other punctuation characters. This is particularly useful for searching text documents, because you don’t have to worry whether the words you are looking for are separated by newlines or spaces. Note that major modes for programming languages or other specialized modes can modify the definition of a word to suit their syntactic needs.

M-s w

If incremental search is active, toggle word search mode (isearch-toggle-word); otherwise, begin an incremental forward word search (isearch-forward-word).

M-s w RET words RET

Search for words, using a forward nonincremental word search.

M-s w C-r RET words RET

Search backward for words, using a nonincremental word search.

M-s M-w

Search the Web for the text in region.

To begin a forward incremental word search, type M-s w. If incremental search is not already active, this runs the command isearch-forward-word. If incremental search is already active (whether a forward or backward search), M-s w runs the command isearch-toggle-word, which switches to a word search while keeping the direction of the search and the current search string unchanged. You can toggle word search back off by typing M-s w again.

To begin a nonincremental word search, type M-s w RET for a forward search, or M-s w C-r RET for a backward search. These run the commands word-search-forward and word-search-backward respectively.

Incremental and nonincremental word searches differ slightly in the way they find a match. In a nonincremental word search, each word in the search string must exactly match a whole word. In an incremental word search, the matching is more lax: while you are typing the search string, its first and last words need not match whole words. This is so that the matching can proceed incrementally as you type. This additional laxity does not apply to the lazy highlight (see Incremental Search), which always matches whole words. While you are typing the search string, ‘Pending’ appears in the search prompt until you use a search repeating key like C-s.

The word search commands don’t perform character folding, and toggling lax whitespace matching (see lax space matching) has no effect on them.

To search the Web for the text in region, type M-s M-w. This command performs an Internet search for the words in region using the search engine whose URL is specified by the variable eww-search-prefix (see EWW in

The Emacs Web Wowser Manual

). If the region is not active, or doesn’t contain any words, this command prompts the user for a URL or keywords to search.

16.4 Symbol Search

A symbol search is much like an ordinary search, except that the boundaries of the search must match the boundaries of a symbol. The meaning of symbol in this context depends on the major mode, and usually refers to a source code token, such as a Lisp symbol in Emacs Lisp mode. For instance, if you perform an incremental symbol search for the Lisp symbol forward-word, it would not match isearch-forward-word. This feature is thus mainly useful for searching source code.

M-s _

If incremental search is active, toggle symbol search mode (isearch-toggle-symbol); otherwise, begin an incremental forward symbol search (isearch-forward-symbol).

M-s .

Start a symbol incremental search forward with the symbol found near point added to the search string initially.

M-s _ RET symbol RET

Search forward for symbol, nonincrementally.

M-s _ C-r RET symbol RET

Search backward for symbol, nonincrementally.

To begin a forward incremental symbol search, type M-s _ (or M-s . if the symbol to search is near point). If incremental search is not already active, M-s _ runs the command isearch-forward-symbol and M-s . runs the command isearch-forward-symbol-at-point. With a numeric prefix argument of n, M-s . will search for the nthe next occurrence of the symbol at point; negative values of n search backwards. If incremental search is already active, M-s _ switches to a symbol search, preserving the direction of the search and the current search string; you can disable symbol search by typing M-s _ again. In incremental symbol search, while you are typing the search string, only the beginning of the search string is required to match the beginning of a symbol, and ‘Pending’ appears in the search prompt until you use a search repeating key like C-s.

To begin a nonincremental symbol search, type M-s _ RET for a forward search, or M-s _ C-r RET or a backward search. In nonincremental symbol searches, the beginning and end of the search string are required to match the beginning and end of a symbol, respectively.

The symbol search commands don’t perform character folding, and toggling lax whitespace matching (see lax space matching) has no effect on them.

16.5 Regular Expression Search

A regular expression (or regexp for short) is a pattern that denotes a class of alternative strings to match. Emacs provides both incremental and nonincremental ways to search for a match for a regexp. The syntax of regular expressions is explained in the next section.

C-M-s

Begin incremental regexp search (isearch-forward-regexp).

C-M-r

Begin reverse incremental regexp search (isearch-backward-regexp).

Incremental search for a regexp is done by typing C-M-s (isearch-forward-regexp), by invoking C-s with a prefix argument (whose value does not matter), or by typing M-r within a forward incremental search. This command reads a search string incrementally just like C-s, but it treats the search string as a regexp rather than looking for an exact match against the text in the buffer. Each time you add text to the search string, you make the regexp longer, and the new regexp is searched for. To search backward for a regexp, use C-M-r (isearch-backward-regexp), C-r with a prefix argument, or M-r within a backward incremental search.

All of the special key sequences in an ordinary incremental search (see Special Input for Incremental Search) do similar things in an incremental regexp search. For instance, typing C-s immediately after starting the search retrieves the last incremental search regexp used and searches forward for it. Incremental regexp and non-regexp searches have independent defaults. They also have separate search rings, which you can access with M-p and M-n. The maximum number of search regexps saved in the search ring is determined by the value of regexp-search-ring-max, 16 by default.

Unlike ordinary incremental search, incremental regexp search does not use lax space matching by default. To toggle this feature use M-s SPC (isearch-toggle-lax-whitespace). Then any SPC typed in incremental regexp search will match any sequence of one or more whitespace characters. The variable search-whitespace-regexp specifies the regexp for the lax space matching. See Special Input for Incremental Search.

Also unlike ordinary incremental search, incremental regexp search cannot use character folding (see Lax Matching During Searching). (If you toggle character folding during incremental regexp search with M-s ', the search becomes a non-regexp search and the search pattern you typed is interpreted as a literal string.)

In some cases, adding characters to the regexp in an incremental regexp search can make the cursor move back and start again. For example, if you have searched for ‘foo’ and you add ‘\|bar’, the cursor backs up in case the first ‘bar’ precedes the first ‘foo’. (The prompt will change to say “Pending” to notify the user that this recalculation has happened.) See Syntax of Regular Expressions.

Forward and backward regexp search are not symmetrical, because regexp matching in Emacs always operates forward, starting with the beginning of the regexp. Thus, forward regexp search scans forward, trying a forward match at each possible starting position. Backward regexp search scans backward, trying a forward match at each possible starting position. These search methods are not mirror images.

Nonincremental search for a regexp is done with the commands re-search-forward and re-search-backward. You can invoke these with M-x, or by way of incremental regexp search with C-M-s RET and C-M-r RET. When you invoke these commands with M-x, they search for the exact regexp you specify, and thus don’t support any lax-search features (see Lax Matching During Searching) except case folding.

If you use the incremental regexp search commands with a prefix argument, they perform ordinary string search, like isearch-forward and isearch-backward. See Incremental Search.

16.6 Syntax of Regular Expressions

This section (and this manual in general) describes regular expression features that users typically use. See Regular Expressions in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for additional features used mainly in Lisp programs.

Regular expressions have a syntax in which a few characters are special constructs and the rest are ordinary. An ordinary character matches that same character and nothing else. The special characters are ‘$^.*+?[\’. The character ‘]’ is special if it ends a character alternative (see below). The character ‘-’ is special inside a character alternative. Any other character appearing in a regular expression is ordinary, unless a ‘\’ precedes it. (When you use regular expressions in a Lisp program, each ‘\’ must be doubled, see the example near the end of this section.)

For example, ‘f’ is not a special character, so it is ordinary, and therefore ‘f’ is a regular expression that matches the string ‘f’ and no other string. (It does not match the string ‘ff’.) Likewise, ‘o’ is a regular expression that matches only ‘o’. (When case distinctions are being ignored, these regexps also match ‘F’ and ‘O’, but we consider this a generalization of “the same string”, rather than an exception.)

Any two regular expressions a and b can be concatenated. The result is a regular expression which matches a string if a matches some amount of the beginning of that string and b matches the rest of the string. As a trivial example, concatenating the regular expressions ‘f’ and ‘o’ gives the regular expression ‘fo’, which matches only the string ‘fo’. To do something less trivial, you need to use one of the special characters. Here is a list of them.

. (Period)

is a special character that matches any single character except a newline. For example, the regular expressions ‘a.b’ matches any three-character string that begins with ‘a’ and ends with ‘b’.

*

is not a construct by itself; it is a postfix operator that means to match the preceding regular expression repetitively any number of times, as many times as possible. Thus, ‘o*’ matches any number of ‘o’s, including no ‘o’s.

‘*’ always applies to the smallest possible preceding expression. Thus, ‘fo*’ has a repeating ‘o’, not a repeating ‘fo’. It matches ‘f’, ‘fo’, ‘foo’, and so on.

The matcher processes a ‘*’ construct by matching, immediately, as many repetitions as can be found. Then it continues with the rest of the pattern. If that fails, backtracking occurs, discarding some of the matches of the ‘*’-modified construct in case that makes it possible to match the rest of the pattern. For example, in matching ‘ca*ar’ against the string ‘caaar’, the ‘a*’ first tries to match all three ‘a’s; but the rest of the pattern is ‘ar’ and there is only ‘r’ left to match, so this try fails. The next alternative is for ‘a*’ to match only two ‘a’s. With this choice, the rest of the regexp matches successfully.

+

is a postfix operator, similar to ‘*’ except that it must match the preceding expression at least once. Thus, ‘ca+r’ matches the strings ‘car’ and ‘caaaar’ but not the string ‘cr’, whereas ‘ca*r’ matches all three strings.

?

is a postfix operator, similar to ‘*’ except that it can match the preceding expression either once or not at all. Thus, ‘ca?r’ matches ‘car’ or ‘cr’, and nothing else.

*?, +?, ??

are non-greedy variants of the operators above. The normal operators ‘*’, ‘+’, ‘?’ match as much as they can, as long as the overall regexp can still match. With a following ‘?’, they will match as little as possible.

Thus, both ‘ab*’ and ‘ab*?’ can match the string ‘a’ and the string ‘abbbb’; but if you try to match them both against the text ‘abbb’, ‘ab*’ will match it all (the longest valid match), while ‘ab*?’ will match just ‘a’ (the shortest valid match).

Non-greedy operators match the shortest possible string starting at a given starting point; in a forward search, though, the earliest possible starting point for match is always the one chosen. Thus, if you search for ‘a.*?$’ against the text ‘abbab’ followed by a newline, it matches the whole string. Since it can match starting at the first ‘a’, it does.

[ … ]

is a set of alternative characters, or a character set, beginning with ‘[’ and terminated by ‘]’.

In the simplest case, the characters between the two brackets are what this set can match. Thus, ‘[ad]’ matches either one ‘a’ or one ‘d’, and ‘[ad]*’ matches any string composed of just ‘a’s and ‘d’s (including the empty string). It follows that ‘c[ad]*r’ matches ‘cr’, ‘car’, ‘cdr’, ‘caddaar’, etc.

You can also include character ranges in a character set, by writing the starting and ending characters with a ‘-’ between them. Thus, ‘[a-z]’ matches any lower-case ASCII letter. Ranges may be intermixed freely with individual characters, as in ‘[a-z$%.]’, which matches any lower-case ASCII letter or ‘$’, ‘%’ or period. As another example, ‘[α-ωί]’ matches all lower-case Greek letters.

You can also include certain special character classes in a character set. A ‘[:’ and balancing ‘:]’ enclose a character class inside a set of alternative characters. For instance, ‘[[:alnum:]]’ matches any letter or digit. See Char Classes in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for a list of character classes.

To include a ‘]’ in a character set, you must make it the first character. For example, ‘[]a]’ matches ‘]’ or ‘a’. To include a ‘-’, write ‘-’ as the last character of the set, tho you can also put it first or after a range. Thus, ‘[]-]’ matches both ‘]’ and ‘-’.

To include ‘^’ in a set, put it anywhere but at the beginning of the set. (At the beginning, it complements the set—see below.)

When you use a range in case-insensitive search, you should write both ends of the range in upper case, or both in lower case, or both should be non-letters. The behavior of a mixed-case range such as ‘A-z’ is somewhat ill-defined, and it may change in future Emacs versions.

[^ … ]

‘[^’ begins a complemented character set, which matches any character except the ones specified. Thus, ‘[^a-z0-9A-Z]’ matches all characters except ASCII letters and digits.

‘^’ is not special in a character set unless it is the first character. The character following the ‘^’ is treated as if it were first (in other words, ‘-’ and ‘]’ are not special there).

A complemented character set can match a newline, unless newline is mentioned as one of the characters not to match. This is in contrast to the handling of regexps in programs such as grep.

^

is a special character that matches the empty string, but only at the beginning of a line in the text being matched. Otherwise it fails to match anything. Thus, ‘^foo’ matches a ‘foo’ that occurs at the beginning of a line.

For historical compatibility reasons, ‘^’ can be used with this meaning only at the beginning of the regular expression, or after ‘\(’ or ‘\|’.

$

is similar to ‘^’ but matches only at the end of a line. Thus, ‘x+$’ matches a string of one ‘x’ or more at the end of a line.

For historical compatibility reasons, ‘$’ can be used with this meaning only at the end of the regular expression, or before ‘\)’ or ‘\|’.

\

has two functions: it quotes the special characters (including ‘\’), and it introduces additional special constructs.

Because ‘\’ quotes special characters, ‘\$’ is a regular expression that matches only ‘$’, and ‘\[’ is a regular expression that matches only ‘[’, and so on.

See the following section for the special constructs that begin with ‘\’.

Note: for historical compatibility, special characters are treated as ordinary ones if they are in contexts where their special meanings make no sense. For example, ‘*foo’ treats ‘*’ as ordinary since there is no preceding expression on which the ‘*’ can act. It is poor practice to depend on this behavior; it is better to quote the special character anyway, regardless of where it appears.

As a ‘\’ is not special inside a set of alternative characters, it can never remove the special meaning of ‘-’, ‘^’ or ‘]’. You should not quote these characters when they have no special meaning. This would not clarify anything, since backslashes can legitimately precede these characters where they have special meaning, as in ‘[^\]’ ("[^\\]" for Lisp string syntax), which matches any single character except a backslash.

16.7 Backslash in Regular Expressions

For the most part, ‘\’ followed by any character matches only that character. However, there are several exceptions: two-character sequences starting with ‘\’ that have special meanings. The second character in the sequence is always an ordinary character when used on its own. Here is a table of ‘\’ constructs.

\|

specifies an alternative. Two regular expressions a and b with ‘\|’ in between form an expression that matches some text if either a matches it or b matches it. It works by trying to match a, and if that fails, by trying to match b.

Thus, ‘foo\|bar’ matches either ‘foo’ or ‘bar’ but no other string.

‘\|’ applies to the largest possible surrounding expressions. Only a surrounding ‘\( … \)’ grouping can limit the grouping power of ‘\|’.

Full backtracking capability exists to handle multiple uses of ‘\|’.

\( … \)

is a grouping construct that serves three purposes:

To enclose a set of ‘\|’ alternatives for other operations. Thus, ‘\(foo\|bar\)x’ matches either ‘foox’ or ‘barx’.
To enclose a complicated expression for the postfix operators ‘*’, ‘+’ and ‘?’ to operate on. Thus, ‘ba\(na\)*’ matches ‘bananana’, etc., with any (zero or more) number of ‘na’ strings.
To record a matched substring for future reference.

This last application is not a consequence of the idea of a parenthetical grouping; it is a separate feature that is assigned as a second meaning to the same ‘\( … \)’ construct. In practice there is usually no conflict between the two meanings; when there is a conflict, you can use a shy group, described below.

\(?: … \)

specifies a shy group that does not record the matched substring; you can’t refer back to it with ‘\d’ (see below). This is useful in mechanically combining regular expressions, so that you can add groups for syntactic purposes without interfering with the numbering of the groups that are meant to be referred to.

\d

matches the same text that matched the dth occurrence of a ‘\( … \)’ construct. This is called a back reference.

After the end of a ‘\( … \)’ construct, the matcher remembers the beginning and end of the text matched by that construct. Then, later on in the regular expression, you can use ‘\’ followed by the digit d to mean “match the same text matched the dth ‘\( … \)’ construct”.

The strings matching the first nine ‘\( … \)’ constructs appearing in a regular expression are assigned numbers 1 through 9 in the order that the open-parentheses appear in the regular expression. So you can use ‘\1’ through ‘\9’ to refer to the text matched by the corresponding ‘\( … \)’ constructs.

For example, ‘\(.*\)\1’ matches any newline-free string that is composed of two identical halves. The ‘\(.*\)’ matches the first half, which may be anything, but the ‘\1’ that follows must match the same exact text.

If a particular ‘\( … \)’ construct matches more than once (which can easily happen if it is followed by ‘*’), only the last match is recorded.

\{m\}

is a postfix operator specifying m repetitions—that is, the preceding regular expression must match exactly m times in a row. For example, ‘x\{4\}’ matches the string ‘xxxx’ and nothing else.

\{m,n\}

is a postfix operator specifying between m and n repetitions—that is, the preceding regular expression must match at least m times, but no more than n times. If n is omitted, then there is no upper limit, but the preceding regular expression must match at least m times.
‘\{0,1\}’ is equivalent to ‘?’.
‘\{0,\}’ is equivalent to ‘*’.
‘\{1,\}’ is equivalent to ‘+’.

\`

matches the empty string, but only at the beginning of the string or buffer (or its accessible portion) being matched against.

\'

matches the empty string, but only at the end of the string or buffer (or its accessible portion) being matched against.

\=

matches the empty string, but only at point.

\b

matches the empty string, but only at the beginning or end of a word. Thus, ‘\bfoo\b’ matches any occurrence of ‘foo’ as a separate word. ‘\bballs?\b’ matches ‘ball’ or ‘balls’ as a separate word.

‘\b’ matches at the beginning or end of the buffer regardless of what text appears next to it.

\B

matches the empty string, but not at the beginning or end of a word.

\<

matches the empty string, but only at the beginning of a word. ‘\<’ matches at the beginning of the buffer only if a word-constituent character follows.

\>

matches the empty string, but only at the end of a word. ‘\>’ matches at the end of the buffer only if the contents end with a word-constituent character.

\w

matches any word-constituent character. The syntax table determines which characters these are. See Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

\W

matches any character that is not a word-constituent.

\_<

matches the empty string, but only at the beginning of a symbol. A symbol is a sequence of one or more symbol-constituent characters. A symbol-constituent character is a character whose syntax is either ‘w’ or ‘_’. ‘\_<’ matches at the beginning of the buffer only if a symbol-constituent character follows. As with words, the syntax table determines which characters are symbol-constituent.

\_>

matches the empty string, but only at the end of a symbol. ‘\_>’ matches at the end of the buffer only if the contents end with a symbol-constituent character.

\sc

matches any character whose syntax is c. Here c is a character that designates a particular syntax class: thus, ‘w’ for word constituent, ‘-’ or ‘ ’ for whitespace, ‘.’ for ordinary punctuation, etc. See Syntax Class Table in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

\Sc

matches any character whose syntax is not c.

\cc

matches any character that belongs to the category c. For example, ‘\cc’ matches Chinese characters, ‘\cg’ matches Greek characters, etc. For the description of the known categories, type M-x describe-categories RET.

\Cc

matches any character that does not belong to category c.

The constructs that pertain to words and syntax are controlled by the setting of the syntax table. See Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

16.8 Regular Expression Example

Here is an example of a regexp—similar to the regexp that Emacs uses, by default, to recognize the end of a sentence, not including the following space (i.e., the variable sentence-end-base):

[.?!][]\"')}]*

This contains two parts in succession: a character set matching period, ‘?’, or ‘!’, and a character set matching close-brackets, quotes, or parentheses, repeated zero or more times.

16.9 Lax Matching During Searching

Normally, you’d want search commands to disregard certain minor differences between the search string you type and the text being searched. For example, sequences of whitespace characters of different length are usually perceived as equivalent; letter-case differences usually don’t matter; etc. This is known as character equivalence.

This section describes the Emacs lax search features, and how to tailor them to your needs.

By default, search commands perform lax space matching: each space, or sequence of spaces, matches any sequence of one or more whitespace characters in the text. More precisely, Emacs matches each sequence of space characters in the search string to a regular expression specified by the user option search-whitespace-regexp. The default value of this option considers any sequence of spaces and tab characters as whitespace. Hence, ‘foo bar’ matches ‘foo bar’ , ‘foo  bar’ , ‘foo   bar’ , and so on (but not ‘foobar’). If you want to make spaces match sequences of newlines as well as spaces and tabs, customize the option to make its value be the regular expression ‘[ \t\n]+’. (The default behavior of the incremental regexp search is different; see Regular Expression Search.)

If you want whitespace characters to match exactly, you can turn lax space matching off by typing M-s SPC (isearch-toggle-lax-whitespace) within an incremental search. Another M-s SPC turns lax space matching back on. To disable lax whitespace matching for all searches, change search-whitespace-regexp to nil; then each space in the search string matches exactly one space.

Searches in Emacs by default ignore the case of the text they are searching through, if you specify the search string in lower case. Thus, if you specify searching for ‘foo’, then ‘Foo’ and ‘fOO’ also match. Regexps, and in particular character sets, behave likewise: ‘[ab]’ matches ‘a’ or ‘A’ or ‘b’ or ‘B’. This feature is known as case folding, and it is supported in both incremental and non-incremental search modes.

An upper-case letter anywhere in the search string makes the search case-sensitive. Thus, searching for ‘Foo’ does not find ‘foo’ or ‘FOO’. This applies to regular expression search as well as to literal string search. The effect ceases if you delete the upper-case letter from the search string. The variable search-upper-case controls this: if it is non-nil, an upper-case character in the search string makes the search case-sensitive; setting it to nil disables this effect of upper-case characters. The default value of this variable is not-yanks, which makes search case-sensitive if there are upper-case letters in the search string, and also causes text yanked into the search string (see Isearch Yanking) to be down-cased, so that such searches are case-insensitive by default.

If you set the variable case-fold-search to nil, then all letters must match exactly, including case. This is a per-buffer variable; altering the variable normally affects only the current buffer, unless you change its default value. See Local Variables. This variable applies to nonincremental searches also, including those performed by the replace commands (see Replacement Commands) and the minibuffer history matching commands (see Minibuffer History).

Typing M-c or M-s c (isearch-toggle-case-fold) within an incremental search toggles the case sensitivity of that search. The effect does not extend beyond the current incremental search, but it does override the effect of adding or removing an upper-case letter in the current search.

Several related variables control case-sensitivity of searching and matching for specific commands or activities. For instance, tags-case-fold-search controls case sensitivity for find-tag. To find these variables, do M-x apropos-variable RET case-fold-search RET.

Case folding disregards case distinctions among characters, making upper-case characters match lower-case variants, and vice versa. A generalization of case folding is character folding, which disregards wider classes of distinctions among similar characters. For instance, under character folding the letter a matches all of its accented cousins like ä and á, i.e., the match disregards the diacritics that distinguish these variants. In addition, a matches other characters that resemble it, or have it as part of their graphical representation, such as U+00AA FEMININE ORDINAL INDICATOR and U+24D0 CIRCLED LATIN SMALL LETTER A (which looks like a small a inside a circle). Similarly, the ASCII double-quote character " matches all the other variants of double quotes defined by the Unicode standard. Finally, character folding can make a sequence of one or more characters match another sequence of a different length: for example, the sequence of two characters ff matches U+FB00 LATIN SMALL LIGATURE FF and the sequence (a) matches U+249C PARENTHESIZED LATIN SMALL LETTER A. Character sequences that are not identical, but match under character folding are known as equivalent character sequences.

Generally, search commands in Emacs do not by default perform character folding in order to match equivalent character sequences. You can enable this behavior by customizing the variable search-default-mode to char-fold-to-regexp. See Tailoring Search to Your Needs. Within an incremental search, typing M-s ' (isearch-toggle-char-fold) toggles character folding, but only for that search. (Replace commands have a different default, controlled by a separate option; see Replace Commands and Lax Matches.)

By default, typing an explicit variant of a character, such as ä, as part of the search string doesn’t match its base character, such as a. But if you customize the variable char-fold-symmetric to t, then search commands treat equivalent characters the same and use of any of a set of equivalent characters in a search string finds any of them in the text being searched, so typing an accented character ä matches the letter a as well as all the other variants like á.

You can add new foldings using the customizable variable char-fold-include, or remove the existing ones using the customizable variable char-fold-exclude. You can also customize char-fold-override to t to disable all the character equivalences except those you add yourself using char-fold-include.

16.10 Replacement Commands

Emacs provides several commands for performing search-and-replace operations. In addition to the simple M-x replace-string command, there is M-% (query-replace), which presents each occurrence of the search pattern and asks you whether to replace it.

The replace commands normally operate on the text from point to the end of the buffer. When the region is active, they operate on it instead (see The Mark and the Region). The basic replace commands replace one search string (or regexp) with one replacement string. It is possible to perform several replacements in parallel, using the command expand-region-abbrevs (see Controlling Abbrev Expansion).

16.10.1 Unconditional Replacement

M-x replace-string RET string RET newstring RET

Replace every occurrence of string with newstring.

To replace every instance of ‘foo’ after point with ‘bar’, use the command M-x replace-string with the two arguments ‘foo’ and ‘bar’. Replacement happens only in the text after point, so if you want to cover the whole buffer you must go to the beginning first. All occurrences up to the end of the buffer are replaced; to limit replacement to part of the buffer, activate the region around that part. When the region is active, replacement is limited to the region (see The Mark and the Region).

When replace-string exits, it leaves point at the last occurrence replaced. It adds the prior position of point (where the replace-string command was issued) to the mark ring, without activating the mark; use C-u C-SPC to move back there. See The Mark Ring.

A prefix argument restricts replacement to matches that are surrounded by word boundaries.

See Replace Commands and Lax Matches, for details about case-sensitivity and character folding in replace commands.

16.10.2 Regexp Replacement

The M-x replace-string command replaces exact matches for a single string. The similar command M-x replace-regexp replaces any match for a specified regular expression pattern (see Syntax of Regular Expressions).

M-x replace-regexp RET regexp RET newstring RET

Replace every match for regexp with newstring.

In replace-regexp, the newstring need not be constant: it can refer to all or part of what is matched by the regexp. ‘\&’ in newstring stands for the entire match being replaced. ‘\d’ in newstring, where d is a digit starting from 1, stands for whatever matched the dth parenthesized grouping in regexp. (This is called a “back reference”.) ‘\#’ refers to the count of replacements already made in this command, as a decimal number. In the first replacement, ‘\#’ stands for ‘0’; in the second, for ‘1’; and so on. For example,

M-x replace-regexp RET c[ad]+r RET \&-safe RET

replaces (for example) ‘cadr’ with ‘cadr-safe’ and ‘cddr’ with ‘cddr-safe’.

M-x replace-regexp RET \(c[ad]+r\)-safe RET \1 RET

performs the inverse transformation. To include a ‘\’ in the text to replace with, you must enter ‘\\’.

If you want to enter part of the replacement string by hand each time, use ‘\?’ in the replacement string. Each replacement will ask you to edit the replacement string in the minibuffer, putting point where the ‘\?’ was.

The remainder of this subsection is intended for specialized tasks and requires knowledge of Lisp. Most readers can skip it.

You can use Lisp expressions to calculate parts of the replacement string. To do this, write ‘\,’ followed by the expression in the replacement string. Each replacement calculates the value of the expression and converts it to text without quoting (if it’s a string, this means using the string’s contents), and uses it in the replacement string in place of the expression itself. If the expression is a symbol, one space in the replacement string after the symbol name goes with the symbol name, so the value replaces them both.

Inside such an expression, you can use some special sequences. ‘\&’ and ‘\d’ refer here, as usual, to the entire match as a string, and to a submatch as a string. d may be multiple digits, and the value of ‘\d’ is nil if the d’th parenthesized grouping did not match. You can also use ‘\#&’ and ‘\#d’ to refer to those matches as numbers (this is valid when the match or submatch has the form of a numeral). ‘\#’ here too stands for the number of already-completed replacements.

For example, we can exchange ‘x’ and ‘y’ this way:

M-x replace-regexp RET \(x\)\|y RET
\,(if \1 "y" "x") RET

For computing replacement strings for ‘\,’, the format function is often useful (see Formatting Strings in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). For example, to add consecutively numbered strings like ‘ABC00042’ to columns 73 to 80 (unless they are already occupied), you can use

M-x replace-regexp RET ^.\{0,72\}$ RET
\,(format "%-72sABC%05d" \& \#) RET

16.10.3 Replace Commands and Lax Matches

This subsection describes the behavior of replace commands with respect to lax matches (see Lax Matching During Searching) and how to customize it. In general, replace commands mostly default to stricter matching than their search counterparts.

Unlike incremental search, the replacement commands do not use lax space matching (see lax space matching) by default. To enable lax space matching for replacement, change the variable replace-lax-whitespace to non-nil. (This only affects how Emacs finds the text to replace, not the replacement text.)

A companion variable replace-regexp-lax-whitespace controls whether query-replace-regexp uses lax whitespace matching when searching for patterns.

If the first argument of a replace command is all lower case, the command ignores case while searching for occurrences to replace—provided case-fold-search is non-nil and search-upper-case is also non-nil. If search-upper-case (see search-upper-case) is nil, whether searching ignores case is determined by case-fold-search alone, regardless of letter-case of the command’s first argument. If case-fold-search is set to nil, case is always significant in all searches.

In addition, when the second argument of a replace command is all or partly lower case, replacement commands try to preserve the case pattern of each occurrence. Thus, the command

M-x replace-string RET foo RET bar RET

replaces a lower case ‘foo’ with a lower case ‘bar’, an all-caps ‘FOO’ with ‘BAR’, and a capitalized ‘Foo’ with ‘Bar’. (These three alternatives—lower case, all caps, and capitalized, are the only ones that replace-string can distinguish.) Note that Emacs decides whether to up-case or capitalize the replacement text by analyzing each word in the text being replaced, and will preserve the letter-case of the replaced text only if all of its words use the same letter-case. Thus, the command

M-x replace-string RET foo bar RET baz quux RET

replaces ‘Foo Bar’ with ‘Baz Quux’ because both words in ‘Foo Bar’ are capitalized. By contrast, the same command replaces ‘Foo bar’ with ‘baz quux’, i.e. it leaves the letter-case of the replacement text unchanged, since the two words in ‘Foo bar’ use different capitalization. What exactly is considered a “word” depends on the syntax tables that are in effect in the current buffer (see Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

); thus, ‘Foo_Bar’ is two words in Text mode, but could be a single word in some major mode that supports a programming language.

If upper-case letters are used in the replacement string, they remain upper case every time that text is inserted. If upper-case letters are used in the first argument, the second argument is always substituted exactly as given, with no case conversion. Likewise, if either case-replace or case-fold-search is set to nil, replacement is done without case conversion.

The replacement commands by default do not use character folding (see character folding) when looking for the text to replace. To enable character folding for matching in query-replace and replace-string, set the variable replace-char-fold to a non-nil value. (This setting does not affect the replacement text, only how Emacs finds the text to replace. It also doesn’t affect replace-regexp.)

16.10.4 Query Replace

M-% string RET newstring RET

Replace some occurrences of string with newstring.

C-M-% regexp RET newstring RET

Replace some matches for regexp with newstring.

If you want to change only some of the occurrences of ‘foo’ to ‘bar’, not all of them, use M-% (query-replace). This command finds occurrences of ‘foo’ one by one, displays each occurrence and asks you whether to replace it. Aside from querying, query-replace works just like replace-string (see Unconditional Replacement). In particular, it preserves case provided that case-replace is non-nil, as it normally is (see Replace Commands and Lax Matches). A numeric argument means to consider only occurrences that are bounded by word-delimiter characters. A negative prefix argument replaces backward.

C-M-% performs regexp search and replace (query-replace-regexp). It works like replace-regexp except that it queries like query-replace.

You can reuse earlier replacements with these commands. When query-replace or query-replace-regexp prompts for the search string, use M-p and M-n to show previous replacements in the form ‘from -> to’, where from is the search pattern, to is its replacement, and the separator between them is determined by the value of the variable query-replace-from-to-separator. Type RET to select the desired replacement. If the value of this variable is nil, replacements are not added to the command history, and cannot be reused.

These commands highlight the current match using the face query-replace. You can disable this highlight by setting the variable query-replace-highlight to nil. They highlight other matches using lazy-highlight just like incremental search (see Incremental Search); this can be disabled by setting query-replace-lazy-highlight to nil. By default, query-replace-regexp will show the substituted replacement string for the current match in the minibuffer. If you want to keep special sequences ‘\&’ and ‘\n’ unexpanded, customize query-replace-show-replacement variable. Like search-highlight-submatches highlights subexpressions in incremental search (see Tailoring Search to Your Needs), the variable query-replace-highlight-submatches defines whether to highlight subexpressions in the regexp replacement commands.

The variable query-replace-skip-read-only, if set non-nil, will cause replacement commands to ignore matches in read-only text. The default is not to ignore them.

The characters you can type when you are shown a match for the string or regexp are:

SPC
y

to replace the occurrence with newstring.

DEL
Delete
BACKSPACE
n

to skip to the next occurrence without replacing this one.

, (Comma)

to replace this occurrence and display the result. You are then asked for another input character to say what to do next. Since the replacement has already been made, DEL and SPC are equivalent in this situation; both move to the next occurrence.

You can type C-r at this point (see below) to alter the replaced text. You can also undo the replacement with the undo command (e.g., type C-x u; see Undo); this exits the query-replace, so if you want to do further replacement you must use C-x ESC ESC RET to restart (see Repeating Minibuffer Commands).

RET
q

to exit without doing any more replacements.

. (Period)

to replace this occurrence and then exit without searching for more occurrences.

!

to replace all remaining occurrences without asking again.

^

to go back to the position of the previous occurrence (or what used to be an occurrence), in case you changed it by mistake or want to reexamine it.

u

to undo the last replacement and go back to where that replacement was made.

U

to undo all the replacements and go back to where the first replacement was made.

C-r

to enter a recursive editing level, in case the occurrence needs to be edited rather than just replaced with newstring. When you are done, exit the recursive editing level with C-M-c to proceed to the next occurrence. See Recursive Editing Levels.

C-w

to delete the occurrence, and then enter a recursive editing level as in C-r. Use the recursive edit to insert text to replace the deleted occurrence of string. When done, exit the recursive editing level with C-M-c to proceed to the next occurrence.

e

to edit the replacement string in the minibuffer. When you exit the minibuffer by typing RET, the minibuffer contents replace the current occurrence of the pattern. They also become the new replacement string for any further occurrences.

E

is like e, but the next replacement will be done with exact case. I.e., if you have a query-replace from ‘foo’ to ‘bar’, a text like ‘Foo’ will be normally be replaced with ‘Bar’. Use this command to do the current replacement with exact case.

C-l

to redisplay the screen. Then you must type another character to specify what to do with this occurrence.

Y (Upper-case)

to replace all remaining occurrences in all remaining buffers in multi-buffer replacements (like the Dired Q command that performs query replace on selected files). It answers this question and all subsequent questions in the series with “yes”, without further user interaction.

N (Upper-case)

to skip to the next buffer in multi-buffer replacements without replacing remaining occurrences in the current buffer. It answers this question “no”, gives up on the questions for the current buffer, and continues to the next buffer in the sequence.

C-h
?
F1

to display a message summarizing these options. Then you must type another character to specify what to do with this occurrence.

Aside from this, any other character exits the query-replace, and is then reread as part of a key sequence. Thus, if you type C-k, it exits the query-replace and then kills to end of line. In particular, C-g simply exits the query-replace.

To restart a query-replace once it is exited, use C-x ESC ESC, which repeats the query-replace because it used the minibuffer to read its arguments. See C-x ESC ESC.

The option search-invisible determines how query-replace treats invisible text. See Outline Search.

See Operating on Files, for the Dired Q command which performs query replace on selected files. See also Transforming File Names in Dired, for Dired commands to rename, copy, or link files by replacing regexp matches in file names.

16.11 Other Search-and-Loop Commands

Here are some other commands that find matches for regular expressions. They all ignore case in matching, if the pattern contains no upper-case letters and case-fold-search is non-nil. Aside from multi-occur and multi-occur-in-matching-buffers, which always search the whole buffer, all of the commands operate on the text from point to the end of the buffer, or on the region if it is active.

M-x multi-isearch-buffers

Prompt for one or more buffer names, ending with RET; then, begin a multi-buffer incremental search in those buffers. (If the search fails in one buffer, the next C-s tries searching the next specified buffer, and so forth.) With a prefix argument, prompt for a regexp and begin a multi-buffer incremental search in buffers matching that regexp.

M-x multi-isearch-buffers-regexp

This command is just like multi-isearch-buffers, except it performs an incremental regexp search.

M-x multi-isearch-files

Prompt for one or more file names, ending with RET; then, begin a multi-file incremental search in those files. (If the search fails in one file, the next C-s tries searching the next specified file, and so forth.) With a prefix argument, prompt for a regexp and begin a multi-file incremental search in files matching that regexp.

M-x multi-isearch-files-regexp

This command is just like multi-isearch-files, except it performs an incremental regexp search.

In some modes that set the buffer-local variable multi-isearch-next-buffer-function (e.g., in Change Log mode) a multi-file incremental search is activated automatically.

M-x occur
M-s o

Prompt for a regexp, and display a list showing each line in the buffer that contains a match for it. If you type M-n at the prompt, you can reuse search strings from previous incremental searches. The text that matched is highlighted using the match face. A numeric argument n specifies that n lines of context are to be displayed before and after each matching line.

The default number of context lines is specified by the variable list-matching-lines-default-context-lines. When list-matching-lines-jump-to-current-line is non-nil the current line is shown highlighted with face list-matching-lines-current-line-face and the point is set at the first match after such line.

You can also run M-s o when an incremental search is active; this uses the current search string.

Note that matches for the regexp you type are extended to include complete lines, and a match that starts before the previous match ends is not considered a match.

The *Occur* buffer uses the Occur mode as its major mode. You can use the n and p keys to move to the next or previous match; with prefix numeric argument, these commands move that many matches. Digit keys are bound to digit-argument, so 5 n moves to the fifth next match (you don’t have to type C-u). SPC and DEL scroll the *Occur* buffer up and down. Clicking on a match or moving point there and typing RET visits the corresponding position in the original buffer that was searched. o and C-o display the match in another window; C-o does not select that window. Alternatively, you can use the M-g M-n (next-error) command to visit the occurrences one by one (see Compilation Mode). Finally, q quits the window showing the *Occur* buffer and buries the buffer.

Typing e in the *Occur* buffer makes the buffer writable and enters the Occur Edit mode, in which you can edit the matching lines and have those edits reflected in the text in the originating buffer. Type C-c C-c to leave the Occur Edit mode and return to the Occur mode.

The command M-x list-matching-lines is a synonym for M-x occur.

M-x multi-occur

This command is just like occur, except it is able to search through multiple buffers. It asks you to specify the buffer names one by one.

M-x multi-occur-in-matching-buffers

This command is similar to multi-occur, except the buffers to search are specified by a regular expression that matches visited file names. With a prefix argument, it uses the regular expression to match buffer names instead.

M-x how-many

Prompt for a regexp, and print the number of matches for it in the buffer after point. If the region is active, this operates on the region instead.

M-x flush-lines

Prompt for a regexp, and delete each line that contains a match for it, operating on the text after point. When the command finishes, it prints the number of deleted matching lines.

This command deletes the current line if it contains a match starting after point. If the region is active, it operates on the region instead; if a line partially contained in the region contains a match entirely contained in the region, it is deleted.

If a match is split across lines, flush-lines deletes all those lines. It deletes the lines before starting to look for the next match; hence, it ignores a match starting on the same line at which another match ended.

M-x keep-lines

Prompt for a regexp, and delete each line that does not contain a match for it, operating on the text after point. If point is not at the beginning of a line, this command always keeps the current line. If the region is active, the command operates on the region instead; it never deletes lines that are only partially contained in the region (a newline that ends a line counts as part of that line).

If a match is split across lines, this command keeps all those lines.

M-x kill-matching-lines

Like flush-lines, but also add the matching lines to the kill ring. The command adds the matching lines to the kill ring as a single string, including the newlines that separated the lines.

M-x copy-matching-lines

Like kill-matching-lines, but the matching lines are not removed from the buffer.

16.12 Tailoring Search to Your Needs

This section describes miscellaneous search-related customizations not described elsewhere.

The default search mode for the incremental search is specified by the variable search-default-mode. It can be nil, t, or a function. If it is nil, the default mode is to do literal searches without character folding, but with case folding and lax-whitespace matches as determined by case-fold-search and search-whitespace-regexp, respectively (see Lax Matching During Searching). If the value is t, incremental search defaults to regexp searches. The default value specifies a function that only performs case folding and lax-whitespace matching.

The current match of an on-going incremental search is highlighted using the isearch face. This highlighting can be disabled by setting the variable search-highlight to nil.

When searching for regular expressions (with C-M-s, for instance), subexpressions receive special highlighting depending on the search-highlight-submatches variable. If this variable’s value is nil, no special highlighting is done, but if the value is non-nil, text that matches ‘\( … \)’ constructs (a.k.a. “subexpressions”) in the regular expression will be highlighted with distinct faces. By default, two distinct faces are defined, named isearch-group-1 and isearch-group-2. With these two faces, odd-numbered subexpressions will be highlighted using the isearch-group-1 face and even-numbered subexpressions will be highlighted using the isearch-group-2 face. For instance, when searching for ‘foo-\([0-9]+\)\([a-z]+\)’, the part matched by ‘[0-9]+’ will be highlighted with the isearch-group-1 face, and the part matched by ‘[a-z]+’ will be highlighted using isearch-group-2. If you define additional faces using the same numbering scheme, i.e. isearch-group-3, isearch-group-4, …, then the face isearch-group-M will be used to highlight the M’th, N+M’th, 2N+M’th, … subexpressions, where N is the total number of faces of the form isearch-group-M.

The other matches for the search string that are visible on display are highlighted using the lazy-highlight face. Setting the variable isearch-lazy-highlight to nil disables this highlighting. Here are some other variables that customize the lazy highlighting:

lazy-highlight-initial-delay

Time in seconds to wait before highlighting visible matches. Applies only if the search string is less than lazy-highlight-no-delay-length characters long.

lazy-highlight-no-delay-length

For search strings at least as long as the value of this variable, lazy highlighting of matches starts immediately.

lazy-highlight-interval

Time in seconds between highlighting successive matches.

lazy-highlight-max-at-a-time

The maximum number of matches to highlight before checking for input. A large number can take some time to highlight, so if you want to continue searching and type C-s or C-r during that time, Emacs will not respond until it finishes highlighting all those matches. Thus, smaller values make Emacs more responsive.

isearch-lazy-count

Show the current match number and the total number of matches in the search prompt.

lazy-count-prefix-format
lazy-count-suffix-format

These two variables determine the format of showing the current and the total number of matches for isearch-lazy-count.

Normally, entering RET within incremental search when the search string is empty launches a nonincremental search. (Actually, it lets you edit the search string, and the next RET does the search.) However, if you customize the variable search-nonincremental-instead to nil, typing RET will always exit the incremental search, even if the search string is empty.

By default, incremental search and query-replace commands match invisible text, but hide any such matches as soon as the current match moves off the invisible text. If you customize the variable isearch-hide-immediately to nil, any invisible text where matches were found stays on display until the search or the replace command exits.

Searching incrementally on slow terminals, such as displays connected to remote machines over slow connection, could be annoying due to the need to redraw large portions of the display as the search proceeds. Emacs provides a special display mode for slow terminals, whereby search pops up a separate small window and displays the text surrounding the match in that window. Small windows display faster, so the annoying effect of slow speed is alleviated. The variable search-slow-speed determines the baud rate threshold below which Emacs will use this display mode. The variable search-slow-window-lines controls the number of lines in the window Emacs pops up for displaying the search results; the default is 1 line. Normally, this window will pop up at the bottom of the window that displays the buffer where you start searching, but if the value of search-slow-window-lines is negative, that means to put the window at the top and give it the number of lines that is the absolute value of search-slow-window-lines.

33 Sending Mail

To send an email message from Emacs, type C-x m. This switches to a buffer named *unsent mail*, where you can edit the text and headers of the message. When done, type C-c C-s or C-c C-c to send it.

C-x m

Begin composing mail (compose-mail).

C-x 4 m

Likewise, in another window (compose-mail-other-window).

C-x 5 m

Likewise, but in a new frame (compose-mail-other-frame).

C-c C-s

In the mail buffer, send the message (message-send).

C-c C-c

In the mail buffer, send the message and bury the buffer (message-send-and-exit).

The mail buffer is an ordinary Emacs buffer, so you can switch to other buffers while composing the mail. If you want to send another message before finishing the current one, type C-x m again to open a new mail buffer whose name has a different numeric suffix (see Miscellaneous Buffer Operations). (This only works if you use the default Message mode to compose email; see Mail Commands.) If you know that you’d like to continue composing the unsent message you were editing, invoke this command with a prefix argument, C-u C-x m , and Emacs will switch to the last mail buffer you used and let you pick up editing the message where you left off.

The command C-x 4 m (compose-mail-other-window) does the same as C-x m, except it displays the mail buffer in a different window. The command C-x 5 m (compose-mail-other-frame) does it in a new frame.

When you type C-c C-c or C-c C-s to send the mail, Emacs may ask you how it should deliver the mail—either directly via SMTP, or using some other method. See Mail Sending, for details.

33.1 The Format of the Mail Buffer

Here is an example of the contents of a mail buffer:

To: subotai@example.org
CC: mongol.soldier@example.net, rms@gnu.org
Subject: Re: What is best in life?
From: conan@example.org
--text follows this line--
To crush your enemies, see them driven before you, and to
hear the lamentation of their women.

At the top of the mail buffer is a set of header fields, which are used for specifying information about the email’s recipient(s), subject, and so on. The above buffer contains header fields for ‘To’, ‘CC’, ‘Subject’, and ‘From’. Some header fields are automatically pre-initialized in the mail buffer, when appropriate.

The line that says ‘--text follows this line--’ separates the header fields from the body (or text) of the message. Everything above that line is treated as part of the headers; everything below it is treated as the body. The delimiter line itself does not appear in the message actually sent.

You can insert and edit header fields using ordinary editing commands. See Mail Header Editing, for commands specific to editing header fields. Certain headers, such as ‘Date’ and ‘Message-Id’, are normally omitted from the mail buffer and are created automatically when the message is sent.

33.2 Mail Header Fields

A header field in the mail buffer starts with a field name at the beginning of a line, terminated by a colon. Upper and lower case are equivalent in field names. After the colon and optional whitespace comes the contents of the field.

You can use any name you like for a header field, but normally people use only standard field names with accepted meanings.

The ‘From’ header field identifies the person sending the email (i.e., you). This should be a valid mailing address, as replies are normally sent there. The default contents of this header field are computed from the variables user-full-name (which specifies your full name) and user-mail-address (your email address). On some operating systems, Emacs initializes these two variables using environment variables (see General Variables). If this information is unavailable or wrong, you should customize the variables yourself (see Easy Customization Interface).

Apart from ‘From’, here is a table of commonly-used fields:

‘To’

The mailing address(es) to which the message is addressed. To list more than one address, use commas to separate them.

‘Subject’

The subject of the message.

‘CC’

Additional mailing address(es) to send the message to. This is like ‘To’, except that these readers should not regard the message as directed at them.

‘BCC’

Additional mailing address(es) to send the message to, which should not appear in the header of the message actually sent. ‘BCC’ stands for blind carbon copies.

‘FCC’

The name of a file, to which a copy of the sent message should be appended. Emacs writes the message in mbox format, unless the file is in Babyl format (used by Rmail before Emacs 23), in which case Emacs writes in Babyl format. If an Rmail buffer is visiting the file, Emacs updates it accordingly. To specify more than one file, use several ‘FCC’ fields, with one file name in each field.

‘Reply-To’

An address to which replies should be sent, instead of ‘From’. This is used if, for some reason, your ‘From’ address cannot receive replies.

‘Mail-Reply-To’

This field takes precedence over ‘Reply-To’. It is used because some mailing lists set the ‘Reply-To’ field for their own purposes (a somewhat controversial practice).

‘Mail-Followup-To’

One of more address(es) to use as default recipient(s) for follow-up messages. This is typically used when you reply to a message from a mailing list that you are subscribed to, and want replies to go to the list without sending an extra copy to you.

‘In-Reply-To’

An identifier for the message you are replying to. Most mail readers use this information to group related messages together. Normally, this header is filled in automatically when you reply to a message in any mail program built into Emacs.

‘References’

Identifiers for previous related messages. Like ‘In-Reply-To’, this is normally filled in automatically for you.

The ‘To’, ‘CC’, and ‘BCC’ fields can appear any number of times, and each such header field can contain multiple addresses, separated by commas. This way, you can specify any number of places to send the message. These fields can also have continuation lines: one or more lines starting with whitespace, following the starting line of the field, are considered part of the field. Here’s an example of a ‘To’ field with a continuation line:

To: foo@example.net, this@example.net,
  bob@example.com

You can direct Emacs to insert certain default headers into the mail buffer by setting the variable mail-default-headers to a string. Then C-x m inserts this string into the message headers. For example, here is how to add a ‘Reply-To’ and ‘FCC’ header to each message:

(setq mail-default-headers
      "Reply-To: foo@example.com\nFCC: ~/Mail/sent")

If the default header fields are not appropriate for a particular message, edit them as necessary before sending the message.

33.3 Mail Aliases

You can define mail aliases, which are short mnemonic names that stand for one or more mailing addresses. By default, mail aliases are defined in the file ~/.mailrc. You can specify a different file name to use, by setting the variable mail-personal-alias-file.

To define an alias in ~/.mailrc, write a line like this:

alias nick fulladdresses

This means that nick should expand into fulladdresses, where fulladdresses can be either a single address, or multiple addresses separated with spaces. For instance, to make maingnu stand for gnu@gnu.org plus a local address of your own, put in this line:

alias maingnu gnu@gnu.org local-gnu

If an address contains a space, quote the whole address with a pair of double quotes, like this:

alias jsmith "John Q. Smith <none@example.com>"

Note that you need not include double quotes around individual parts of the address, such as the person’s full name. Emacs puts them in if they are needed. For instance, it inserts the above address as ‘"John Q. Smith" <none@example.com>’.

After editing the ~/.mailrc file, or if the file was modified outside of Emacs, you can update the mail aliases used by a running Emacs session with M-x rebuild-mail-abbrevs RET . This prompts for the name of the file to use, the default being the value of mail-personal-alias-file. A similar command merge-mail-abbrevs prompts for a file with mail aliases, then merges the aliases in that file with the existing ones.

Alternatively, you can use Emacs commands to define mail aliases. The command define-mail-abbrev prompts for the alias and the full address, and defines the alias to expand to the full address. Emacs will save the added aliases whenever it offers to save all files (for C-x s or C-x C-c), like it does with other abbrevs (see Saving Abbrevs).

Emacs also recognizes include commands in ~/.mailrc. They look like this:

source filename

The ~/.mailrc file is not unique to Emacs; many other mail-reading programs use it for mail aliases, and it can contain various other commands. However, Emacs ignores everything except alias definitions and include commands.

Mail aliases expand as abbrevs—that is to say, as soon as you type a word-separator character after an alias (see Abbrevs). This expansion takes place only within the ‘To’, ‘From’, ‘CC’, ‘BCC’, and ‘Reply-To’ header fields (plus their ‘Resent-’ variants); it does not take place in other header fields, such as ‘Subject’.

You can also insert an aliased address directly, using the command M-x mail-abbrev-insert-alias. This reads an alias name, with completion, and inserts its definition at point.

The command mail-abbrev-complete-alias completes on the mail alias preceding point.

33.4 Mail Commands

The default major mode for the *mail* buffer is called Message mode. It behaves like Text mode in many ways, but provides several additional commands on the C-c prefix, which make editing a message more convenient.

In this section, we will describe some of the most commonly-used commands available in Message mode. Message mode also has its own manual, where its features are described in greater detail. See Message in

Message

.

33.4.1 Mail Sending

C-c C-c

Send the message, and bury the mail buffer (message-send-and-exit).

C-c C-s

Send the message, and leave the mail buffer selected (message-send).

The usual command to send a message is C-c C-c (message-send-and-exit). This sends the message and then buries the mail buffer, putting it at the lowest priority for reselection. If you want it to kill the mail buffer instead, change the variable message-kill-buffer-on-exit to t.

The command C-c C-s (message-send) sends the message and leaves the buffer selected. Use this command if you want to modify the message (perhaps with new recipients) and send it again.

Sending a message runs the hook message-send-hook. It also marks the mail buffer as unmodified, except if the mail buffer is also a file-visiting buffer (in that case, only saving the file does that, and you don’t get a warning if you try to send the same message twice).

The variable message-send-mail-function controls how the message is delivered (send-mail-function is used for Mail mode). The value of send-mail-function should be one of the following functions:

sendmail-query-once

Query for a delivery method (one of the other entries in this list), and use that method for this message; then save the method to send-mail-function, so that it is used for future deliveries. This is the default, unless you have already set the variables for sending mail via smtpmail-send-it (see below).

smtpmail-send-it

Send mail through an external mail host, such as your Internet service provider’s outgoing SMTP mail server. If you have not told Emacs how to contact the SMTP server, it prompts for this information, which is saved in the smtpmail-smtp-server variable and the file ~/.authinfo. See Emacs SMTP Library in

Sending mail via SMTP

.

sendmail-send-it

Send mail using the system’s default sendmail program, or equivalent. This requires the system to be set up for delivering mail directly via SMTP.

mailclient-send-it

Pass the mail buffer on to the system’s designated mail client. See the commentary section in the file mailclient.el for details.

feedmail-send-it

This is similar to sendmail-send-it, but allows you to queue messages for later sending. See the commentary section in the file feedmail.el for details.

When you send a message containing non-ASCII characters, they need to be encoded with a coding system (see Coding Systems). Usually the coding system is specified automatically by your chosen language environment (see Language Environments). You can explicitly specify the coding system for outgoing mail by setting the variable sendmail-coding-system (see Recognizing Coding Systems). If the coding system thus determined does not handle the characters in a particular message, Emacs asks you to select the coding system to use, showing a list of possible coding systems. See Choosing Coding Systems for Output.

33.4.2 Mail Header Editing

Message mode provides the following special commands to move to particular header fields and to complete addresses in headers.

C-c C-f C-t

Move to the ‘To’ header (message-goto-to).

C-c C-f C-s

Move to the ‘Subject’ header (message-goto-subject).

C-c C-f C-c

Move to the ‘CC’ header (message-goto-cc).

C-c C-f C-b

Move to the ‘BCC’ header (message-goto-bcc).

C-c C-f C-r

Move to the ‘Reply-To’ header (message-goto-reply-to).

C-c C-f C-f

Move to the ‘Mail-Followup-To’ header field (message-goto-followup-to).

C-c C-f C-w

Add a new ‘FCC’ header field, with file-name completion (message-goto-fcc).

C-c C-b

Move to the start of the message body (message-goto-body).

TAB

Complete a mailing address (message-tab).

The commands to move point to particular header fields are all based on the prefix C-c C-f (‘C-f’ is for “field”). If the field in question does not exist, the command creates one (the exception is mail-fcc, which creates a new field each time).

The command C-c C-b (message-goto-body) moves point to just after the header separator line—that is, to the beginning of the body.

While editing a header field that contains addresses, such as ‘To:’, ‘CC:’ and ‘BCC:’, you can complete an address by typing TAB (message-tab). This attempts to insert the full name corresponding to the address based on a couple of methods, including EUDC, a library that recognizes a number of directory server protocols (see EUDC in

The Emacs Unified Directory Client

). Failing that, it attempts to expand the address as a mail alias (see Mail Aliases). If point is on a header field that does not take addresses, or if it is in the message body, then TAB just inserts a tab character.

33.4.3 Citing Mail

C-c C-y

Yank the selected message from the mail reader, as a citation (message-yank-original).

C-c C-q

Fill each paragraph cited from another message (message-fill-yanked-message).

You can use the command C-c C-y (message-yank-original) to cite a message that you are replying to. This inserts the text of that message into the mail buffer. This command works only if the mail buffer is invoked from a mail reader running in Emacs, such as Rmail.

By default, Emacs inserts the string ‘>’ in front of each line of the cited text; this prefix string is specified by the variable message-yank-prefix. If you call message-yank-original with a prefix argument, the citation prefix is not inserted.

After using C-c C-y, you can type C-c C-q (message-fill-yanked-message) to fill the paragraphs of the cited message. One use of C-c C-q fills all such paragraphs, each one individually. To fill a single paragraph of the quoted message, use M-q. If filling does not automatically handle the type of citation prefix you use, try setting the fill prefix explicitly. See Filling Text.

You can customize mail citation through the hook mail-citation-hook. For example, you can use the Supercite package, which provides more flexible citation (see Introduction in

Supercite

).

33.4.4 Mail Miscellany

You can attach a file to an outgoing message by typing C-c C-a (mml-attach-file) in the mail buffer. Attaching is done using the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) standard.

The mml-attach-file command prompts for the name of the file, and for the attachment’s content type, description, and disposition. The content type is normally detected automatically; just type RET to accept the default. The description is a single line of text that the recipient will see next to the attachment; you may also choose to leave this empty. The disposition is either ‘inline’, which means the recipient will see a link to the attachment within the message body, or ‘attachment’, which means the link will be separate from the body.

The mml-attach-file command is specific to Message mode; in Mail mode use mail-add-attachment instead. It will prompt only for the name of the file, and will determine the content type and the disposition automatically. If you want to include some description of the attached file, type that in the message body.

The actual contents of the attached file are not inserted into the mail buffer. Instead, some placeholder text is inserted into the mail buffer, like this:

<#part type="text/plain" filename="~/foo.txt" disposition=inline>
<#/part>

When you type C-c C-c or C-c C-s to send the message, the attached file will be delivered with it.

While composing a message, you can do spelling correction on the message text by typing M-x ispell-message. If you have yanked an incoming message into the outgoing draft, this command skips what was yanked, but it checks the text that you yourself inserted (it looks for indentation or mail-yank-prefix to distinguish the cited lines from your input). See Checking and Correcting Spelling.

Turning on Message mode (which C-x m does automatically) runs the normal hooks text-mode-hook and message-mode-hook. Initializing a new outgoing message runs the normal hook message-setup-hook; you can use this hook if you want to make changes to the appearance of the mail buffer. See Hooks.

The main difference between these hooks is just when they are invoked. Whenever you type C-x m, message-mode-hook runs as soon as the mail buffer is created. Then the message-setup function inserts the default contents of the buffer. After these default contents are inserted, message-setup-hook runs.

If you use C-x m to continue an existing composition, message-mode-hook runs immediately after switching to the mail buffer. If the buffer is unmodified, or if you decide to erase it and start again, message-setup-hook runs after the default contents are inserted.

33.5 Mail Signature

You can add a standard piece of text—your mail signature—to the end of every message. This signature may contain information such as your telephone number or your physical location. The variable message-signature determines how Emacs handles the mail signature.

The default value of message-signature is t; this means to look for your mail signature in the file ~/.signature. If this file exists, its contents are automatically inserted into the end of the mail buffer. You can change the signature file via the variable message-signature-file.

If you change message-signature to a string, that specifies the text of the signature directly.

If you change message-signature to nil, Emacs will not insert your mail signature automatically. You can insert your mail signature by typing C-c C-w (message-insert-signature) in the mail buffer. Emacs will look for your signature in the signature file.

If you use Mail mode rather than Message mode for composing your mail, the corresponding variables that determine how your signature is sent are mail-signature and mail-signature-file instead.

By convention, a mail signature should be marked by a line whose contents are ‘-- ’. If your signature lacks this prefix, it is added for you. The remainder of your signature should be no more than four lines.

33.6 Mail Amusements

M-x spook adds a line of randomly chosen keywords to an outgoing mail message. The keywords are chosen from a list of words that suggest you are discussing something subversive.

The idea behind this feature is the suspicion that the NSA^18 and other intelligence agencies snoop on all electronic mail messages that contain keywords suggesting they might find them interesting. (The agencies say that they don’t, but that’s what they would say.) The idea is that if lots of people add suspicious words to their messages, the agencies will get so busy with spurious input that they will have to give up reading it all. Whether or not this is true, it at least amuses some people.

You can use the fortune program to put a fortune cookie message into outgoing mail. To do this, add fortune-to-signature to mail-setup-hook:

(add-hook 'mail-setup-hook 'fortune-to-signature)

You will probably need to set the variable fortune-file before using this.

33.7 Mail-Composition Methods

In this chapter we have described the usual Emacs mode for editing and sending mail—Message mode. This is only one of several available modes. Prior to Emacs 23.2, the default mode was Mail mode, which is similar to Message mode in many respects but lacks features such as MIME support. Another available mode is MH-E (see MH-E in

The Emacs Interface to MH

).

You can choose any of these mail user agents as your preferred method for editing and sending mail. The commands C-x m, C-x 4 m and C-x 5 m use whichever agent you have specified; so do various other parts of Emacs that send mail, such as the bug reporter (see Reporting Bugs). To specify a mail user agent, customize the variable mail-user-agent. Currently, legitimate values include message-user-agent (Message mode) sendmail-user-agent (Mail mode), gnus-user-agent, and mh-e-user-agent. Additional options may be available; check in the manual of your mail user agent package for details. You may also define another mail user agent using define-mail-user-agent.

If you select a different mail-composition method, the information in this chapter about the mail buffer and Message mode does not apply; the other methods use a different format of text in a different buffer, and their commands are different as well.

Similarly, to specify your preferred method for reading mail, customize the variable read-mail-command. The default is rmail (see Reading Mail with Rmail).

Footnotes

(18)

The US National Security Agency.

39 Running Shell Commands from Emacs

Emacs has commands for passing single command lines to shell subprocesses, and for running a shell interactively with input and output to an Emacs buffer, and for running a shell in a terminal emulator window.

M-! cmd RET

Run the shell command cmd and display the output (shell-command).

M-| cmd RET

Run the shell command cmd with region contents as input; optionally replace the region with the output (shell-command-on-region).

M-& cmd RET

Run the shell command cmd asynchronously, and display the output (async-shell-command).

M-x shell

Run a subshell with input and output through an Emacs buffer. You can then give commands interactively.

M-x term

Run a subshell with input and output through an Emacs buffer. You can then give commands interactively. Full terminal emulation is available.

Whenever you specify a relative file name for an executable program (either in the cmd argument to one of the above commands, or in other contexts), Emacs searches for the program in the directories specified by the variable exec-path. The value of this variable must be a list of directories; the default value is initialized from the environment variable PATH when Emacs is started (see General Variables).

M-x eshell invokes a shell implemented entirely in Emacs. It is documented in its own manual. See Eshell in

Eshell: The Emacs Shell

.

39.1 Single Shell Commands

M-! (shell-command) reads a line of text using the minibuffer and executes it as a shell command, in a subshell made just for that command. Standard input for the command comes from the null device. If the shell command produces any output, the output appears either in the echo area (if it is short), or in the ‘"*Shell Command Output*"’ (shell-command-buffer-name) buffer (if the output is long). The variables resize-mini-windows and max-mini-window-height (see Editing in the Minibuffer) control when Emacs should consider the output to be too long for the echo area. Note that customizing shell-command-dont-erase-buffer, described below, can affect what is displayed in the echo area.

For instance, one way to decompress a file named foo.gz is to type M-! gunzip foo.gz RET. That shell command normally creates the file foo and produces no terminal output.

A numeric argument to shell-command, e.g., M-1 M-!, causes it to insert terminal output into the current buffer instead of a separate buffer. By default, it puts point before the output, and sets the mark after the output (but a non-default value of shell-command-dont-erase-buffer can change that, see below). For instance, M-1 M-! gunzip < foo.gz RET would insert the uncompressed form of the file foo.gz into the current buffer.

Provided the specified shell command does not end with ‘&’, it runs synchronously, and you must wait for it to exit before continuing to use Emacs. To stop waiting, type C-g to quit; this sends a SIGINT signal to terminate the shell command (this is the same signal that C-c normally generates in the shell). Emacs then waits until the command actually terminates. If the shell command doesn’t stop (because it ignores the SIGINT signal), type C-g again; this sends the command a SIGKILL signal, which is impossible to ignore.

A shell command that ends in ‘&’ is executed asynchronously, and you can continue to use Emacs as it runs. You can also type M-& (async-shell-command) to execute a shell command asynchronously; this is exactly like calling M-! with a trailing ‘&’, except that you do not need the ‘&’. The output from asynchronous shell commands, by default, goes into the ‘"*Async Shell Command*"’ buffer (shell-command-buffer-name-async). Emacs inserts the output into this buffer as it comes in, whether or not the buffer is visible in a window.

If you want to run more than one asynchronous shell command at the same time, they could end up competing for the output buffer. The option async-shell-command-buffer specifies what to do about this; e.g., whether to rename the pre-existing output buffer, or to use a different buffer for the new command. Consult the variable’s documentation for more possibilities.

If you want the output buffer for asynchronous shell commands to be displayed only when the command generates output, set async-shell-command-display-buffer to nil.

The option async-shell-command-width defines the number of display columns available for output of asynchronous shell commands. A positive integer tells the shell to use that number of columns for command output. The default value is nil that means to use the same number of columns as provided by the shell.

To make the above commands show the current directory in their prompts, customize the variable shell-command-prompt-show-cwd to a non-nil value.

M-| (shell-command-on-region) is like M-!, but passes the contents of the region as the standard input to the shell command, instead of no input. With a numeric argument, it deletes the old region and replaces it with the output from the shell command.

For example, you can use M-| with the gpg program to see what keys are in the buffer. If the buffer contains a GnuPG key, type C-x h M-| gpg RET to feed the entire buffer contents to gpg. This will output the list of keys to the buffer whose name is the value of shell-command-buffer-name.

The above commands use the shell specified by the variable shell-file-name. Its default value is determined by the SHELL environment variable when Emacs is started. If the file name is relative, Emacs searches the directories listed in exec-path (see Running Shell Commands from Emacs).

If the default directory is remote (see Remote Files), the default value is /bin/sh. This can be changed by declaring shell-file-name connection-local (see Per-Connection Local Variables).

To specify a coding system for M-! or M-|, use the command C-x RET c immediately beforehand. See Coding Systems for Interprocess Communication.

By default, error output is intermixed with the regular output in the output buffer. But if you change the value of the variable shell-command-default-error-buffer to a string, error output is inserted into a buffer of that name.

By default, the output buffer is erased between shell commands, except when the output goes to the current buffer. If you change the value of the option shell-command-dont-erase-buffer to erase, then the output buffer is always erased. Other non-nil values prevent erasing of the output buffer, and—if the output buffer is not the current buffer—also control where to put point after inserting the output of the shell command:

beg-last-out

Puts point at the beginning of the last shell-command output.

end-last-out

Puts point at the end of the last shell-command output, i.e. at the end of the output buffer.

save-point

Restores the position of point as it was before inserting the shell-command output.

Note that if this option is non-nil, the output shown in the echo area could be from more than just the last command, since the echo area just displays a portion of the output buffer.

In case the output buffer is not the current buffer, shell command output is appended at the end of this buffer.

39.2 Interactive Subshell

To run a subshell interactively, type M-x shell. This creates (or reuses) a buffer named *shell*, and runs a shell subprocess with input coming from and output going to that buffer. That is to say, any terminal output from the subshell goes into the buffer, advancing point, and any terminal input for the subshell comes from text in the buffer. To give input to the subshell, go to the end of the buffer and type the input, terminated by RET.

By default, when the subshell is invoked interactively, the *shell* buffer is displayed in a new window, unless the current window already shows the *shell* buffer. This behavior can be customized via display-buffer-alist (see How display-buffer works).

While the subshell is waiting or running a command, you can switch windows or buffers and perform other editing in Emacs. Emacs inserts the output from the subshell into the Shell buffer whenever it has time to process it (e.g., while waiting for keyboard input).

In the Shell buffer, prompts are displayed with the face comint-highlight-prompt, and submitted input lines are displayed with the face comint-highlight-input. This makes it easier to distinguish input lines from the shell output. See Text Faces.

To make multiple subshells, invoke M-x shell with a prefix argument (e.g., C-u M-x shell). Then the command will read a buffer name, and create (or reuse) a subshell in that buffer. You can also rename the *shell* buffer using M-x rename-uniquely, then create a new *shell* buffer using plain M-x shell. Subshells in different buffers run independently and in parallel.

Emacs attempts to keep track of what the current directory is by looking at the commands you enter, looking for ‘cd’ commands and the like. This is an error-prone solution, since there are many ways to change the current directory, so Emacs also looks for special OSC (Operating System Commands) escape codes that are designed to convey this information in a more reliable fashion. You should arrange for your shell to print the appropriate escape sequence at each prompt, for instance with the following command:

printf "\e]7;file://%s%s\e\\" "$HOSTNAME" "$PWD"

To specify the shell file name used by M-x shell, customize the variable explicit-shell-file-name. If this is nil (the default), Emacs uses the environment variable ESHELL if it exists. Otherwise, it usually uses the variable shell-file-name (see Single Shell Commands); but if the default directory is remote (see Remote Files), it prompts you for the shell file name. See Minibuffers for File Names, for hints how to type remote file names effectively.

Emacs sends the new shell the contents of the file ~/.emacs_shellname as input, if it exists, where shellname is the name of the file that the shell was loaded from. For example, if you use bash, the file sent to it is ~/.emacs_bash. If this file is not found, Emacs tries with ~/.emacs.d/init_shellname.sh.

To specify a coding system for the shell, you can use the command C-x RET c immediately before M-x shell. You can also change the coding system for a running subshell by typing C-x RET p in the shell buffer. See Coding Systems for Interprocess Communication.

Emacs sets the environment variable INSIDE_EMACS in the subshell to ‘version,comint’, where version is the Emacs version (e.g., ‘28.1’). Programs can check this variable to determine whether they are running inside an Emacs subshell.

39.3 Shell Mode

The major mode for Shell buffers is Shell mode. Many of its special commands are bound to the C-c prefix, and resemble the usual editing and job control characters present in ordinary shells, except that you must type C-c first. Here is a list of Shell mode commands:

RET

Send the current line as input to the subshell (comint-send-input). Any shell prompt at the beginning of the line is omitted (see Shell Prompts). If point is at the end of buffer, this is like submitting the command line in an ordinary interactive shell. However, you can also invoke RET elsewhere in the shell buffer to submit the current line as input.

TAB

Complete the command name or file name before point in the shell buffer (completion-at-point). This uses the usual Emacs completion rules (see Completion), with the completion alternatives being file names, environment variable names, the shell command history, and history references (see Shell History References). For options controlling the completion, see Shell Mode Options.

M-?

Display temporarily a list of the possible completions of the file name before point (comint-dynamic-list-filename-completions).

C-d

Either delete a character or send EOF (comint-delchar-or-maybe-eof). Typed at the end of the shell buffer, this sends EOF to the subshell. Typed at any other position in the buffer, this deletes a character as usual.

C-c C-a

Move to the beginning of the line, but after the prompt if any (comint-bol-or-process-mark). If you repeat this command twice in a row, the second time it moves back to the process mark, which is the beginning of the input that you have not yet sent to the subshell. (Normally that is the same place—the end of the prompt on this line—but after C-c SPC the process mark may be in a previous line.)

C-c SPC

Accumulate multiple lines of input, then send them together (comint-accumulate). This command inserts a newline before point, but does not send the preceding text as input to the subshell—at least, not yet. Both lines, the one before this newline and the one after, will be sent together (along with the newline that separates them), when you type RET.

C-c C-u

Kill all text pending at end of buffer to be sent as input (comint-kill-input). If point is not at end of buffer, this only kills the part of this text that precedes point.

C-c C-w

Kill a word before point (backward-kill-word).

C-c C-c

Interrupt the shell or its current subjob if any (comint-interrupt-subjob). This command also kills any shell input pending in the shell buffer and not yet sent.

C-c C-z

Stop the shell or its current subjob if any (comint-stop-subjob). This command also kills any shell input pending in the shell buffer and not yet sent.

C-c C-\

Send quit signal to the shell or its current subjob if any (comint-quit-subjob). This command also kills any shell input pending in the shell buffer and not yet sent.

C-c C-o

Delete the last batch of output from a shell command (comint-delete-output). This is useful if a shell command spews out lots of output that just gets in the way. With a prefix argument, this command saves the deleted text in the kill-ring (see The Kill Ring), so that you could later yank it (see Yanking) elsewhere.

C-c C-s

Write the last batch of output from a shell command to a file (comint-write-output). With a prefix argument, the file is appended to instead. Any prompt at the end of the output is not written.

C-c C-r
C-M-l

Scroll to display the beginning of the last batch of output at the top of the window; also move the cursor there (comint-show-output).

C-c C-e

Scroll to put the last line of the buffer at the bottom of the window (comint-show-maximum-output).

C-c C-f

Move forward across one shell command, but not beyond the current line (shell-forward-command). The variable shell-command-regexp specifies how to recognize the end of a command.

C-c C-b

Move backward across one shell command, but not beyond the current line (shell-backward-command).

M-x dirs

Ask the shell for its working directory, and update the Shell buffer’s default directory. See Directory Tracking.

M-x comint-send-invisible RET text RET

Send text as input to the shell, after reading it without echoing. This is useful when a shell command runs a program that asks for a password.

Please note that Emacs will not echo passwords by default. If you really want them to be echoed, evaluate (see Evaluating Emacs Lisp Expressions) the following Lisp expression:

(remove-hook 'comint-output-filter-functions
             'comint-watch-for-password-prompt)

M-x comint-continue-subjob

Continue the shell process. This is useful if you accidentally suspend the shell process.^21

M-x comint-strip-ctrl-m

Discard all control-M characters from the current group of shell output. The most convenient way to use this command is to make it run automatically when you get output from the subshell. To do that, evaluate this Lisp expression:

(add-hook 'comint-output-filter-functions
          'comint-strip-ctrl-m)

M-x comint-truncate-buffer

This command truncates the shell buffer to a certain maximum number of lines, specified by the variable comint-buffer-maximum-size. Here’s how to do this automatically each time you get output from the subshell:

(add-hook 'comint-output-filter-functions
          'comint-truncate-buffer)

By default, Shell mode handles common ANSI escape codes (for instance, for changing the color of text). Emacs also optionally supports some extend escape codes, like some of the OSC (Operating System Codes) if you put the following in your init file:

(add-hook 'comint-output-filter-functions 'comint-osc-process-output)

With this enabled, the output from, for instance, ls --hyperlink will be made into clickable buttons in the Shell mode buffer.

Shell mode is a derivative of Comint mode, a general-purpose mode for communicating with interactive subprocesses. Most of the features of Shell mode actually come from Comint mode, as you can see from the command names listed above. The special features of Shell mode include the directory tracking feature, and a few user commands.

Other Emacs features that use variants of Comint mode include GUD (see Running Debuggers Under Emacs) and M-x run-lisp (see Running an External Lisp).

You can use M-x comint-run to execute any program of your choice in a subprocess using unmodified Comint mode—without the specializations of Shell mode. To pass arguments to the program, use C-u M-x comint-run.

39.4 Shell Prompts

A prompt is text output by a program to show that it is ready to accept new user input. Normally, Comint mode (and thus Shell mode) automatically figures out which part of the buffer is a prompt, based on the output of the subprocess. (Specifically, it assumes that any received output line which doesn’t end with a newline is a prompt.)

Comint mode divides the buffer into two types of fields: input fields (where user input is typed) and output fields (everywhere else). Prompts are part of the output fields. Most Emacs motion commands do not cross field boundaries, unless they move over multiple lines. For instance, when point is in the input field on a shell command line, C-a puts point at the beginning of the input field, after the prompt. Internally, the fields are implemented using the field text property (see Text Properties in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

If you change the variable comint-use-prompt-regexp to a non-nil value, then Comint mode will recognize prompts using a regular expression (see Syntax of Regular Expressions). In Shell mode, the regular expression is specified by the variable shell-prompt-pattern. The default value of comint-use-prompt-regexp is nil, because this method for recognizing prompts is unreliable, but you may want to set it to a non-nil value in unusual circumstances. In that case, Emacs does not divide the Comint buffer into fields, so the general motion commands behave as they normally do in buffers without special text properties. However, you can use the paragraph motion commands to conveniently navigate the buffer (see Paragraphs); in Shell mode, Emacs uses shell-prompt-pattern as paragraph boundaries.

39.5 Shell Command History

Shell buffers support three ways of repeating earlier commands. You can use keys like those used for the minibuffer history; these work much as they do in the minibuffer, inserting text from prior commands while point remains always at the end of the buffer. You can move through the buffer to previous inputs in their original place, then resubmit them or copy them to the end. Or you can use a ‘!’-style history reference.

39.5.1 Shell History Ring

M-p
C-UP

Fetch the next earlier old shell command (comint-previous-input).

M-n
C-DOWN

Fetch the next later old shell command (comint-next-input).

M-r

Begin an incremental regexp search of old shell commands (comint-history-isearch-backward-regexp).

C-c C-x

Fetch the next subsequent command from the history (comint-get-next-from-history).

C-c .

Fetch one argument from an old shell command (comint-input-previous-argument).

C-c C-l

Display the buffer’s history of shell commands in another window (comint-dynamic-list-input-ring).

Shell buffers provide a history of previously entered shell commands. To reuse shell commands from the history, use the editing commands M-p, M-n, and M-r. These work similar to the minibuffer history commands (see Minibuffer History), except that they operate within the Shell buffer rather than the minibuffer, and M-r in a Shell buffer invokes incremental search through shell command history.

M-p fetches an earlier shell command to the end of the shell buffer. Successive use of M-p fetches successively earlier shell commands, each replacing any text that was already present as potential shell input. M-n does likewise except that it finds successively more recent shell commands from the buffer. C-UP works like M-p, and C-DOWN like M-n.

The history search command M-r begins an incremental regular expression search of previous shell commands. After typing M-r, start typing the desired string or regular expression; the last matching shell command will be displayed in the current line. Incremental search commands have their usual effects—for instance, C-s and C-r search forward and backward for the next match (see Incremental Search). When you find the desired input, type RET to terminate the search. This puts the input in the command line. Any partial input you were composing before navigating the history list is restored when you go to the beginning or end of the history ring.

Often it is useful to reexecute several successive shell commands that were previously executed in sequence. To do this, first find and reexecute the first command of the sequence. Then type C-c C-x; that will fetch the following command—the one that follows the command you just repeated. Then type RET to reexecute this command. You can reexecute several successive commands by typing C-c C-x RET over and over.

The command C-c . (comint-insert-previous-argument) copies an individual argument from a previous command, like ESC . in Bash and zsh. The simplest use copies the last argument from the previous shell command. With a prefix argument n, it copies the nth argument instead. Repeating C-c . copies from an earlier shell commands, always using the same value of n (don’t give a prefix argument when you repeat the C-c . command).

If you set comint-insert-previous-argument-from-end to a non-nil value, C-c . will instead copy the nth argument counting from the last one; this emulates ESC . in zsh.

These commands get the text of previous shell commands from a special history list, not from the shell buffer itself. Thus, editing the shell buffer, or even killing large parts of it, does not affect the history that these commands access.

Some shells store their command histories in files so that you can refer to commands from previous shell sessions. Emacs reads the command history file for your chosen shell, to initialize its own command history. The file name is ~/.bash_history for bash, ~/.sh_history for ksh, and ~/.history for other shells.

If you run the shell on a remote host, this setting might be overwritten by the variable tramp-histfile-override. It is recommended to set this variable to nil.

39.5.2 Shell History Copying

C-c C-p

Move point to the previous prompt (comint-previous-prompt).

C-c C-n

Move point to the following prompt (comint-next-prompt).

C-c RET

Copy the input command at point, inserting the copy at the end of the buffer (comint-copy-old-input). This is useful if you move point back to a previous command. After you copy the command, you can submit the copy as input with RET. If you wish, you can edit the copy before resubmitting it. If you use this command on an output line, it copies that line to the end of the buffer.

mouse-2

If comint-use-prompt-regexp is nil (the default), copy the old input command that you click on, inserting the copy at the end of the buffer (comint-insert-input). If comint-use-prompt-regexp is non-nil, or if the click is not over old input, just yank as usual.

Moving to a previous input and then copying it with C-c RET or mouse-2 produces the same results—the same buffer contents—that you would get by using M-p enough times to fetch that previous input from the history list. However, C-c RET copies the text from the buffer, which can be different from what is in the history list if you edit the input text in the buffer after it has been sent.

39.5.3 Shell History References

Various shells, including csh and bash, support history references that begin with ‘!’ and ‘^’. Shell mode recognizes these constructs, and can perform the history substitution for you.

If you insert a history reference and type TAB, this searches the input history for a matching command, performs substitution if necessary, and places the result in the buffer in place of the history reference. For example, you can fetch the most recent command beginning with ‘mv’ with ! m v TAB. You can edit the command if you wish, and then resubmit the command to the shell by typing RET.

Shell mode can optionally expand history references in the buffer when you send them to the shell. To request this, set the variable comint-input-autoexpand to input. You can make SPC perform history expansion by binding SPC to the command comint-magic-space. See Changing Key Bindings Interactively.

Shell mode recognizes history references when they follow a prompt. See Shell Prompts, for how Shell mode recognizes prompts.

39.6 Directory Tracking

Shell mode keeps track of ‘cd’, ‘pushd’ and ‘popd’ commands given to the subshell, in order to keep the Shell buffer’s default directory (see File Names) the same as the shell’s working directory. It recognizes these commands by examining lines of input that you send.

If you use aliases for these commands, you can tell Emacs to recognize them also, by setting the variables shell-pushd-regexp, shell-popd-regexp, and shell-cd-regexp to the appropriate regular expressions (see Syntax of Regular Expressions). For example, if shell-pushd-regexp matches the beginning of a shell command line, that line is regarded as a pushd command. These commands are recognized only at the beginning of a shell command line.

If Emacs gets confused about changes in the working directory of the subshell, type M-x dirs. This command asks the shell for its working directory and updates the default directory accordingly. It works for shells that support the most common command syntax, but may not work for unusual shells.

You can also use Dirtrack mode, a buffer-local minor mode that implements an alternative method of tracking the shell’s working directory. To use this method, your shell prompt must contain the working directory at all times, and you must supply a regular expression for recognizing which part of the prompt contains the working directory; see the documentation of the variable dirtrack-list for details. To use Dirtrack mode, type M-x dirtrack-mode in the Shell buffer, or add dirtrack-mode to shell-mode-hook (see Hooks).

39.7 Shell Mode Options

If the variable comint-scroll-to-bottom-on-input is non-nil, insertion and yank commands scroll the selected window to the bottom before inserting. The default is nil.

If comint-scroll-show-maximum-output is non-nil, then arrival of output when point is at the end tries to scroll the last line of text to the bottom line of the window, showing as much useful text as possible. (This mimics the scrolling behavior of most terminals.) The default is t.

By setting comint-move-point-for-output, you can opt for having point jump to the end of the buffer whenever output arrives—no matter where in the buffer point was before. If the value is this, point jumps in the selected window. If the value is all, point jumps in each window that shows the Comint buffer. If the value is other, point jumps in all nonselected windows that show the current buffer. The default value is nil, which means point does not jump to the end.

If you set comint-prompt-read-only, the prompts in the Comint buffer are read-only.

The variable comint-input-ignoredups controls whether successive identical inputs are stored in the input history. A non-nil value means to omit an input that is the same as the previous input. The default is nil, which means to store each input even if it is equal to the previous input.

Three variables customize file name completion. The variable comint-completion-addsuffix controls whether completion inserts a space or a slash to indicate a fully completed file or directory name (non-nil means do insert a space or slash). comint-completion-recexact, if non-nil, directs TAB to choose the shortest possible completion if the usual Emacs completion algorithm cannot add even a single character. comint-completion-autolist, if non-nil, says to list all the possible completions whenever completion is not exact.

Command completion normally considers only executable files. If you set shell-completion-execonly to nil, it considers nonexecutable files as well.

The variable shell-completion-fignore specifies a list of file name extensions to ignore in Shell mode completion. The default setting is nil, but some users prefer ("~" "#" "%") to ignore file names ending in ‘~’, ‘#’ or ‘%’. Other related Comint modes use the variable comint-completion-fignore instead.

Some implementation details of the shell command completion may also be found in the lisp documentation of the shell-dynamic-complete-command function.

You can configure the behavior of ‘pushd’. Variables control whether ‘pushd’ behaves like ‘cd’ if no argument is given (shell-pushd-tohome), pop rather than rotate with a numeric argument (shell-pushd-dextract), and only add directories to the directory stack if they are not already on it (shell-pushd-dunique). The values you choose should match the underlying shell, of course.

Comint mode sets the TERM environment variable to a safe default value, but this value disables some useful features. For example, color is disabled in applications that use TERM to determine if color is supported. Therefore, Emacs provides an option comint-terminfo-terminal to let you choose a terminal with more advanced features, as defined in your system’s terminfo database. Emacs will use this option as the value for TERM so long as system-uses-terminfo is non-nil.

Both comint-terminfo-terminal and system-uses-terminfo can be declared as connection-local variables to adjust these options to match what a remote system expects (see Per-Connection Local Variables).

39.8 Emacs Terminal Emulator

To run a subshell in a text terminal emulator, use M-x term. This creates (or reuses) a buffer named *terminal*, and runs a subshell with input coming from your keyboard, and output going to that buffer.

The terminal emulator uses Term mode, which has two input modes. In line mode, Term basically acts like Shell mode (see Shell Mode). In char mode, each character is sent directly to the subshell, as terminal input; the sole exception is the terminal escape character, which by default is C-c (see Term Mode). Any echoing of your input is the responsibility of the subshell; any terminal output from the subshell goes into the buffer, advancing point.

Some programs (such as Emacs itself) need to control the appearance of the terminal screen in detail. They do this by emitting special control codes. Term mode recognizes and handles ANSI-standard VT100-style escape sequences, which are accepted by most modern terminals, including xterm. (Hence, you can actually run Emacs inside an Emacs Term window.)

The term face specifies the default appearance of text in the terminal emulator (the default is the same appearance as the default face). When terminal control codes are used to change the appearance of text, these are represented in the terminal emulator by the faces term-color-black, term-color-red, term-color-green, term-color-yellow term-color-blue, term-color-magenta, term-color-cyan, term-color-white, term-color-underline, and term-color-bold. See Text Faces.

You can also use Term mode to communicate with a device connected to a serial port. See Serial Terminal.

The file name used to load the subshell is determined the same way as for Shell mode. To make multiple terminal emulators, rename the buffer *terminal* to something different using M-x rename-uniquely, just as with Shell mode.

Unlike Shell mode, Term mode does not track the current directory by examining your input. But some shells can tell Term what the current directory is. This is done automatically by bash version 1.15 and later.

39.9 Term Mode

To switch between line and char mode in Term mode, use these commands:

C-c C-j

Switch to line mode (term-line-mode). Do nothing if already in line mode.

C-c C-k

Switch to char mode (term-char-mode). Do nothing if already in char mode.

The following commands are only available in char mode:

C-c C-c

Send a literal C-c to the sub-shell (term-interrupt-subjob).

C-c char

This is equivalent to C-x char in normal Emacs. For example, C-c o invokes the global binding of C-x o, which is normally ‘other-window’.

Term mode has a page-at-a-time feature. When enabled, it makes output pause at the end of each screenful:

C-c C-q

Toggle the page-at-a-time feature (term-pager-toggle). This command works in both line and char modes. When the feature is enabled, the mode-line displays the word ‘page’, and each time Term receives more than a screenful of output, it pauses and displays ‘**MORE**’ in the mode-line. Type SPC to display the next screenful of output, or ? to see your other options. The interface is similar to the more program.

39.10 Remote Host Shell

You can login to a remote computer, using whatever commands you would from a regular terminal (e.g., the ssh command), from a Term window.

A program that asks you for a password will normally suppress echoing of the password, so the password will not show up in the buffer. This will happen just as if you were using a real terminal, if the buffer is in char mode. If it is in line mode, the password is temporarily visible, but will be erased when you hit return. (This happens automatically; there is no special password processing.)

When you log in to a different machine, you need to specify the type of terminal you’re using, by setting the TERM environment variable in the environment for the remote login command. (If you use bash, you do that by writing the variable assignment before the remote login command, without a separating comma.) Terminal types ‘ansi’ or ‘vt100’ will work on most systems.

39.11 Serial Terminal

If you have a device connected to a serial port of your computer, you can communicate with it by typing M-x serial-term. This command asks for a serial port name and speed, and switches to a new Term mode buffer. Emacs communicates with the serial device through this buffer just like it does with a terminal in ordinary Term mode.

The speed of the serial port is measured in bits per second. The most common speed is 9600 bits per second. You can change the speed interactively by clicking on the mode line.

A serial port can be configured even more by clicking on ‘8N1’ in the mode line. By default, a serial port is configured as ‘8N1’, which means that each byte consists of 8 data bits, No parity check bit, and 1 stopbit.

If the speed or the configuration is wrong, you cannot communicate with your device and will probably only see garbage output in the window.

Footnotes

(21)

You should not suspend the shell process. Suspending a subjob of the shell is a completely different matter—that is normal practice, but you must use the shell to continue the subjob; this command won’t do it.

42 Sorting Text

Emacs provides several commands for sorting text in the buffer. All operate on the contents of the region. They divide the text of the region into many sort records, identify a sort key for each record, and then reorder the records into the order determined by the sort keys. The records are ordered so that their keys are in alphabetical order, or, for numeric sorting, in numeric order. In alphabetic sorting, all upper-case letters ‘A’ through ‘Z’ come before lower-case ‘a’, in accordance with the ASCII character sequence (but sort-fold-case, described below, can change that).

The various sort commands differ in how they divide the text into sort records and in which part of each record is used as the sort key. Most of the commands make each line a separate sort record, but some commands use paragraphs or pages as sort records. Most of the sort commands use each entire sort record as its own sort key, but some use only a portion of the record as the sort key.

M-x sort-lines

Divide the region into lines, and sort by comparing the entire text of a line. A numeric argument means sort into descending order.

M-x sort-paragraphs

Divide the region into paragraphs, and sort by comparing the entire text of a paragraph (except for leading blank lines). A numeric argument means sort into descending order.

M-x sort-pages

Divide the region into pages, and sort by comparing the entire text of a page (except for leading blank lines). A numeric argument means sort into descending order.

M-x sort-fields

Divide the region into lines, and sort by comparing the contents of one field in each line. Fields are defined as separated by whitespace, so the first run of consecutive non-whitespace characters in a line constitutes field 1, the second such run constitutes field 2, etc.

Specify which field to sort by with a numeric argument: 1 to sort by field 1, etc.; the default is 1. A negative argument means count fields from the right instead of from the left; thus, minus 1 means sort by the last field. If several lines have identical contents in the field being sorted, they keep the same relative order that they had in the original buffer.

M-x sort-numeric-fields

Like M-x sort-fields except the specified field is converted to an integer for each line, and the numbers are compared. ‘10’ comes before ‘2’ when considered as text, but after it when considered as a number. By default, numbers are interpreted according to sort-numeric-base, but numbers beginning with ‘0x’ or ‘0’ are interpreted as hexadecimal and octal, respectively.

M-x sort-columns

Like M-x sort-fields except that the text within each line used for comparison comes from a fixed range of columns. With a prefix argument, sort in reverse order. See below for more details on this command.

M-x reverse-region

Reverse the order of the lines in the region. This is useful for sorting into descending order by fields, since those sort commands do not have a feature for doing that.

For example, if the buffer contains this:

On systems where clash detection (locking of files being edited) is
implemented, Emacs also checks the first time you modify a buffer
whether the file has changed on disk since it was last visited or
saved.  If it has, you are asked to confirm that you want to change
the buffer.

applying M-x sort-lines to the entire buffer produces this:

On systems where clash detection (locking of files being edited) is
implemented, Emacs also checks the first time you modify a buffer
saved.  If it has, you are asked to confirm that you want to change
the buffer.
whether the file has changed on disk since it was last visited or

where the upper-case ‘O’ sorts before all lower-case letters. If you use C-u 2 M-x sort-fields instead, you get this:

implemented, Emacs also checks the first time you modify a buffer
saved.  If it has, you are asked to confirm that you want to change
the buffer.
On systems where clash detection (locking of files being edited) is
whether the file has changed on disk since it was last visited or

where the sort keys were ‘Emacs’, ‘If’, ‘buffer’, ‘systems’ and ‘the’.

M-x sort-columns requires more explanation. You specify the columns by putting point at one of the columns and the mark at the other column. Because this means you cannot put point or the mark at the beginning of the first line of the text you want to sort, this command uses an unusual definition of “region”: all of the line point is in is considered part of the region, and so is all of the line the mark is in, as well as all the lines in between.

For example, to sort a table by information found in columns 10 to 15, you could put the mark on column 10 in the first line of the table, and point on column 15 in the last line of the table, and then run sort-columns. Equivalently, you could run it with the mark on column 15 in the first line and point on column 10 in the last line.

This can be thought of as sorting the rectangle specified by point and the mark, except that the text on each line to the left or right of the rectangle moves along with the text inside the rectangle. See Rectangles.

Many of the sort commands ignore case differences when comparing, if sort-fold-case is non-nil.

26 Commands for Human Languages

This chapter describes Emacs commands that act on text, by which we mean sequences of characters in a human language (as opposed to, say, a computer programming language). These commands act in ways that take into account the syntactic and stylistic conventions of human languages: conventions involving words, sentences, paragraphs, and capital letters. There are also commands for filling, which means rearranging the lines of a paragraph to be approximately equal in length. These commands, while intended primarily for editing text, are also often useful for editing programs.

Emacs has several major modes for editing human-language text. If the file contains ordinary text, use Text mode, which customizes Emacs in small ways for the syntactic conventions of text. Outline mode provides special commands for operating on text with an outline structure. See Outline Mode.

Org mode extends Outline mode and turns Emacs into a full-fledged organizer: you can manage TODO lists, store notes and publish them in many formats. See the Org Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs.

Emacs has other major modes for text which contains embedded commands, such as TeX and LaTeX (see TeX Mode); HTML and SGML (see SGML and HTML Modes); XML (see the nXML mode Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs); and Groff and Nroff (see Nroff Mode).

If you need to edit ASCII art pictures made out of text characters, use Picture mode, a special major mode for editing such pictures. See Editing Pictures.

26.1 Words

Emacs defines several commands for moving over or operating on words:

M-f

Move forward over a word (forward-word).

M-b

Move backward over a word (backward-word).

M-d

Kill up to the end of a word (kill-word).

M-DEL

Kill back to the beginning of a word (backward-kill-word).

M-@

Set mark at the end of the next word (mark-word).

M-t

Transpose two words or drag a word across others (transpose-words).

Notice how these keys form a series that parallels the character-based C-f, C-b, C-d, DEL and C-t. M-@ is cognate to C-@, which is an alias for C-SPC.

The commands M-f (forward-word) and M-b (backward-word) move forward and backward over words. These Meta-based key sequences are analogous to the key sequences C-f and C-b, which move over single characters. The analogy extends to numeric arguments, which serve as repeat counts. M-f with a negative argument moves backward, and M-b with a negative argument moves forward. Forward motion stops right after the last letter of the word, while backward motion stops right before the first letter.

M-d (kill-word) kills the word after point. To be precise, it kills everything from point to the place M-f would move to. Thus, if point is in the middle of a word, M-d kills just the part after point. If some punctuation comes between point and the next word, it is killed along with the word. (If you wish to kill only the next word but not the punctuation before it, simply do M-f to get the end, and kill the word backwards with M-DEL.) M-d takes arguments just like M-f.

M-DEL (backward-kill-word) kills the word before point. It kills everything from point back to where M-b would move to. For instance, if point is after the space in ‘FOO, BAR’ , it kills ‘FOO, ’ . If you wish to kill just ‘FOO’, and not the comma and the space, use M-b M-d instead of M-DEL.

M-t (transpose-words) exchanges the word before or containing point with the following word. The delimiter characters between the words do not move. For example, ‘FOO, BAR’ transposes into ‘BAR, FOO’ rather than ‘BAR FOO, ’. See Transposing Text, for more on transposition.

To operate on words with an operation which acts on the region, use the command M-@ (mark-word). This command sets the mark where M-f would move to. See Commands to Mark Textual Objects, for more information about this command.

The word commands’ understanding of word boundaries is controlled by the syntax table. Any character can, for example, be declared to be a word delimiter. See Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

In addition, see Cursor Position Information for the M-= (count-words-region) and M-x count-words commands, which count and report the number of words in the region or buffer.

26.2 Sentences

The Emacs commands for manipulating sentences and paragraphs are mostly on Meta keys, like the word-handling commands.

M-a

Move back to the beginning of the sentence (backward-sentence).

M-e

Move forward to the end of the sentence (forward-sentence).

M-k

Kill forward to the end of the sentence (kill-sentence).

C-x DEL

Kill back to the beginning of the sentence (backward-kill-sentence).

The commands M-a (backward-sentence) and M-e (forward-sentence) move to the beginning and end of the current sentence, respectively. Their bindings were chosen to resemble C-a and C-e, which move to the beginning and end of a line. Unlike them, M-a and M-e move over successive sentences if repeated.

Moving backward over a sentence places point just before the first character of the sentence; moving forward places point right after the punctuation that ends the sentence. Neither one moves over the whitespace at the sentence boundary.

Just as C-a and C-e have a kill command, C-k, to go with them, M-a and M-e have a corresponding kill command: M-k (kill-sentence) kills from point to the end of the sentence. With a positive numeric argument n, it kills the next n sentences; with a negative argument −n, it kills back to the beginning of the nth preceding sentence.

The C-x DEL (backward-kill-sentence) kills back to the beginning of a sentence.

The sentence commands assume that you follow the American typist’s convention of putting two spaces at the end of a sentence. That is, a sentence ends wherever there is a ‘.’, ‘?’ or ‘!’ followed by the end of a line or two spaces, with any number of ‘)’, ‘]’, ‘'’, or ‘"’ characters allowed in between. A sentence also begins or ends wherever a paragraph begins or ends. It is useful to follow this convention, because it allows the Emacs sentence commands to distinguish between periods that end a sentence and periods that indicate abbreviations.

If you want to use just one space between sentences, you can set the variable sentence-end-double-space to nil to make the sentence commands stop for single spaces. However, this has a drawback: there is no way to distinguish between periods that end sentences and those that indicate abbreviations. For convenient and reliable editing, we therefore recommend you follow the two-space convention. The variable sentence-end-double-space also affects filling (see Explicit Fill Commands).

The variable sentence-end controls how to recognize the end of a sentence. If non-nil, its value should be a regular expression, which is used to match the last few characters of a sentence, together with the whitespace following the sentence (see Syntax of Regular Expressions). If the value is nil, the default, then Emacs computes sentence ends according to various criteria such as the value of sentence-end-double-space.

Some languages, such as Thai, do not use periods to indicate the end of a sentence. Set the variable sentence-end-without-period to t in such cases.

26.3 Paragraphs

The Emacs commands for manipulating paragraphs are also on Meta keys.

M-{

Move back to previous paragraph beginning (backward-paragraph).

M-}

Move forward to next paragraph end (forward-paragraph).

M-h

Put point and mark around this or next paragraph (mark-paragraph).

M-{ (backward-paragraph) moves to the beginning of the current or previous paragraph, depending on where point is when the command is invoked (see below for the definition of a paragraph). M-} (forward-paragraph) similarly moves to the end of the current or next paragraph. If there is a blank line before the paragraph, M-{ moves to the blank line.

When you wish to operate on a paragraph, type M-h (mark-paragraph) to set the region around it. For example, M-h C-w kills the paragraph around or after point. M-h puts point at the beginning and mark at the end of the paragraph point was in. If point is between paragraphs (in a run of blank lines, or at a boundary), M-h sets the region around the paragraph following point. If there are blank lines preceding the first line of the paragraph, one of these blank lines is included in the region. If the region is already active, the command sets the mark without changing point, and each subsequent M-h further advances the mark by one paragraph.

The definition of a paragraph depends on the major mode. In Fundamental mode, as well as Text mode and related modes, a paragraph is separated from neighboring paragraphs by one or more blank lines—lines that are either empty, or consist solely of space, tab and/or formfeed characters. In programming language modes, paragraphs are usually defined in a similar way, so that you can use the paragraph commands even though there are no paragraphs as such in a program.

Note that an indented line is not itself a paragraph break in Text mode. If you want indented lines to separate paragraphs, use Paragraph-Indent Text mode instead. See Text Mode.

If you set a fill prefix, then paragraphs are delimited by all lines which don’t start with the fill prefix. See Filling Text.

The precise definition of a paragraph boundary is controlled by the variables paragraph-separate and paragraph-start. The value of paragraph-start is a regular expression that should match lines that either start or separate paragraphs (see Syntax of Regular Expressions). The value of paragraph-separate is another regular expression that should match lines that separate paragraphs without being part of any paragraph (for example, blank lines). Lines that start a new paragraph and are contained in it must match only paragraph-start, not paragraph-separate. For example, in Fundamental mode, paragraph-start is "\f\\|[ \t]*$" , and paragraph-separate is "[ \t\f]*$" .

Note that paragraph-start and paragraph-separate are matched against the text at the left margin, which is not necessarily the beginning of the line, so these regexps should not use ‘^’ as an anchor, to ensure that the paragraph functions will work equally within a region of text indented by a margin setting.

26.4 Pages

Within some text files, text is divided into pages delimited by the formfeed character (ASCII code 12, also denoted as ‘control-L’), which is displayed in Emacs as the escape sequence ‘^L’ (see How Text Is Displayed). Traditionally, when such text files are printed to hardcopy, each formfeed character forces a page break. Most Emacs commands treat it just like any other character, so you can insert it with C-q C-l, delete it with DEL, etc. In addition, Emacs provides commands to move over pages and operate on them.

M-x what-page

Display the page number of point, and the line number within that page.

C-x [

Move point to previous page boundary (backward-page).

C-x ]

Move point to next page boundary (forward-page).

C-x C-p

Put point and mark around this page (or another page) (mark-page).

C-x l

Count the lines in this page (count-lines-page).

M-x what-page counts pages from the beginning of the file, and counts lines within the page, showing both numbers in the echo area.

The C-x [ (backward-page) command moves point to immediately after the previous page delimiter. If point is already right after a page delimiter, it skips that one and stops at the previous one. A numeric argument serves as a repeat count. The C-x ] (forward-page) command moves forward past the next page delimiter.

The C-x C-p command (mark-page) puts point at the beginning of the current page (after that page delimiter at the front), and the mark at the end of the page (after the page delimiter at the end).

C-x C-p C-w is a handy way to kill a page to move it elsewhere. If you move to another page delimiter with C-x [ and C-x ], then yank the killed page, all the pages will be properly delimited once again. Making sure this works as expected is the reason C-x C-p includes only the following page delimiter in the region.

A numeric argument to C-x C-p specifies which page to go to, relative to the current one. Zero means the current page, one means the next page, and −1 means the previous one.

The C-x l command (count-lines-page) is good for deciding where to break a page in two. It displays in the echo area the total number of lines in the current page, and then divides it up into those preceding the current line and those following, as in

Page has 96 (72+25) lines

Notice that the sum is off by one; this is correct if point is not at the beginning of a line.

The variable page-delimiter controls where pages begin. Its value is a regular expression that matches the beginning of a line that separates pages (see Syntax of Regular Expressions). The normal value of this variable is "^\f", which matches a formfeed character at the beginning of a line.

26.5 Quotation Marks

One common way to quote is the typewriter convention, which quotes using straight apostrophes ‘'like this'’ or double-quotes ‘"like this"’. Another common way is the curved quote convention, which uses left and right single or double quotation marks ‘like this’ or “like this”^11. In text files, typewriter quotes are simple and portable; curved quotes are less ambiguous and typically look nicer.

Electric Quote mode makes it easier to type curved quotes. As you type characters it optionally converts ` to ‘, ' to ’, `` to “, and '' to ”. It’s possible to change the default quotes listed above, by customizing the variable electric-quote-chars, a list of four characters, where the items correspond to the left single quote, the right single quote, the left double quote and the right double quote, respectively, whose default value is '(? ‘ ?’ ?“ ?”) .

You can customize the behavior of Electric Quote mode by customizing variables that control where it is active. It is active in text paragraphs if electric-quote-paragraph is non-nil, in programming-language comments if electric-quote-comment is non-nil, and in programming-language strings if electric-quote-string is non-nil. The default is nil for electric-quote-string and t for the other variables.

You can also set the option electric-quote-replace-double to a non-nil value. Then, typing " inserts an appropriate curved double quote depending on context: “ at the beginning of the buffer or after a line break, whitespace, opening parenthesis, or quote character, and ” otherwise.

Electric Quote mode is disabled by default. To toggle it in a single buffer, use M-x electric-quote-local-mode. To toggle it globally, type M-x electric-quote-mode. To suppress it for a single use, type C-q ` or C-q ' instead of ` or '. To insert a curved quote even when Electric Quote is disabled or inactive, you can type C-x 8 [ for ‘, C-x 8 ] for ’, C-x 8 { for “, and C-x 8 } for ”. See Inserting Text. Note that the value of electric-quote-chars does not affect these key bindings, they are not key bindings of electric-quote-mode but bound in global-map.

26.6 Filling Text

Filling text means breaking it up into lines that fit a specified width. Emacs does filling in two ways. In Auto Fill mode, inserting text with self-inserting characters also automatically fills it. There are also explicit fill commands that you can use when editing text.

26.6.1 Auto Fill Mode

Auto Fill mode is a buffer-local minor mode (see Minor Modes) in which lines are broken automatically when the line becomes too wide and you type SPC or RET.

M-x auto-fill-mode

Enable or disable Auto Fill mode.

SPC
RET

In Auto Fill mode, break lines when appropriate.

The mode command M-x auto-fill-mode toggles Auto Fill mode in the current buffer. Like any other minor mode, with a positive numeric argument, it enables Auto Fill mode, and with a negative argument it disables it. To enable Auto Fill mode automatically in certain major modes, add auto-fill-mode to the mode hooks (see Major Modes). When Auto Fill mode is enabled, the mode indicator ‘Fill’ appears in the mode line (see The Mode Line).

Auto Fill mode breaks lines automatically at the appropriate places whenever lines get longer than the desired width. This line breaking occurs only when you type SPC or RET. If you wish to insert a space or newline without permitting line-breaking, type C-q SPC or C-q C-j respectively. Also, C-o inserts a newline without line breaking.

The place where Auto Fill breaks a line depends on the line’s characters. For characters from ASCII, Latin, and most other scripts Emacs breaks a line on space characters, to keep the words intact. But for CJK scripts, a line can be broken between any two characters. (If you load the kinsoku library, Emacs will avoid breaking a line between certain pairs of CJK characters, where special rules prohibit that.)

When Auto Fill mode breaks a line, it tries to obey the adaptive fill prefix: if a fill prefix can be deduced from the first and/or second line of the current paragraph, it is inserted into the new line (see Adaptive Filling). Otherwise the new line is indented, as though you had typed TAB on it (see Indentation). In a programming language mode, if a line is broken in the middle of a comment, the comment is split by inserting new comment delimiters as appropriate.

Auto Fill mode does not refill entire paragraphs; it breaks lines but does not merge lines. Therefore, editing in the middle of a paragraph can result in a paragraph that is not correctly filled. To fill it, call the explicit fill commands (see Explicit Fill Commands).

A similar feature that wraps long lines automatically at display time is Visual Line Mode (see Visual Line Mode).

26.6.2 Explicit Fill Commands

M-q

Fill current paragraph (fill-paragraph).

C-x f

Set the fill column (set-fill-column).

M-x fill-region

Fill each paragraph in the region (fill-region).

M-x fill-region-as-paragraph

Fill the region, considering it as one paragraph.

M-x center-line

Center a line.

The command M-q (fill-paragraph) fills the current paragraph. It redistributes the line breaks within the paragraph, and deletes any excess space and tab characters occurring within the paragraph, in such a way that the lines end up fitting within a certain maximum width. Like Auto Fill mode, this and other filling commands usually break lines at space characters, but for CJK characters these commands can break a line between almost any two characters, and they can also obey the kinsoku rules. See Auto Fill Mode.

Normally, M-q acts on the paragraph where point is, but if point is between paragraphs, it acts on the paragraph after point. If the region is active, it acts instead on the text in the region. You can also call M-x fill-region to specifically fill the text in the region.

M-q and fill-region use the usual Emacs criteria for finding paragraph boundaries (see Paragraphs). For more control, you can use M-x fill-region-as-paragraph, which refills everything between point and mark as a single paragraph. This command deletes any blank lines within the region, so separate blocks of text end up combined into one block.

A numeric argument to M-q tells it to justify the text as well as filling it. This means that extra spaces are inserted to make the right margin line up exactly at the fill column. To remove the extra spaces, use M-q with no argument. (Likewise for fill-region.)

The maximum line width for filling is specified by the buffer-local variable fill-column. The default value (see Local Variables) is 70. The easiest way to set fill-column in the current buffer is to use the command C-x f (set-fill-column). With a numeric argument, it uses that as the new fill column. With just C-u as argument, it sets fill-column to the current horizontal position of point. Note that, by its very nature, fill-column is measured in column units; the actual position of that column on a graphical display depends on the font being used. In particular, using variable-pitch fonts will cause the fill-column occupy different horizontal positions on display in different lines.

The command M-x center-line centers the current line within the current fill column. With an argument n, it centers n lines individually and moves past them. This binding is made by Text mode and is available only in that and related modes (see Text Mode).

By default, Emacs considers a period followed by two spaces or by a newline as the end of a sentence; a period followed by just one space indicates an abbreviation, not the end of a sentence. Accordingly, the fill commands will not break a line after a period followed by just one space. If you set the variable sentence-end-double-space to nil, the fill commands will break a line after a period followed by one space, and put just one space after each period. See Sentences, for other effects and possible drawbacks of this.

If the variable colon-double-space is non-nil, the fill commands put two spaces after a colon.

To specify additional conditions where line-breaking is not allowed, customize the abnormal hook variable fill-nobreak-predicate (see Hooks). Each function in this hook is called with no arguments, with point positioned where Emacs is considering breaking a line. If a function returns a non-nil value, Emacs will not break the line there. Functions you can use there include: fill-single-word-nobreak-p (don’t break after the first word of a sentence or before the last); fill-single-char-nobreak-p (don’t break after a one-letter word preceded by a whitespace character); fill-french-nobreak-p (don’t break after ‘(’ or before ‘)’, ‘:’ or ‘?’); and fill-polish-nobreak-p (don’t break after a one letter word, even if preceded by a non-whitespace character).

Emacs can display an indicator in the fill-column position using the Display fill column indicator mode (see display-fill-column-indicator).

26.6.3 The Fill Prefix

The fill prefix feature allows paragraphs to be filled so that each line starts with a special string of characters (such as a sequence of spaces, giving an indented paragraph). You can specify a fill prefix explicitly; otherwise, Emacs tries to deduce one automatically (see Adaptive Filling).

C-x .

Set the fill prefix (set-fill-prefix).

M-q

Fill a paragraph using current fill prefix (fill-paragraph).

M-x fill-individual-paragraphs

Fill the region, considering each change of indentation as starting a new paragraph.

M-x fill-nonuniform-paragraphs

Fill the region, considering only paragraph-separator lines as starting a new paragraph.

To specify a fill prefix for the current buffer, move to a line that starts with the desired prefix, put point at the end of the prefix, and type C-x . (set-fill-prefix). (That’s a period after the C-x.) To turn off the fill prefix, specify an empty prefix: type C-x . with point at the beginning of a line.

When a fill prefix is in effect, the fill commands remove the fill prefix from each line of the paragraph before filling, and insert it on each line after filling. (The beginning of the first line of the paragraph is left unchanged, since often that is intentionally different.) Auto Fill mode also inserts the fill prefix automatically when it makes a new line (see Auto Fill Mode). The C-o command inserts the fill prefix on new lines it creates, when you use it at the beginning of a line (see Blank Lines). Conversely, the command M-^ deletes the prefix (if it occurs) after the newline that it deletes (see Indentation).

For example, if fill-column is 40 and you set the fill prefix to ‘;; ’, then M-q in the following text

;; This is an
;; example of a paragraph
;; inside a Lisp-style comment.

produces this:

;; This is an example of a paragraph
;; inside a Lisp-style comment.

Lines that do not start with the fill prefix are considered to start paragraphs, both in M-q and the paragraph commands; this gives good results for paragraphs with hanging indentation (every line indented except the first one). Lines which are blank or indented once the prefix is removed also separate or start paragraphs; this is what you want if you are writing multi-paragraph comments with a comment delimiter on each line.

You can use M-x fill-individual-paragraphs to set the fill prefix for each paragraph automatically. This command divides the region into paragraphs, treating every change in the amount of indentation as the start of a new paragraph, and fills each of these paragraphs. Thus, all the lines in one paragraph have the same amount of indentation. That indentation serves as the fill prefix for that paragraph.

M-x fill-nonuniform-paragraphs is a similar command that divides the region into paragraphs in a different way. It considers only paragraph-separating lines (as defined by paragraph-separate) as starting a new paragraph. Since this means that the lines of one paragraph may have different amounts of indentation, the fill prefix used is the smallest amount of indentation of any of the lines of the paragraph. This gives good results with styles that indent a paragraph’s first line more or less that the rest of the paragraph.

The fill prefix is stored in the variable fill-prefix. Its value is a string, or nil when there is no fill prefix. This is a per-buffer variable; altering the variable affects only the current buffer, but there is a default value which you can change as well. See Local Variables.

The indentation text property provides another way to control the amount of indentation paragraphs receive. See Indentation in Enriched Text.

26.6.4 Adaptive Filling

The fill commands can deduce the proper fill prefix for a paragraph automatically in certain cases: either whitespace or certain punctuation characters at the beginning of a line are propagated to all lines of the paragraph.

If the paragraph has two or more lines, the fill prefix is taken from the paragraph’s second line, but only if it appears on the first line as well.

If a paragraph has just one line, fill commands may take a prefix from that line. The decision is complicated because there are three reasonable things to do in such a case:

Use the first line’s prefix on all the lines of the paragraph.
Indent subsequent lines with whitespace, so that they line up under the text that follows the prefix on the first line, but don’t actually copy the prefix from the first line.
Don’t do anything special with the second and following lines.

All three of these styles of formatting are commonly used. So the fill commands try to determine what you would like, based on the prefix that appears and on the major mode. Here is how.

If the prefix found on the first line matches adaptive-fill-first-line-regexp, or if it appears to be a comment-starting sequence (this depends on the major mode), then the prefix found is used for filling the paragraph, provided it would not act as a paragraph starter on subsequent lines.

Otherwise, the prefix found is converted to an equivalent number of spaces, and those spaces are used as the fill prefix for the rest of the lines, provided they would not act as a paragraph starter on subsequent lines.

In Text mode, and other modes where only blank lines and page delimiters separate paragraphs, the prefix chosen by adaptive filling never acts as a paragraph starter, so it can always be used for filling.

The variable adaptive-fill-regexp determines what kinds of line beginnings can serve as a fill prefix: any characters at the start of the line that match this regular expression are used. If you set the variable adaptive-fill-mode to nil, the fill prefix is never chosen automatically.

You can specify more complex ways of choosing a fill prefix automatically by setting the variable adaptive-fill-function to a function. This function is called with point after the left margin of a line, and it should return the appropriate fill prefix based on that line. If it returns nil, adaptive-fill-regexp gets a chance to find a prefix.

26.7 Case Conversion Commands

Emacs has commands for converting either a single word or any arbitrary range of text to upper case or to lower case.

M-l

Convert following word to lower case (downcase-word).

M-u

Convert following word to upper case (upcase-word).

M-c

Capitalize the following word (capitalize-word).

C-x C-l

Convert region to lower case (downcase-region).

C-x C-u

Convert region to upper case (upcase-region).

M-l (downcase-word) converts the word after point to lower case, moving past it. Thus, repeating M-l converts successive words. M-u (upcase-word) converts to all capitals instead, while M-c (capitalize-word) puts the first letter of the word into upper case and the rest into lower case. All these commands convert several words at once if given an argument. They are especially convenient for converting a large amount of text from all upper case to mixed case, because you can move through the text using M-l, M-u or M-c on each word as appropriate, occasionally using M-f instead to skip a word.

When given a negative argument, the word case conversion commands apply to the appropriate number of words before point, but do not move point. This is convenient when you have just typed a word in the wrong case: you can give the case conversion command and continue typing.

If a word case conversion command is given in the middle of a word, it applies only to the part of the word which follows point. (This is comparable to what M-d (kill-word) does.) With a negative argument, case conversion applies only to the part of the word before point.

The other case conversion commands are C-x C-u (upcase-region) and C-x C-l (downcase-region), which convert everything between point and mark to the specified case. Point and mark do not move.

The region case conversion commands upcase-region and downcase-region are normally disabled. This means that they ask for confirmation if you try to use them. When you confirm, you may enable the command, which means it will not ask for confirmation again. See Disabling Commands.

26.8 Text Mode

Text mode is a major mode for editing files of text in a human language. Files which have names ending in the extension .txt are usually opened in Text mode (see Choosing File Modes). To explicitly switch to Text mode, type M-x text-mode.

In Text mode, only blank lines and page delimiters separate paragraphs. As a result, paragraphs can be indented, and adaptive filling determines what indentation to use when filling a paragraph. See Adaptive Filling.

In Text mode, the TAB (indent-for-tab-command) command usually inserts whitespace up to the next tab stop, instead of indenting the current line. See Indentation, for details.

Text mode turns off the features concerned with comments except when you explicitly invoke them. It changes the syntax table so that apostrophes are considered part of words (e.g., ‘don't’ is considered one word). However, if a word starts with an apostrophe, it is treated as a prefix for the purposes of capitalization (e.g., M-c converts ‘'hello'’ into ‘'Hello'’, as expected).

If you indent the first lines of paragraphs, then you should use Paragraph-Indent Text mode (M-x paragraph-indent-text-mode) rather than Text mode. In that mode, you do not need to have blank lines between paragraphs, because the first-line indentation is sufficient to start a paragraph; however paragraphs in which every line is indented are not supported. Use M-x paragraph-indent-minor-mode to enable an equivalent minor mode for situations where you shouldn’t change the major mode—in mail composition, for instance.

Text mode binds M-TAB to ispell-complete-word. This command performs completion of the partial word in the buffer before point, using the spelling dictionary as the space of possible words. See Checking and Correcting Spelling. If your window manager defines M-TAB to switch windows, you can type ESC TAB or C-M-i instead.

Entering Text mode runs the mode hook text-mode-hook (see Major Modes).

The following sections describe several major modes that are derived from Text mode. These derivatives share most of the features of Text mode described above. In particular, derivatives of Text mode run text-mode-hook prior to running their own mode hooks.

26.9 Outline Mode

Outline mode is a major mode derived from Text mode, which is specialized for editing outlines. It provides commands to navigate between entries in the outline structure, and commands to make parts of a buffer temporarily invisible, so that the outline structure may be more easily viewed. Type M-x outline-mode to switch to Outline mode. Entering Outline mode runs the hook text-mode-hook followed by the hook outline-mode-hook (see Hooks).

When you use an Outline mode command to make a line invisible (see Outline Visibility Commands), the line disappears from the screen. An ellipsis (three periods in a row) is displayed at the end of the previous visible line, to indicate the hidden text. Multiple consecutive invisible lines produce just one ellipsis.

Editing commands that operate on lines, such as C-n and C-p, treat the text of the invisible line as part of the previous visible line. Killing the ellipsis at the end of a visible line really kills all the following invisible text associated with the ellipsis.

26.9.1 Outline Minor Mode

Outline minor mode is a buffer-local minor mode which provides the same commands as the major mode, Outline mode, but can be used in conjunction with other major modes. You can type M-x outline-minor-mode to toggle Outline minor mode in the current buffer, or use a file-local variable setting to enable it in a specific file (see Local Variables in Files).

The major mode, Outline mode, provides special key bindings on the C-c prefix. Outline minor mode provides similar bindings with C-c @ as the prefix; this is to reduce the conflicts with the major mode’s special commands. (The variable outline-minor-mode-prefix controls the prefix used.)

If outline-minor-mode-use-buttons is non-nil, Outline minor mode will use buttons at the beginning of the heading lines, in addition to ellipsis, to show that a section is hidden. Clicking the mouse on the button toggles display of the section. If the value of this variable is insert, the buttons are inserted directly into the buffer text, so RET on the button will also toggle display of the section, like a mouse click does. Using the value insert is not recommended in editable buffers because it modifies them. If the value is in-margins, Outline minor mode will use the window margins to indicate that a section is hidden. The buttons are customizable as icons (see Icons).

If the outline-minor-mode-cycle user option is non-nil, the TAB and S-TAB keys that cycle the visibility are enabled on the outline heading lines (see outline-cycle). TAB cycles hiding, showing the sub-heading, and showing all for the current section. S-TAB does the same for the entire buffer.

26.9.2 Format of Outlines

Outline mode assumes that the lines in the buffer are of two types: heading lines and body lines. A heading line represents a topic in the outline. Heading lines start with one or more asterisk (‘*’) characters; the number of asterisks determines the depth of the heading in the outline structure. Thus, a heading line with one ‘*’ is a major topic; all the heading lines with two ‘*’s between it and the next one-‘*’ heading are its subtopics; and so on. Any line that is not a heading line is a body line. Body lines belong with the preceding heading line. Here is an example:

* Food
This is the body,
which says something about the topic of food.

** Delicious Food
This is the body of the second-level header.

** Distasteful Food
This could have
a body too, with
several lines.

*** Dormitory Food

* Shelter
Another first-level topic with its header line.

A heading line together with all following body lines is called collectively an entry. A heading line together with all following deeper heading lines and their body lines is called a subtree.

You can customize the criterion for distinguishing heading lines by setting the variable outline-regexp. (The recommended ways to do this are in a major mode function or with a file local variable.) Any line whose beginning has a match for this regexp is considered a heading line. Matches that start within a line (not at the left margin) do not count.

The length of the matching text determines the level of the heading; longer matches make a more deeply nested level. Thus, for example, if a text formatter has commands ‘@chapter’, ‘@section’ and ‘@subsection’ to divide the document into chapters and sections, you could make those lines count as heading lines by setting outline-regexp to ‘"@chap\\|@\\(sub\\)*section"’. Note the trick: the two words ‘chapter’ and ‘section’ are equally long, but by defining the regexp to match only ‘chap’ we ensure that the length of the text matched on a chapter heading is shorter, so that Outline mode will know that sections are contained in chapters. This works as long as no other command starts with ‘@chap’.

You can explicitly specify a rule for calculating the level of a heading line by setting the variable outline-level. The value of outline-level should be a function that takes no arguments and returns the level of the current heading. The recommended ways to set this variable are in a major mode command or with a file local variable.

26.9.3 Outline Motion Commands

Outline mode provides special motion commands that move backward and forward to heading lines.

C-c C-n

Move point to the next visible heading line (outline-next-visible-heading).

C-c C-p

Move point to the previous visible heading line (outline-previous-visible-heading).

C-c C-f

Move point to the next visible heading line at the same level as the one point is on (outline-forward-same-level).

C-c C-b

Move point to the previous visible heading line at the same level (outline-backward-same-level).

C-c C-u

Move point up to a lower-level (more inclusive) visible heading line (outline-up-heading).

All of the above commands accept numeric arguments as repeat counts. For example, C-c C-f, when given an argument, moves forward that many visible heading lines on the same level, and C-c C-u with an argument moves out of that many nested levels.

26.9.4 Outline Visibility Commands

Outline mode provides several commands for temporarily hiding or revealing parts of the buffer, based on the outline structure. These commands are not undoable; their effects are simply not recorded by the undo mechanism, so you can undo right past them (see Undo).

Many of these commands act on the current heading line. If point is on a heading line, that is the current heading line; if point is on a body line, the current heading line is the nearest preceding header line.

C-c C-c

Make the current heading line’s body invisible (outline-hide-entry).

C-c C-e

Make the current heading line’s body visible (outline-show-entry).

C-c C-d

Make everything under the current heading invisible, not including the heading itself (outline-hide-subtree).

C-c C-s

Make everything under the current heading visible, including body, subheadings, and their bodies (outline-show-subtree).

C-c C-l

Make the body of the current heading line, and of all its subheadings, invisible (outline-hide-leaves).

C-c C-k

Make all subheadings of the current heading line, at all levels, visible (outline-show-branches).

C-c C-i

Make immediate subheadings (one level down) of the current heading line visible (outline-show-children).

C-c C-t

Make all body lines in the buffer invisible (outline-hide-body).

C-c C-a

Make all lines in the buffer visible (outline-show-all).

C-c C-q

Hide everything except the top n levels of heading lines (outline-hide-sublevels).

C-c C-o

Hide everything except for the heading or body that point is in, plus the headings leading up from there to the top level of the outline (outline-hide-other).

The simplest of these commands are C-c C-c (outline-hide-entry), which hides the body lines directly following the current heading line, and C-c C-e (outline-show-entry), which reveals them. Subheadings and their bodies are not affected.

The commands C-c C-d (outline-hide-subtree) and C-c C-s (outline-show-subtree) are more powerful. They apply to the current heading line’s subtree: its body, all of its subheadings, both direct and indirect, and all of their bodies.

The command C-c C-l (outline-hide-leaves) hides the body of the current heading line as well as all the bodies in its subtree; the subheadings themselves are left visible. The command C-c C-k (outline-show-branches) reveals the subheadings, if they had previously been hidden (e.g., by C-c C-d). The command C-c C-i (outline-show-children) is a weaker version of this; it reveals just the direct subheadings, i.e., those one level down.

The command C-c C-o (outline-hide-other) hides everything except the entry that point is in, plus its parents (the headers leading up from there to top level in the outline) and the top level headings. It also reveals body lines preceding the first heading in the buffer.

The remaining commands affect the whole buffer. C-c C-t (outline-hide-body) makes all body lines invisible, so that you see just the outline structure (as a special exception, it will not hide lines at the top of the file, preceding the first header line, even though these are technically body lines). C-c C-a (outline-show-all) makes all lines visible. C-c C-q (outline-hide-sublevels) hides all but the top level headings at and above the level of the current heading line (defaulting to 1 if point is not on a heading); with a numeric argument n, it hides everything except the top n levels of heading lines. Note that it completely reveals all the n top levels and the body lines before the first heading.

Outline also provides two convenience commands to cycle the visibility of each section and the whole buffer. Typing TAB (outline-cycle) on a heading cycles the current section between “hide all”, “subheadings”, and “show all” states. Typing S-TAB (outline-cycle-buffer) cycles the whole buffer between “only top-level headings”, “all headings and subheadings”, and “show all” states.

When incremental search finds text that is hidden by Outline mode, it makes that part of the buffer visible. If you exit the search at that position, the text remains visible. To toggle whether or not an active incremental search can match hidden text, type M-s i. To change the default for future searches, customize the option search-invisible. (This option also affects how query-replace and related functions treat hidden text, see Query Replace.) You can also automatically make text visible as you navigate in it by using Reveal mode (M-x reveal-mode), a buffer-local minor mode.

The outline-default-state variable controls what headings will be visible after Outline mode is turned on. If non-nil, some headings are initially outlined. If equal to a number, show only headings up to and including the corresponding level. If equal to outline-show-all, all text of buffer is shown. If equal to outline-show-only-headings, show only headings, whatever their level is. If equal to a lambda function or function name, this function is expected to toggle headings visibility, and will be called without arguments after the mode is enabled.

26.9.5 Viewing One Outline in Multiple Views

You can display two views of a single outline at the same time, in different windows. To do this, you must create an indirect buffer using M-x make-indirect-buffer. The first argument of this command is the existing outline buffer name, and its second argument is the name to use for the new indirect buffer. See Indirect Buffers.

Once the indirect buffer exists, you can display it in a window in the normal fashion, with C-x 4 b or other Emacs commands. The Outline mode commands to show and hide parts of the text operate on each buffer independently; as a result, each buffer can have its own view. If you want more than two views on the same outline, create additional indirect buffers.

26.9.6 Folding Editing

The Foldout package extends Outline mode and Outline minor mode with folding commands. The idea of folding is that you zoom in on a nested portion of the outline, while hiding its relatives at higher levels.

Consider an Outline mode buffer with all the text and subheadings under level-1 headings hidden. To look at what is hidden under one of these headings, you could use C-c C-e (M-x outline-show-entry) to expose the body, or C-c C-i to expose the child (level-2) headings.

With Foldout, you use C-c C-z (M-x foldout-zoom-subtree). This exposes the body and child subheadings, and narrows the buffer so that only the level-1 heading, the body and the level-2 headings are visible. Now to look under one of the level-2 headings, position the cursor on it and use C-c C-z again. This exposes the level-2 body and its level-3 child subheadings and narrows the buffer again. Zooming in on successive subheadings can be done as much as you like. A string in the mode line shows how deep you’ve gone.

When zooming in on a heading, to see only the child subheadings specify a numeric argument: C-u C-c C-z. The number of levels of children can be specified too (compare M-x outline-show-children), e.g., M-2 C-c C-z exposes two levels of child subheadings. Alternatively, the body can be specified with a negative argument: M-- C-c C-z . The whole subtree can be expanded, similarly to C-c C-s (M-x outline-show-subtree), by specifying a zero argument: M-0 C-c C-z .

While you’re zoomed in, you can still use Outline mode’s exposure and hiding functions without disturbing Foldout. Also, since the buffer is narrowed, global editing actions will only affect text under the zoomed-in heading. This is useful for restricting changes to a particular chapter or section of your document.

To unzoom (exit) a fold, use C-c C-x (M-x foldout-exit-fold). This hides all the text and subheadings under the top-level heading and returns you to the previous view of the buffer. Specifying a numeric argument exits that many levels of folds. Specifying a zero argument exits all folds.

To cancel the narrowing of a fold without hiding the text and subheadings, specify a negative argument. For example, M--2 C-c C-x exits two folds and leaves the text and subheadings exposed.

Foldout mode also provides mouse commands for entering and exiting folds, and for showing and hiding text:

C-M-mouse-1 zooms in on the heading clicked on

single click: expose body.
double click: expose subheadings.
triple click: expose body and subheadings.
quad click: expose entire subtree.

C-M-mouse-2 exposes text under the heading clicked on

single click: expose body.
double click: expose subheadings.
triple click: expose body and subheadings.
quad click: expose entire subtree.

C-M-mouse-3 hides text under the heading clicked on or exits fold

single click: hide subtree.
double click: exit fold and hide text.
triple click: exit fold without hiding text.
quad click: exit all folds and hide text.

You can specify different modifier keys (instead of Ctrl-Meta-) by setting foldout-mouse-modifiers; but if you have already loaded the foldout.el library, you must reload it in order for this to take effect.

To use the Foldout package, you can type M-x load-library RET foldout RET; or you can arrange for to do that automatically by putting the following in your init file:

(with-eval-after-load "outline"
  (require 'foldout))

26.10 Org Mode

Org mode is a variant of Outline mode for using Emacs as an organizer and/or authoring system. Files with names ending in the extension .org are opened in Org mode (see Choosing File Modes). To explicitly switch to Org mode, type M-x org-mode.

In Org mode, as in Outline mode, each entry has a heading line that starts with one or more ‘*’ characters. See Format of Outlines. In addition, any line that begins with the ‘#’ character is treated as a comment.

Org mode provides commands for easily viewing and manipulating the outline structure. The simplest of these commands is TAB (org-cycle). If invoked on a heading line, it cycles through the different visibility states of the subtree: (i) showing only that heading line, (ii) showing only the heading line and the heading lines of its direct children, if any, and (iii) showing the entire subtree. If invoked in a body line, the global binding for TAB is executed.

Typing S-TAB (org-shifttab) anywhere in an Org mode buffer cycles the visibility of the entire outline structure, between (i) showing only top-level heading lines, (ii) showing all heading lines but no body lines, and (iii) showing everything.

You can move an entire entry up or down in the buffer, including its body lines and subtree (if any), by typing M-UP (org-metaup) or M-DOWN (org-metadown) on the heading line. Similarly, you can promote or demote a heading line with M-LEFT (org-metaleft) and M-RIGHT (org-metaright). These commands execute their global bindings if invoked on a body line.

The following subsections give basic instructions for using Org mode as an organizer and as an authoring system. For details, see Introduction in

The Org Manual

.

26.10.1 Org as an organizer

You can tag an Org entry as a TODO item by typing C-c C-t (org-todo) anywhere in the entry. This adds the keyword ‘TODO’ to the heading line. Typing C-c C-t again switches the keyword to ‘DONE’; another C-c C-t removes the keyword entirely, and so forth. You can customize the keywords used by C-c C-t via the variable org-todo-keywords.

Apart from marking an entry as TODO, you can attach a date to it, by typing C-c C-s (org-schedule) in the entry. This prompts for a date by popping up the Emacs Calendar (see The Calendar and the Diary), and then adds the tag ‘SCHEDULED’, together with the selected date, beneath the heading line. The command C-c C-d (org-deadline) has the same effect, except that it uses the tag DEADLINE.

Once you have some TODO items planned in an Org file, you can add that file to the list of agenda files by typing C-c [ (org-agenda-file-to-front). Org mode is designed to let you easily maintain multiple agenda files, e.g., for organizing different aspects of your life. The list of agenda files is stored in the variable org-agenda-files.

To view items coming from your agenda files, type M-x org-agenda. This command prompts for what you want to see: a list of things to do this week, a list of TODO items with specific keywords, etc. See Agenda Views in

The Org Manual

, for details.

26.10.2 Org as an authoring system

You may want to format your Org notes nicely and to prepare them for export and publication. To export the current buffer, type C-c C-e (org-export-dispatch) anywhere in an Org buffer. This command prompts for an export format; currently supported formats include HTML, LaTeX, Texinfo, OpenDocument (.odt), iCalendar, Markdown, man-page, and PDF. Some formats, such as PDF, require certain system tools to be installed.

To export several files at once to a specific directory, either locally or over the network, you must define a list of projects through the variable org-publish-project-alist. See its documentation for details.

Org supports a simple markup scheme for applying text formatting to exported documents:

- This text is /emphasized/
- This text is *in bold*
- This text is _underlined_
- This text uses =a teletype font=

#+begin_quote
``This is a quote.''
#+end_quote

#+begin_example
This is an example.
#+end_example

For further details, Exporting in

The Org Manual

, and Publishing in

The Org Manual

.

26.11 TeX Mode

TeX is a powerful text formatter written by Donald Knuth; like GNU Emacs, it is free software. The TeX format has several variants, including LaTeX, a simplified input format for TeX; DocTeX, a special file format in which the LaTeX sources are written, combining sources with documentation; and SliTeX, an obsolete special form of LaTeX^12.

Emacs provides a TeX major mode for each of these variants: Plain TeX mode, LaTeX mode, DocTeX mode, and SliTeX mode. Emacs selects the appropriate mode by looking at the contents of the buffer. (This is done by invoking the tex-mode command, which is normally called automatically when you visit a TeX-like file. See Choosing File Modes.) If the contents are insufficient to determine this, Emacs chooses the mode specified by the variable tex-default-mode; its default value is latex-mode. If Emacs does not guess right, you can select the correct variant of TeX mode using the commands plain-tex-mode, latex-mode, slitex-mode, or doctex-mode.

The following sections document the features of TeX mode and its variants. There are several other TeX-related Emacs packages, which are not documented in this manual:

BibTeX mode is a major mode for BibTeX files, which are commonly used for keeping bibliographic references for LaTeX documents. For more information, see the documentation string for the command bibtex-mode.
The RefTeX package provides a minor mode which can be used with LaTeX mode to manage bibliographic references. For more information, see the RefTeX Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs.
The AUCTeX package provides more advanced features for editing TeX and its related formats, including the ability to preview TeX equations within Emacs buffers. Unlike BibTeX mode and the RefTeX package, AUCTeX is not distributed with Emacs by default. It can be downloaded via the Package Menu (see Emacs Lisp Packages); once installed, see the AUCTeX manual, which is included with the package.

26.11.1 TeX Editing Commands

"

Insert, according to context, either ‘``’ or ‘"’ or ‘''’ (tex-insert-quote).

C-j

Insert a paragraph break (two newlines) and check the previous paragraph for unbalanced braces or dollar signs (tex-terminate-paragraph).

M-x tex-validate-region

Check each paragraph in the region for unbalanced braces or dollar signs.

C-c {

Insert ‘{}’ and position point between them (tex-insert-braces).

C-c }

Move forward past the next unmatched close brace (up-list).

In TeX, the character ‘"’ is not normally used; instead, quotations begin with ‘``’ and end with ‘''’. TeX mode therefore binds the " key to the tex-insert-quote command. This inserts ‘``’ after whitespace or an open brace, ‘"’ after a backslash, and ‘''’ after any other character.

As a special exception, if you type " when the text before point is either ‘``’ or ‘''’, Emacs replaces that preceding text with a single ‘"’ character. You can therefore type "" to insert ‘"’, should you ever need to do so. (You can also use C-q " to insert this character.)

In TeX mode, ‘$’ has a special syntax code which attempts to understand the way TeX math mode delimiters match. When you insert a ‘$’ that is meant to exit math mode, the position of the matching ‘$’ that entered math mode is displayed for a second. This is the same feature that displays the open brace that matches a close brace that is inserted. However, there is no way to tell whether a ‘$’ enters math mode or leaves it; so when you insert a ‘$’ that enters math mode, the previous ‘$’ position is shown as if it were a match, even though they are actually unrelated.

TeX uses braces as delimiters that must match. Some users prefer to keep braces balanced at all times, rather than inserting them singly. Use C-c { (tex-insert-braces) to insert a pair of braces. It leaves point between the two braces so you can insert the text that belongs inside. Afterward, use the command C-c } (up-list) to move forward past the close brace. You can also invoke C-c { after marking some text: then the command encloses the marked text in braces.

There are two commands for checking the matching of braces. C-j (tex-terminate-paragraph) checks the paragraph before point, and inserts two newlines to start a new paragraph. It outputs a message in the echo area if any mismatch is found. M-x tex-validate-region checks a region, paragraph by paragraph. The errors are listed in an *Occur* buffer; you can use the usual Occur mode commands in that buffer, such as C-c C-c, to visit a particular mismatch (see Other Search-and-Loop Commands).

Note that Emacs commands count square brackets and parentheses in TeX mode, not just braces. This is not strictly correct for the purpose of checking TeX syntax. However, parentheses and square brackets are likely to be used in text as matching delimiters, and it is useful for the various motion commands and automatic match display to work with them.

26.11.2 LaTeX Editing Commands

LaTeX mode provides a few extra features not applicable to plain TeX:

C-c C-o

Insert ‘\begin’ and ‘\end’ for LaTeX block and position point on a line between them (latex-insert-block).

C-c C-e

Close the innermost LaTeX block not yet closed (latex-close-block).

In LaTeX input, ‘\begin’ and ‘\end’ tags are used to group blocks of text. To insert a block, type C-c C-o (latex-insert-block). This prompts for a block type, and inserts the appropriate matching ‘\begin’ and ‘\end’ tags, leaving a blank line between the two and moving point there.

When entering the block type argument to C-c C-o, you can use the usual completion commands (see Completion). The default completion list contains the standard LaTeX block types. If you want additional block types for completion, customize the list variable latex-block-names.

In LaTeX input, ‘\begin’ and ‘\end’ tags must balance. You can use C-c C-e (latex-close-block) to insert an ‘\end’ tag which matches the last unmatched ‘\begin’. It also indents the ‘\end’ to match the corresponding ‘\begin’, and inserts a newline after the ‘\end’ tag if point is at the beginning of a line. The minor mode latex-electric-env-pair-mode automatically inserts an ‘\end’ or ‘\begin’ tag for you when you type the corresponding one.

26.11.3 TeX Printing Commands

You can invoke TeX as a subprocess of Emacs, supplying either the entire contents of the buffer or just part of it (e.g., one chapter of a larger document).

C-c C-b

Invoke TeX on the entire current buffer (tex-buffer).

C-c C-r

Invoke TeX on the current region, together with the buffer’s header (tex-region).

C-c C-f

Invoke TeX on the current file (tex-file).

C-c C-v

Preview the output from the last C-c C-b, C-c C-r, or C-c C-f command (tex-view).

C-c C-p

Print the output from the last C-c C-b, C-c C-r, or C-c C-f command (tex-print).

C-c TAB

Invoke BibTeX on the current file (tex-bibtex-file).

C-c C-l

Recenter the window showing output from TeX so that the last line can be seen (tex-recenter-output-buffer).

C-c C-k

Kill the TeX subprocess (tex-kill-job).

C-c C-c

Invoke some other compilation command on the entire current buffer (tex-compile).

To pass the current buffer through TeX, type C-c C-b (tex-buffer). The formatted output goes in a temporary file, normally a .dvi file. Afterwards, you can type C-c C-v (tex-view) to launch an external program, such as xdvi, to view this output file. You can also type C-c C-p (tex-print) to print a hardcopy of the output file.

By default, C-c C-b runs TeX in the current directory. The output of TeX is also created in this directory. To run TeX in a different directory, change the variable tex-directory to the desired directory. If your environment variable TEXINPUTS contains relative names, or if your files contain ‘\input’ commands with relative file names, then tex-directory must be "." or you will get the wrong results. Otherwise, it is safe to specify some other directory, such as "/tmp".

The buffer’s TeX variant determines what shell command C-c C-b actually runs. In Plain TeX mode, it is specified by the variable tex-run-command, which defaults to "tex". In LaTeX mode, it is specified by latex-run-command, which defaults to "latex". The shell command that C-c C-v runs to view the .dvi output is determined by the variable tex-dvi-view-command, regardless of the TeX variant. The shell command that C-c C-p runs to print the output is determined by the variable tex-dvi-print-command. The variable tex-print-file-extension can be set to the required file extension for viewing and printing TeX-compiled files. For example, you can set it to .pdf, and update tex-dvi-view-command and tex-dvi-print-command accordingly, as well as latex-run-command or tex-run-command.

Normally, Emacs automatically appends the output file name to the shell command strings described in the preceding paragraph. For example, if tex-dvi-view-command is "xdvi", C-c C-v runs xdvi output-file-name. In some cases, however, the file name needs to be embedded in the command, e.g., if you need to provide the file name as an argument to one command whose output is piped to another. You can specify where to put the file name with ‘*’ in the command string. For example,

(setq tex-dvi-print-command "dvips -f * | lpr")

The terminal output from TeX, including any error messages, appears in a buffer called *tex-shell*. If TeX gets an error, you can switch to this buffer and feed it input (this works as in Shell mode; see Interactive Subshell). Without switching to this buffer you can scroll it so that its last line is visible by typing C-c C-l.

Type C-c C-k (tex-kill-job) to kill the TeX process if you see that its output is no longer useful. Using C-c C-b or C-c C-r also kills any TeX process still running.

You can also pass an arbitrary region through TeX by typing C-c C-r (tex-region). This is tricky, however, because most files of TeX input contain commands at the beginning to set parameters and define macros, without which no later part of the file will format correctly. To solve this problem, C-c C-r allows you to designate a part of the file as containing essential commands; it is included before the specified region as part of the input to TeX. The designated part of the file is called the header.

To indicate the bounds of the header in Plain TeX mode, you insert two special strings in the file. Insert ‘%**start of header’ before the header, and ‘%**end of header’ after it. Each string must appear entirely on one line, but there may be other text on the line before or after. The lines containing the two strings are included in the header. If ‘%**start of header’ does not appear within the first 100 lines of the buffer, C-c C-r assumes that there is no header.

In LaTeX mode, the header begins with ‘\documentclass’ or ‘\documentstyle’ and ends with ‘\begin{document}’. These are commands that LaTeX requires you to use in any case, so nothing special needs to be done to identify the header.

The commands (tex-buffer) and (tex-region) do all of their work in a temporary directory, and do not have available any of the auxiliary files needed by TeX for cross-references; these commands are generally not suitable for running the final copy in which all of the cross-references need to be correct.

When you want the auxiliary files for cross references, use C-c C-f (tex-file) which runs TeX on the current buffer’s file, in that file’s directory. Before running TeX, it offers to save any modified buffers. Generally, you need to use (tex-file) twice to get the cross-references right.

The value of the variable tex-start-options specifies options for the TeX run.

The value of the variable tex-start-commands specifies TeX commands for starting TeX. The default value causes TeX to run in nonstop mode. To run TeX interactively, set the variable to "".

Large TeX documents are often split into several files—one main file, plus subfiles. Running TeX on a subfile typically does not work; you have to run it on the main file. In order to make tex-file useful when you are editing a subfile, you can set the variable tex-main-file to the name of the main file. Then tex-file runs TeX on that file.

The most convenient way to use tex-main-file is to specify it in a local variable list in each of the subfiles. See Local Variables in Files.

For LaTeX files, you can use BibTeX to process the auxiliary file for the current buffer’s file. BibTeX looks up bibliographic citations in a data base and prepares the cited references for the bibliography section. The command C-c TAB (tex-bibtex-file) runs the shell command (tex-bibtex-command) to produce a ‘.bbl’ file for the current buffer’s file. Generally, you need to do C-c C-f (tex-file) once to generate the ‘.aux’ file, then do C-c TAB (tex-bibtex-file), and then repeat C-c C-f (tex-file) twice more to get the cross-references correct.

To invoke some other compilation program on the current TeX buffer, type C-c C-c (tex-compile). This command knows how to pass arguments to many common programs, including pdflatex, yap, xdvi, and dvips. You can select your desired compilation program using the standard completion keys (see Completion).

26.11.4 TeX Mode Miscellany

Entering any variant of TeX mode runs the hooks text-mode-hook and tex-mode-hook. Then it runs either plain-tex-mode-hook, doctex-mode-hook, latex-mode-hook, or slitex-mode-hook, whichever is appropriate. Starting the TeX shell runs the hook tex-shell-hook. See Hooks.

The commands M-x iso-iso2tex, M-x iso-tex2iso, M-x iso-iso2gtex and M-x iso-gtex2iso can be used to convert between Latin-1 encoded files and TeX-encoded equivalents.

26.12 SGML and HTML Modes

The major modes for SGML and HTML provide indentation support and commands for operating on tags.

HTML consists of two modes—one, a basic mode called html-mode is a slightly customized variant of SGML mode. The other, which is used by default for HTML files, is called mhtml-mode, and attempts to properly handle Javascript enclosed in a <script> element and CSS embedded in a <style> element.

C-c C-n

Interactively specify a special character and insert the SGML ‘&’-command for that character (sgml-name-char).

C-c C-t

Interactively specify a tag and its attributes (sgml-tag). This command asks you for a tag name and for the attribute values, then inserts both the opening tag and the closing tag, leaving point between them.

With a prefix argument n, the command puts the tag around the n words already present in the buffer after point. Whenever a region is active, it puts the tag around the region (when Transient Mark mode is off, it does this when a numeric argument of −1 is supplied.)

C-c C-a

Interactively insert attribute values for the current tag (sgml-attributes).

C-c C-f

Skip across a balanced tag group (which extends from an opening tag through its corresponding closing tag) (sgml-skip-tag-forward). A numeric argument acts as a repeat count.

C-c C-b

Skip backward across a balanced tag group (which extends from an opening tag through its corresponding closing tag) (sgml-skip-tag-backward). A numeric argument acts as a repeat count.

C-c C-d

Delete the tag at or after point, and delete the matching tag too (sgml-delete-tag). If the tag at or after point is an opening tag, delete the closing tag too; if it is a closing tag, delete the opening tag too.

C-c ? tag RET

Display a description of the meaning of tag tag (sgml-tag-help). If the argument tag is empty, describe the tag at point.

C-c /

Insert a close tag for the innermost unterminated tag (sgml-close-tag). If called within a tag or a comment, close it instead of inserting a close tag.

C-c 8

Toggle a minor mode in which Latin-1 characters insert the corresponding SGML commands that stand for them, instead of the characters themselves (sgml-name-8bit-mode).

C-c C-v

Run a shell command (which you must specify) to validate the current buffer as SGML (sgml-validate). (In HTML mode this key sequence runs a different command.)

C-c TAB

Toggle the visibility of existing tags in the buffer. This can be used as a cheap preview (sgml-tags-invisible).

The major mode for editing XML documents is called nXML mode. This is a powerful major mode that can recognize many existing XML schemas and use them to provide completion of XML elements via M-TAB, as well as on-the-fly XML validation with error highlighting. To enable nXML mode in an existing buffer, type M-x nxml-mode, or, equivalently, M-x xml-mode. Emacs uses nXML mode for files which have the extension .xml. For XHTML files, which have the extension .xhtml, Emacs uses HTML mode by default; you can make it use nXML mode by customizing the variable auto-mode-alist (see Choosing File Modes). nXML mode is described in an Info manual, which is distributed with Emacs.

You may choose to use the less powerful SGML mode for editing XML, since XML is a strict subset of SGML. To enable SGML mode in an existing buffer, type M-x sgml-mode. On enabling SGML mode, Emacs examines the buffer to determine whether it is XML; if so, it sets the variable sgml-xml-mode to a non-nil value. This causes SGML mode’s tag insertion commands, described above, to always insert explicit closing tags as well.

26.13 Nroff Mode

Nroff mode, a major mode derived from Text mode, is specialized for editing nroff files (e.g., Unix man pages). Type M-x nroff-mode to enter this mode. Entering Nroff mode runs the hook text-mode-hook, then nroff-mode-hook (see Hooks).

In Nroff mode, nroff command lines are treated as paragraph separators, pages are separated by ‘.bp’ commands, and comments start with backslash-doublequote. It also defines these commands:

M-n

Move to the beginning of the next line that isn’t an nroff command (nroff-forward-text-line). An argument is a repeat count.

M-p

Like M-n but move up (nroff-backward-text-line).

M-?

Displays in the echo area the number of text lines (lines that are not nroff commands) in the region (nroff-count-text-lines).

Electric Nroff mode is a buffer-local minor mode that can be used with Nroff mode. To toggle this minor mode, type M-x nroff-electric-mode (see Minor Modes). When the mode is on, each time you type RET to end a line containing an nroff command that opens a kind of grouping, the nroff command to close that grouping is automatically inserted on the following line.

If you use Outline minor mode with Nroff mode (see Outline Mode), heading lines are lines of the form ‘.H’ followed by a number (the header level).

26.14 Enriched Text

Enriched mode is a minor mode for editing formatted text files in a WYSIWYG (What You See Is What You Get) fashion. When Enriched mode is enabled, you can apply various formatting properties to the text in the buffer, such as fonts and colors; upon saving the buffer, those properties are saved together with the text, using the MIME ‘text/enriched’ file format.

Enriched mode is typically used with Text mode (see Text Mode). It is not compatible with Font Lock mode, which is used by many major modes, including most programming language modes, for syntax highlighting (see Font Lock mode). Unlike Enriched mode, Font Lock mode assigns text properties automatically, based on the current buffer contents; those properties are not saved to disk.

The file enriched.txt in Emacs’s data-directory serves as an example of the features of Enriched mode.

26.14.1 Enriched Mode

Enriched mode is a buffer-local minor mode (see Minor Modes). When you visit a file that has been saved in the ‘text/enriched’ format, Emacs automatically enables Enriched mode, and applies the formatting information in the file to the buffer text. When you save a buffer with Enriched mode enabled, it is saved using the ‘text/enriched’ format, including the formatting information.

To create a new file of formatted text, visit the nonexistent file and type M-x enriched-mode. This command actually toggles Enriched mode. With a prefix argument, it enables Enriched mode if the argument is positive, and disables Enriched mode otherwise. If you disable Enriched mode, Emacs no longer saves the buffer using the ‘text/enriched’ format; any formatting properties that have been added to the buffer remain in the buffer, but they are not saved to disk.

Enriched mode does not save all Emacs text properties, only those specified in the variable enriched-translations. These include properties for fonts, colors, indentation, and justification.

If you visit a file and Emacs fails to recognize that it is in the ‘text/enriched’ format, type M-x format-decode-buffer. This command prompts for a file format, and re-reads the file in that format. Specifying the ‘text/enriched’ format automatically enables Enriched mode.

To view a ‘text/enriched’ file in raw form (as plain text with markup tags rather than formatted text), use M-x find-file-literally (see Visiting Files).

See Format Conversion in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for details of how Emacs recognizes and converts file formats like ‘text/enriched’. See Text Properties in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for more information about text properties.

26.14.2 Hard and Soft Newlines

In Enriched mode, Emacs distinguishes between two different kinds of newlines, hard newlines and soft newlines. You can also enable or disable this feature in other buffers, by typing M-x use-hard-newlines.

Hard newlines are used to separate paragraphs, or anywhere there needs to be a line break regardless of how the text is filled; soft newlines are used for filling. The RET (newline) and C-o (open-line) commands insert hard newlines. The fill commands, including Auto Fill (see Auto Fill Mode), insert only soft newlines and delete only soft newlines, leaving hard newlines alone.

Thus, when editing with Enriched mode, you should not use RET or C-o to break lines in the middle of filled paragraphs. Use Auto Fill mode or explicit fill commands (see Explicit Fill Commands) instead. Use RET or C-o where line breaks should always remain, such as in tables and lists. For such lines, you may also want to set the justification style to unfilled (see Justification in Enriched Text).

26.14.3 Editing Format Information

The easiest way to alter properties is with the ‘Text Properties’ menu. You can get to this menu from the ‘Edit’ menu in the menu bar (see The Menu Bar), or with C-mouse-2 (see Mouse Clicks for Menus). Some of the commands in the ‘Text Properties’ menu are listed below (you can also invoke them with M-x):

Remove Face Properties

Remove face properties from the region (facemenu-remove-face-props).

Remove Text Properties

Remove all text properties from the region, including face properties (facemenu-remove-all).

Describe Properties

List all text properties and other information about the character following point (describe-text-properties).

Display Faces

Display a list of defined faces (list-faces-display). See Text Faces.

Display Colors

Display a list of defined colors (list-colors-display). See Colors for Faces.

The other menu entries are described in the following sections.

26.14.4 Faces in Enriched Text

The following commands can be used to add or remove faces (see Text Faces). Each applies to the text in the region if the mark is active, and to the next self-inserting character if the mark is inactive. With a prefix argument, each command applies to the next self-inserting character even if the region is active.

M-o d

Remove all face properties (facemenu-set-default).

M-o b

Apply the bold face (facemenu-set-bold).

M-o i

Apply the italic face (facemenu-set-italic).

M-o l

Apply the bold-italic face (facemenu-set-bold-italic).

M-o u

Apply the underline face (facemenu-set-underline).

M-o o face RET

Apply the face face (facemenu-set-face).

M-x facemenu-set-foreground

Prompt for a color (see Colors for Faces), and apply it as a foreground color.

M-x facemenu-set-background

Prompt for a color, and apply it as a background color.

These commands are also available via the Text Properties menu.

A self-inserting character normally inherits the face properties (and most other text properties) from the preceding character in the buffer. If you use one of the above commands to specify the face for the next self-inserting character, that character will not inherit the faces properties from the preceding character, but it will still inherit other text properties.

Enriched mode defines two additional faces: excerpt and fixed. These correspond to codes used in the text/enriched file format. The excerpt face is intended for quotations; by default, it appears the same as italic. The fixed face specifies fixed-width text; by default, it appears the same as bold.

26.14.5 Indentation in Enriched Text

In Enriched mode, you can specify different amounts of indentation for the right or left margin of a paragraph or a part of a paragraph. These margins also affect fill commands such as M-q (see Filling Text).

The Indentation submenu of Text Properties offers commands for specifying indentation:

Indent More

Indent the region by 4 columns (increase-left-margin). In Enriched mode, this command is also available on C-x TAB; if you supply a numeric argument, that says how many columns to add to the margin (a negative argument reduces the number of columns).

Indent Less

Remove 4 columns of indentation from the region.

Indent Right More

Make the text narrower by indenting 4 columns at the right margin.

Indent Right Less

Remove 4 columns of indentation from the right margin.

The variable standard-indent specifies how many columns these commands should add to or subtract from the indentation. The default value is 4. The default right margin for Enriched mode is controlled by the variable fill-column, as usual.

You can also type C-c [ (set-left-margin) and C-c ] (set-right-margin) to set the left and right margins. You can specify the margin width with a numeric argument; otherwise these commands prompt for a value via the minibuffer.

The fill prefix, if any, works in addition to the specified paragraph indentation: C-x . does not include the specified indentation’s whitespace in the new value for the fill prefix, and the fill commands look for the fill prefix after the indentation on each line. See The Fill Prefix.

26.14.6 Justification in Enriched Text

In Enriched mode, you can use the following commands to specify various justification styles for filling. These commands apply to the paragraph containing point, or, if the region is active, to all paragraphs overlapping the region.

M-j l

Align lines to the left margin (set-justification-left).

M-j r

Align lines to the right margin (set-justification-right).

M-j b

Align lines to both margins, inserting spaces in the middle of the line to achieve this (set-justification-full).

M-j c
M-S

Center lines between the margins (set-justification-center).

M-j u

Turn off filling entirely (set-justification-none). The fill commands do nothing on text with this setting. You can, however, still indent the left margin.

You can also specify justification styles using the Justification submenu in the Text Properties menu. The default justification style is specified by the per-buffer variable default-justification. Its value should be one of the symbols left, right, full, center, or none; their meanings correspond to the commands above.

26.14.7 Setting Other Text Properties

The Special Properties submenu of Text Properties has entries for adding or removing four other text properties: read-only, (which disallows alteration of the text), invisible (which hides text), intangible (which disallows moving point within the text), and charset (which is important for selecting a proper font to display a character). The ‘Remove Special’ menu item removes all of these special properties from the text in the region.

The invisible and intangible properties are not saved.

Enriched mode also supports saving and restoring display properties (see Display Property in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

), which affect how text is displayed on the screen, and also allow displaying images and strings that come from sources other than buffer text. The display properties also support execution of arbitrary Lisp forms as part of processing the property for display, thus providing a means to dynamically tailor the display to some conditions that can only be known at display time. Since execution of arbitrary Lisp opens Emacs to potential attacks, especially when the source of enriched text is outside of Emacs or even outside of your system (e.g., if it was received in an email message), such execution is by default disabled in Enriched mode. You can enable it by customizing the variable enriched-allow-eval-in-display-props to a non-nil value.

26.15 Editing Text-based Tables

The table package provides commands to easily edit text-based tables. Here is an example of what such a table looks like:

+-----------------+--------------------------------+-----------------+
|     Command     |          Description           |   Key Binding   |
+-----------------+--------------------------------+-----------------+
|  forward-char   |Move point right N characters   |       C-f       |
|                 |(left if N is negative).        |                 |
|                 |                                |                 |
+-----------------+--------------------------------+-----------------+
|  backward-char  |Move point left N characters    |       C-b       |
|                 |(right if N is negative).       |                 |
|                 |                                |                 |
+-----------------+--------------------------------+-----------------+

When Emacs recognizes such a stretch of text as a table (see Table Recognition), editing the contents of each table cell will automatically resize the table, whenever the contents become too large to fit in the cell. You can use the commands defined in the following sections for navigating and editing the table layout.

Type M-x table-fixed-width-mode to toggle the automatic table resizing feature.

26.15.1 What is a Text-based Table?

A table consists of a rectangular text area which is divided into cells. Each cell must be at least one character wide and one character high, not counting its border lines. A cell can be subdivided into more cells, but they cannot overlap.

Cell border lines are drawn with three special characters, specified by the following variables:

table-cell-vertical-char

The character used for vertical lines. The default is ‘|’.

table-cell-horizontal-chars

The characters used for horizontal lines. The default is ‘"-="’.

table-cell-intersection-char

The character used for the intersection of horizontal and vertical lines. The default is ‘+’.

The following are examples of invalid tables:

   +-----+       +--+    +-++--+
   |     |       |  |    | ||  |
   |     |       |  |    | ||  |
   +--+  |    +--+--+    +-++--+
   |  |  |    |  |  |    +-++--+
   |  |  |    |  |  |    | ||  |
   +--+--+    +--+--+    +-++--+
      a          b          c

From left to right:

Overlapped cells or non-rectangular cells are not allowed.
The border must be rectangular.
Cells must have a minimum width/height of one character.

26.15.2 Creating a Table

To create a text-based table from scratch, type M-x table-insert. This command prompts for the number of table columns, the number of table rows, cell width and cell height. The cell width and cell height do not include the cell borders; each can be specified as a single integer (which means each cell is given the same width/height), or as a sequence of integers separated by spaces or commas (which specify the width/height of the individual table columns/rows, counting from left to right for table columns and from top to bottom for table rows). The specified table is then inserted at point.

The table inserted by M-x table-insert contains special text properties, which tell Emacs to treat it specially as a text-based table. If you save the buffer to a file and visit it again later, those properties are lost, and the table appears to Emacs as an ordinary piece of text. See the next section, for how to convert it back into a table.

26.15.3 Table Recognition

Existing text-based tables in a buffer, which lack the special text properties applied by M-x table-insert, are not treated specially as tables. To apply those text properties, type M-x table-recognize. This command scans the current buffer, recognizes valid table cells, and applies the relevant text properties. Conversely, type M-x table-unrecognize to unrecognize all tables in the current buffer, removing the special text properties and converting tables back to plain text.

You can also use the following commands to selectively recognize or unrecognize tables:

M-x table-recognize-region

Recognize tables within the current region.

M-x table-unrecognize-region

Unrecognize tables within the current region.

M-x table-recognize-table

Recognize the table at point and activate it.

M-x table-unrecognize-table

Deactivate the table at point.

M-x table-recognize-cell

Recognize the cell at point and activate it.

M-x table-unrecognize-cell

Deactivate the cell at point.

See Converting Between Plain Text and Tables, for another way to recognize a table.

26.15.4 Commands for Table Cells

The commands M-x table-forward-cell and M-x table-backward-cell move point from the current cell to an adjacent cell. The order is cyclic: when point is in the last cell of a table, M-x table-forward-cell moves to the first cell. Likewise, when point is on the first cell, M-x table-backward-cell moves to the last cell.

M-x table-span-cell prompts for a direction—right, left, above, or below—and merges the current cell with the adjacent cell in that direction. This command signals an error if the merge would result in an illegitimate cell layout.

M-x table-split-cell splits the current cell vertically or horizontally, prompting for the direction with the minibuffer. To split in a specific direction, use M-x table-split-cell-vertically and M-x table-split-cell-horizontally. When splitting vertically, the old cell contents are automatically split between the two new cells. When splitting horizontally, you are prompted for how to divide the cell contents, if the cell is non-empty; the options are ‘split’ (divide the contents at point), ‘left’ (put all the contents in the left cell), and ‘right’ (put all the contents in the right cell).

The following commands enlarge or shrink a cell. By default, they resize by one row or column; if a numeric argument is supplied, that specifies the number of rows or columns to resize by.

M-x table-heighten-cell

Enlarge the current cell vertically.

M-x table-shorten-cell

Shrink the current cell vertically.

M-x table-widen-cell

Enlarge the current cell horizontally.

M-x table-narrow-cell

Shrink the current cell horizontally.

26.15.5 Cell Justification

The command M-x table-justify imposes justification on one or more cells in a text-based table. Justification determines how the text in the cell is aligned, relative to the edges of the cell. Each cell in a table can be separately justified.

M-x table-justify first prompts for what to justify; the options are ‘cell’ (just the current cell), ‘column’ (all cells in the current table column) and ‘row’ (all cells in the current table row). The command then prompts for the justification style; the options are left, center, right, top, middle, bottom, or none (meaning no vertical justification).

Horizontal and vertical justification styles are specified independently, and both types can be in effect simultaneously; for instance, you can call M-x table-justify twice, once to specify right justification and once to specify bottom justification, to align the contents of a cell to the bottom right.

The justification style is stored in the buffer as a text property, and is lost when you kill the buffer or exit Emacs. However, the table recognition commands, such as M-x table-recognize (see Table Recognition), attempt to determine and re-apply each cell’s justification style, by examining its contents. To disable this feature, change the variable table-detect-cell-alignment to nil.

26.15.6 Table Rows and Columns

M-x table-insert-row inserts a row of cells before the current table row. The current row, together with point, is pushed down past the new row. To insert a row after the last row at the bottom of a table, invoke this command with point below the table, just below the bottom edge. You can insert more than one row at a time by using a numeric prefix argument.

Similarly, M-x table-insert-column inserts a column of cells to the left of the current table column. To insert a column to the right side of the rightmost column, invoke this command with point to the right of the rightmost column, outside the table. A numeric prefix argument specifies the number of columns to insert.

M-x table-delete-column deletes the column of cells at point. Similarly, M-x table-delete-row deletes the row of cells at point. A numeric prefix argument to either command specifies the number of columns or rows to delete.

26.15.7 Converting Between Plain Text and Tables

The command M-x table-capture captures plain text in a region and turns it into a table. Unlike M-x table-recognize (see Table Recognition), the original text does not need to have a table appearance; it only needs to have a logical table-like structure.

For example, suppose we have the following numbers, which are divided into three lines and separated horizontally by commas:

1, 2, 3, 4
5, 6, 7, 8
, 9, 10

Invoking M-x table-capture on that text produces this table:

+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|1    |2    |3    |4    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|5    |6    |7    |8    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|     |9    |10   |     |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+

M-x table-release does the opposite: it converts a table back to plain text, removing its cell borders.

One application of this pair of commands is to edit a text in layout. Look at the following three paragraphs:

table-capture is a powerful command.
Here are some things it can do:

Parse Cell Items   Using row and column delimiter regexps,
                   it parses the specified text area and
                   extracts cell items into a table.

Applying table-capture to a region containing the above text, with empty strings for the column and row delimiter regexps, creates a table with a single cell like the following one.

+----------------------------------------------------------+
|table-capture is a powerful command.                      |
|Here are some things it can do:                           |
|                                                          |
|Parse Cell Items   Using row and column delimiter regexps,|
|                   it parses the specified text area and  |
|                   extracts cell items into a table.      |
+----------------------------------------------------------+

We can then use the cell splitting commands (see Commands for Table Cells) to subdivide the table so that each paragraph occupies a cell:

+----------------------------------------------------------+
|table-capture is a powerful command.                      |
|Here are some things it can do:                           |
+-----------------+----------------------------------------+
|Parse Cell Items | Using row and column delimiter regexps,|
|                 | it parses the specified text area and  |
|                 | extracts cell items into a table.      |
+-----------------+----------------------------------------+

Each cell can now be edited independently without affecting the layout of other cells. When finished, we can invoke M-x table-release to convert the table back to plain text.

26.15.8 Table Miscellany

The command table-query-dimension reports the layout of the table and table cell at point. Here is an example of its output:

Cell: (21w, 6h), Table: (67w, 16h), Dim: (2c, 3r), Total Cells: 5

This indicates that the current cell is 21 characters wide and 6 lines high, the table is 67 characters wide and 16 lines high with 2 columns and 3 rows, and a total of 5 cells.

M-x table-insert-sequence traverses the cells of a table inserting a sequence of text strings into each cell as it goes. It asks for the base string of the sequence, and then produces the sequence by “incrementing” the base string, either numerically (if the base string ends in numerical characters) or in the ASCII order. In addition to the base string, the command prompts for the number of elements in the sequence, the increment, the cell interval, and the justification of the text in each cell.

M-x table-generate-source generates a table formatted for a specific markup language. It asks for a language (which must be one of html, latex, cals, wiki or mediawiki), a destination buffer in which to put the result, and a table caption, and then inserts the generated table into the specified buffer. The default destination buffer is table.lang, where lang is the language you specified.

26.16 Two-Column Editing

Two-column mode lets you conveniently edit two side-by-side columns of text. It uses two side-by-side windows, each showing its own buffer. There are three ways to enter two-column mode:

F2 2 or C-x 6 2

Enter two-column mode with the current buffer on the left, and on the right, a buffer whose name is based on the current buffer’s name (2C-two-columns). If the right-hand buffer doesn’t already exist, it starts out empty; the current buffer’s contents are not changed.

This command is appropriate when the current buffer is empty or contains just one column and you want to add another column.

F2 s or C-x 6 s

Split the current buffer, which contains two-column text, into two buffers, and display them side by side (2C-split). The current buffer becomes the left-hand buffer, but the text in the right-hand column is moved into the right-hand buffer. The current column specifies the split point. Splitting starts with the current line and continues to the end of the buffer.

This command is appropriate when you have a buffer that already contains two-column text, and you wish to separate the columns temporarily.

F2 b buffer RET
C-x 6 b buffer RET

Enter two-column mode using the current buffer as the left-hand buffer, and using buffer buffer as the right-hand buffer (2C-associate-buffer).

F2 s or C-x 6 s looks for a column separator, which is a string that appears on each line between the two columns. You can specify the width of the separator with a numeric argument to F2 s; that many characters, before point, constitute the separator string. By default, the width is 1, so the column separator is the character before point.

When a line has the separator at the proper place, F2 s puts the text after the separator into the right-hand buffer, and deletes the separator. Lines that don’t have the column separator at the proper place remain unsplit; they stay in the left-hand buffer, and the right-hand buffer gets an empty line to correspond. (This is the way to write a line that spans both columns while in two-column mode: write it in the left-hand buffer, and put an empty line in the right-hand buffer.)

The command F2 RET or C-x 6 RET (2C-newline) inserts a newline in each of the two buffers at corresponding positions. This is the easiest way to add a new line to the two-column text while editing it in split buffers.

When you have edited both buffers as you wish, merge them with F2 1 or C-x 6 1 (2C-merge). This copies the text from the right-hand buffer as a second column in the other buffer. To go back to two-column editing, use F2 s.

Use F2 d or C-x 6 d to dissociate the two buffers, leaving each as it stands (2C-dissociate). If the other buffer, the one not current when you type F2 d, is empty, F2 d kills it.

Footnotes

(11)

The curved single quote characters are U+2018 LEFT SINGLE QUOTATION MARK and U+2019 RIGHT SINGLE QUOTATION MARK; the curved double quotes are U+201C LEFT DOUBLE QUOTATION MARK and U+201D RIGHT DOUBLE QUOTATION MARK. On text terminals which cannot display these characters, the Info reader might show them as the typewriter ASCII quote characters.

(12)

It has been replaced by the ‘slides’ document class, which comes with LaTeX.

21 Multiple Windows

Emacs can split a frame into two or many windows. Multiple windows can display parts of different buffers, or different parts of one buffer. Multiple frames always imply multiple windows, because each frame has its own set of windows. Each window belongs to one and only one frame.

21.1 Concepts of Emacs Windows

Each Emacs window displays one Emacs buffer at any time. A single buffer may appear in more than one window; if it does, any changes in its text are displayed in all the windows where it appears. But these windows can show different parts of the buffer, because each window has its own value of point.

At any time, one Emacs window is the selected window; the buffer this window is displaying is the current buffer. On graphical displays, the point is indicated by a solid blinking cursor in the selected window, and by a hollow box in non-selected windows. On text terminals, the cursor is drawn only in the selected window. See Displaying the Cursor.

Commands to move point affect the value of point for the selected Emacs window only. They do not change the value of point in other Emacs windows, even those showing the same buffer. The same is true for buffer-switching commands such as C-x b; they do not affect other windows at all. However, there are other commands such as C-x 4 b that select a different window and switch buffers in it. Also, all commands that display information in a window, including (for example) C-h f (describe-function) and C-x C-b (list-buffers), usually work by displaying buffers in a nonselected window without affecting the selected window.

When multiple windows show the same buffer, they can have different regions, because they can have different values of point. However, they all have the same value for the mark, because each buffer has only one mark position.

Each window has its own mode line, which displays the buffer name, modification status and major and minor modes of the buffer that is displayed in the window. The selected window’s mode line appears in a different color. See The Mode Line, for details.

21.2 Splitting Windows

C-x 2

Split the selected window into two windows, one above the other (split-window-below).

C-x 3

Split the selected window into two windows, positioned side by side (split-window-right).

C-mouse-2

In the mode line of a window, split that window.

C-x 2 (split-window-below) splits the selected window into two windows, one above the other. After splitting, the selected window is the upper one, and the newly split-off window is below. Both windows have the same value of point as before, and display the same portion of the buffer (or as close to it as possible). If necessary, the windows are scrolled to keep point on-screen. By default, the two windows each get half the height of the original window. A positive numeric argument specifies how many lines to give to the top window; a negative numeric argument specifies how many lines to give to the bottom window.

If you change the variable split-window-keep-point to nil, C-x 2 instead adjusts the portion of the buffer displayed by the two windows, as well as the value of point in each window, in order to keep the text on the screen as close as possible to what it was before; furthermore, if point was in the lower half of the original window, the bottom window is selected instead of the upper one.

C-x 3 (split-window-right) splits the selected window into two side-by-side windows. The left window is the selected one; the right window displays the same portion of the same buffer, and has the same value of point. A positive numeric argument specifies how many columns to give the left window; a negative numeric argument specifies how many columns to give the right window.

When you split a window with C-x 3, each resulting window occupies less than the full width of the frame. If it becomes too narrow, the buffer may be difficult to read if continuation lines are in use (see Continuation Lines). Therefore, Emacs automatically switches to line truncation if the window width becomes narrower than 50 columns. This truncation occurs regardless of the value of the variable truncate-lines (see Line Truncation); it is instead controlled by the variable truncate-partial-width-windows. If the value of this variable is a positive integer (the default is 50), that specifies the minimum total width for a partial-width window before automatic line truncation occurs; if the value is nil, automatic line truncation is disabled; and for any other non-nil value, Emacs truncates lines in every partial-width window regardless of its width. The total width of a window is in column units as reported by window-total-width (see Window Sizes in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

), it includes the fringes, the continuation and truncation glyphs, the margins, and the scroll bar.

On text terminals, side-by-side windows are separated by a vertical divider which is drawn using the vertical-border face.

If you click C-mouse-2 in the mode line of a window, that splits the window, putting a vertical divider where you click. Depending on how Emacs is compiled, you can also split a window by clicking C-mouse-2 in the scroll bar, which puts a horizontal divider where you click (this feature does not work when Emacs uses GTK+ scroll bars).

By default, when you split a window, Emacs gives each of the resulting windows dimensions that are an integral multiple of the default font size of the frame. That might subdivide the screen estate unevenly between the resulting windows. If you set the variable window-resize-pixelwise to a non-nil value, Emacs will give each window the same number of pixels (give or take one pixel if the initial dimension was an odd number of pixels). Note that when a frame’s pixel size is not a multiple of the frame’s character size, at least one window may get resized pixelwise even if this option is nil.

21.3 Using Other Windows

C-x o

Select another window (other-window).

C-M-v

Scroll the next window upward (scroll-other-window).

C-M-S-v

Scroll the next window downward (scroll-other-window-down).

C-M-S-l

Recenter the next window (recenter-other-window).

mouse-1

mouse-1, in the text area of a window, selects the window and moves point to the position clicked. Clicking in the mode line selects the window without moving point in it.

With the keyboard, you can switch windows by typing C-x o (other-window). That is an o, for “other”, not a zero. When there are more than two windows, this command moves through all the windows in a cyclic order, generally top to bottom and left to right. After the rightmost and bottommost window, it goes back to the one at the upper left corner. A numeric argument means to move several steps in the cyclic order of windows. A negative argument moves around the cycle in the opposite order. When the minibuffer is active, the minibuffer window is the last window in the cycle; you can switch from the minibuffer window to one of the other windows, and later switch back and finish supplying the minibuffer argument that is requested. See Editing in the Minibuffer.

The other-window command will normally only switch to the next window in the current frame (unless otherwise configured). If you work in a multi-frame environment and you want windows in all frames to be part of the cycle, you can rebind C-x o to the next-window-any-frame command. (See Changing Key Bindings Interactively, for how to rebind a command.)

The usual scrolling commands (see Controlling the Display) apply to the selected window only, but there are also commands to scroll the next window. C-M-v (scroll-other-window) scrolls the window that C-x o would select. In other respects, the command behaves like C-v; both move the buffer text upward relative to the window, and take positive and negative arguments. (In the minibuffer, C-M-v scrolls the help window associated with the minibuffer, if any, rather than the next window in the standard cyclic order; see Editing in the Minibuffer.) C-M-S-v (scroll-other-window-down) scrolls the next window downward in a similar way. Likewise, C-M-S-l (recenter-other-window) behaves like C-l (recenter-top-bottom) in the next window.

If you set mouse-autoselect-window to a non-nil value, moving the mouse over a different window selects that window. This feature is off by default.

21.4 Displaying in Another Window

C-x 4 is a prefix key for a variety of commands that switch to a buffer in a different window—either another existing window, or a new window created by splitting the selected window. See How display-buffer works, for how Emacs picks or creates the window to use.

C-x 4 b bufname RET

Select buffer bufname in another window (switch-to-buffer-other-window). See Creating and Selecting Buffers.

C-x 4 C-o bufname RET

Display buffer bufname in some window, without trying to select it (display-buffer). See Displaying a Buffer in a Window, for details about how the window is chosen.

C-x 4 f filename RET

Visit file filename and select its buffer in another window (find-file-other-window). See Visiting Files.

C-x 4 d directory RET

Select a Dired buffer for directory directory in another window (dired-other-window). See Dired, the Directory Editor.

C-x 4 m

Start composing a mail message, similar to C-x m (see Sending Mail), but in another window (compose-mail-other-window).

C-x 4 .

Find the definition of an identifier, similar to M-. (see Find Identifier References), but in another window (xref-find-definitions-other-window).

C-x 4 r filename RET

Visit file filename read-only, and select its buffer in another window (find-file-read-only-other-window). See Visiting Files.

C-x 4 4

A more general prefix command affects the buffer displayed by the next command invoked immediately after this prefix command. It requests the buffer of the next command to be displayed in another window.

C-x 4 1

This general prefix command requests the buffer of the next command to be displayed in the same window.

21.5 Deleting and Resizing Windows

C-x 0

Delete the selected window (delete-window).

C-x 1

Delete all windows in the selected frame except the selected window (delete-other-windows).

C-x 4 0

Delete the selected window and kill the buffer that was showing in it (kill-buffer-and-window). The last character in this key sequence is a zero.

C-x w 0 RET buffer RET

Delete windows showing the specified buffer.

C-x ^

Make selected window taller (enlarge-window).

C-x }

Make selected window wider (enlarge-window-horizontally).

C-x {

Make selected window narrower (shrink-window-horizontally).

C-x -

Shrink this window if its buffer doesn’t need so many lines (shrink-window-if-larger-than-buffer).

C-x +

Make all windows the same height (balance-windows).

To delete the selected window, type C-x 0 (delete-window). (That is a zero.) Once a window is deleted, the space that it occupied is given to an adjacent window (but not the minibuffer window, even if that is active at the time). Deleting the window has no effect on the buffer it used to display; the buffer continues to exist, and you can still switch to it with C-x b. The option delete-window-choose-selected controls which window is chosen as the new selected window instead (see Deleting Windows in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

C-x 4 0 (kill-buffer-and-window) is a stronger command than C-x 0; it kills the current buffer and then deletes the selected window.

C-x 1 (delete-other-windows) deletes all the windows, except the selected one; the selected window expands to use the whole frame. (This command cannot be used while the minibuffer window is active; attempting to do so signals an error.)

M-x delete-windows-on deletes windows that show a specific buffer. It prompts for the buffer, defaulting to the current buffer. With prefix argument of zero, C-u 0, this command deletes windows only on the current display’s frames.

The command C-x ^ (enlarge-window) makes the selected window one line taller, taking space from a vertically adjacent window without changing the height of the frame. With a positive numeric argument, this command increases the window height by that many lines; with a negative argument, it reduces the height by that many lines. If there are no vertically adjacent windows (i.e., the window is at the full frame height), that signals an error. The command also signals an error if you attempt to reduce the height of any window below a certain minimum number of lines, specified by the variable window-min-height (the default is 4).

Similarly, C-x } (enlarge-window-horizontally) makes the selected window wider, and C-x { (shrink-window-horizontally) makes it narrower. These commands signal an error if you attempt to reduce the width of any window below a certain minimum number of columns, specified by the variable window-min-width (the default is 10).

Mouse clicks on the mode line (see Mode Line Mouse Commands) or on window dividers (see Window Dividers) provide another way to change window heights and to split or delete windows.

C-x - (shrink-window-if-larger-than-buffer) reduces the height of the selected window, if it is taller than necessary to show the whole text of the buffer it is displaying. It gives the extra lines to other windows in the frame.

You can also use C-x + (balance-windows) to even out the heights of all the windows in the selected frame.

21.6 Displaying a Buffer in a Window

It is a common Emacs operation to display or pop up some buffer in response to a user command. There are several different ways in which commands do this.

Many commands, like C-x C-f (find-file), by default display the buffer by “taking over” the selected window, expecting that the user’s attention will be diverted to that buffer.

Some commands try to display intelligently, trying not to take over the selected window, e.g., by splitting off a new window and displaying the desired buffer there. Such commands, which include the various help commands (see Help), work by calling display-buffer internally. See How display-buffer works, for details.

Other commands do the same as display-buffer, and additionally select the displaying window so that you can begin editing its buffer. The command M-g M-n (next-error) is one example (see Compilation Mode). Such commands work by calling the function pop-to-buffer internally. See Switching to a Buffer in a Window in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

Commands with names ending in -other-window behave like display-buffer, except that they never display in the selected window. Several of these commands are bound in the C-x 4 prefix key (see Displaying in Another Window).

Commands with names ending in -other-frame behave like display-buffer, except that they (i) never display in the selected window and (ii) prefer to either create a new frame or use a window on some other frame to display the desired buffer. Several of these commands are bound in the C-x 5 prefix key.

21.6.1 How display-buffer works

The display-buffer command (as well as commands that call it internally) chooses a window to display by following the steps given below. See Choosing a Window for Displaying a Buffer in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

, for details about how to alter this sequence of steps.

If the buffer should be displayed in the selected window regardless of other considerations, reuse the selected window. By default, this step is skipped, but you can tell Emacs not to skip it by adding a regular expression matching the buffer’s name together with a reference to the display-buffer-same-window action function (see Action Functions for Buffer Display in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

) to the option display-buffer-alist (see Choosing a Window for Displaying a Buffer in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). For example, to display the buffer *scratch* preferably in the selected window write:

(setopt
 display-buffer-alist
 '(("\\*scratch\\*" (display-buffer-same-window))))

By default, display-buffer-alist is nil.

Otherwise, if the buffer is already displayed in an existing window, reuse that window. Normally, only windows on the selected frame are considered, but windows on other frames are also reusable if you use the corresponding reusable-frames action alist entry (see Action Alists for Buffer Display in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

). See the next step for an example of how to do that.
Otherwise, optionally create a new frame and display the buffer there. By default, this step is skipped. To enable it, change the value of the option display-buffer-base-action (see Choosing a Window for Displaying a Buffer in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

) as follows:

(setopt
 display-buffer-base-action
 '((display-buffer-reuse-window display-buffer-pop-up-frame)
   (reusable-frames . 0)))

This customization will also try to make the preceding step search for a reusable window on all visible or iconified frames.

Otherwise, try to create a new window by splitting a window on the selected frame, and display the buffer in that new window.

The split can be either vertical or horizontal, depending on the variables split-height-threshold and split-width-threshold. These variables should have integer values. If split-height-threshold is smaller than the chosen window’s height, the split puts the new window below. Otherwise, if split-width-threshold is smaller than the window’s width, the split puts the new window on the right. If neither condition holds, Emacs tries to split so that the new window is below—but only if the window was not split before (to avoid excessive splitting).

Otherwise, display the buffer in a window previously showing it. Normally, only windows on the selected frame are considered, but with a suitable reusable-frames action alist entry (see above) the window may be also on another frame.
Otherwise, display the buffer in an existing window on the selected frame.
If all the above methods fail for whatever reason, create a new frame and display the buffer there.

21.6.2 Displaying non-editable buffers.

Some buffers are shown in windows for perusal rather than for editing. Help commands (see Help) typically use a buffer called *Help* for that purpose, minibuffer completion (see Completion) uses a buffer called *Completions*, etc. Such buffers are usually displayed only for a short period of time.

Normally, Emacs chooses the window for such temporary displays via display-buffer, as described in the previous subsection. The *Completions* buffer, on the other hand, is normally displayed in a window at the bottom of the selected frame, regardless of the number of windows already shown on that frame.

If you prefer Emacs to display a temporary buffer in a different fashion, customize the variable display-buffer-alist (see Choosing a Window for Displaying a Buffer in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

) appropriately. For example, to display *Completions* always below the selected window, use the following form in your initialization file (see The Emacs Initialization File):

(setopt
 display-buffer-alist
 '(("\\*Completions\\*" display-buffer-below-selected)))

The *Completions* buffer is also special in the sense that Emacs usually tries to make its window just as large as necessary to display all of its contents. To resize windows showing other temporary displays, like, for example, the *Help* buffer, turn on the minor mode (see Minor Modes) temp-buffer-resize-mode (see Temporary Displays in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

The maximum size of windows resized by temp-buffer-resize-mode can be controlled by customizing the options temp-buffer-max-height and temp-buffer-max-width (see Temporary Displays in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

), and cannot exceed the size of the containing frame.

21.7 Convenience Features for Window Handling

Winner mode is a global minor mode that records the changes in the window configuration (i.e., how the frames are partitioned into windows), so that you can undo them. You can toggle Winner mode with M-x winner-mode, or by customizing the variable winner-mode. When the mode is enabled, C-c left (winner-undo) undoes the last window configuration change. If you change your mind while undoing, you can redo the changes you had undone using C-c right (M-x winner-redo). To prevent Winner mode from binding C-c left and C-c right, you can customize the variable winner-dont-bind-my-keys to a non-nil value. By default, Winner mode stores a maximum of 200 window configurations per frame, but you can change that by modifying the variable winner-ring-size. If there are some buffers whose windows you wouldn’t want Winner mode to restore, add their names to the list variable winner-boring-buffers or to the regexp winner-boring-buffers-regexp.

Follow mode (M-x follow-mode) synchronizes several windows on the same buffer so that they always display adjacent sections of that buffer. See Follow Mode.

The Windmove package defines commands for moving directionally between neighboring windows in a frame. M-x windmove-right selects the window immediately to the right of the currently selected one, and similarly for the left, up, and down counterparts. windmove-default-keybindings binds these commands to S-right etc.; doing so disables shift selection for those keys (see Shift Selection). In the same way as key bindings can be defined for commands that select windows directionally, you can use windmove-display-default-keybindings to define keybindings for commands that specify in what direction to display the window for the buffer that the next command is going to display. Also there is windmove-delete-default-keybindings to define keybindings for commands that delete windows directionally, and windmove-swap-states-default-keybindings that defines key bindings for commands that swap the window contents of the selected window with the window in the specified direction.

The command M-x compare-windows lets you compare the text shown in different windows. See Comparing Files.

Scroll All mode (M-x scroll-all-mode) is a global minor mode that causes scrolling commands and point motion commands to apply to every single window.

21.8 Window Tab Line

The command global-tab-line-mode toggles the display of a tab line on the top screen line of each window. The Tab Line shows special buttons (“tabs”) for each buffer that was displayed in a window, and allows switching to any of these buffers by clicking the corresponding button. Clicking on the + icon adds a new buffer to the window-local tab line of buffers, and clicking on the x icon of a tab deletes it. The mouse wheel on the tab line scrolls the tabs horizontally.

Selecting the previous window-local tab is the same as typing C-x LEFT (previous-buffer), selecting the next tab is the same as C-x RIGHT (next-buffer). Both commands support a numeric prefix argument as a repeat count.

You can customize the variable tab-line-tabs-function to define the preferred contents of the tab line. By default, it displays all buffers previously visited in the window, as described above. But you can also set it to display a list of buffers with the same major mode as the current buffer, or to display buffers grouped by their major mode, where clicking on the mode name in the first tab displays a list of all major modes where you can select another group of buffers.

Note that the Tab Line is different from the Tab Bar (see Tab Bars). Whereas tabs on the Tab Bar at the top of each frame are used to switch between window configurations containing several windows with buffers, tabs on the Tab Line at the top of each window are used to switch between buffers in the window.

Appendix D X Options and Resources

You can customize some X-related aspects of Emacs behavior using X resources, as is usual for programs that use X.

When Emacs is compiled with GTK+ support, the appearance of various graphical widgets, such as the menu-bar, scroll-bar, and dialog boxes, is determined by GTK+ resources, which we will also describe. When Emacs is built without GTK+ support, the appearance of these widgets is determined by additional X resources.

On MS-Windows, you can customize some of the same aspects using the system registry (see The MS-Windows System Registry).

D.1 X Resources

Programs running under the X Window System organize their user options under a hierarchy of classes and resources. You can specify default values for these options in your X resource file, usually named ~/.Xdefaults or ~/.Xresources. Changes in this file do not take effect immediately, because the X server stores its own list of resources; to update it, use the command xrdb—for instance, ‘xrdb ~/.Xdefaults’.

Settings specified via X resources in general override the equivalent settings in Emacs init files (see The Emacs Initialization File), in particular for parameters of the initial frame (see Frame Parameters).

(MS-Windows systems do not support X resource files; on such systems, Emacs looks for X resources in the Windows Registry, first under the key ‘HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\GNU\Emacs’, which affects only the current user and override the system-wide settings, and then under the key ‘HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\GNU\Emacs’, which affects all users of the system. The menu and scroll bars are native widgets on MS-Windows, so they are only customizable via the system-wide settings in the Display Control Panel. You can also set resources using the ‘-xrm’ command line option, as explained below.)

Each line in the X resource file specifies a value for one option or for a collection of related options. The order in which the lines appear in the file does not matter. Each resource specification consists of a program name and a resource name. Case distinctions are significant in each of these names. Here is an example:

emacs.cursorColor: dark green

The program name is the name of the executable file to which the resource applies. For Emacs, this is normally ‘emacs’. To specify a definition that applies to all instances of Emacs, regardless of the name of the Emacs executable, use ‘Emacs’.

The resource name is the name of a program setting. For instance, Emacs recognizes a ‘cursorColor’ resource that controls the color of the text cursor.

Resources are grouped into named classes. For instance, the ‘Foreground’ class contains the ‘cursorColor’, ‘foreground’ and ‘pointerColor’ resources (see Table of X Resources for Emacs). Instead of using a resource name, you can use a class name to specify the default value for all resources in that class, like this:

emacs.Foreground: dark green

Emacs does not process X resources at all if you set the variable inhibit-x-resources to a non-nil value. If you invoke Emacs with the ‘-Q’ (or ‘--quick’) command-line option, inhibit-x-resources is automatically set to t (see Initial Options).

In addition, you can use the following command-line options to override the X resources file:

‘-name name’

‘--name=name’

This option sets the program name of the initial Emacs frame to name. It also sets the title of the initial frame to name. This option does not affect subsequent frames.

If you don’t specify this option, the default is to use the Emacs executable’s name as the program name.

For consistency, ‘-name’ also specifies the name to use for other resource values that do not belong to any particular frame.

The resources that name Emacs invocations also belong to a class, named ‘Emacs’. If you write ‘Emacs’ instead of ‘emacs’, the resource applies to all frames in all Emacs jobs, regardless of frame titles and regardless of the name of the executable file.

‘-xrm resource-value’

‘--xrm=resource-value’

This option specifies X resource values for the present Emacs job.

resource-value should have the same format that you would use inside a file of X resources. Several ‘-xrm’ options are possible to include multiple resource specifications. You can also use ‘#include "filename"’ as resource-value to include a file full of resource specifications. Resource values specified with ‘-xrm’ take precedence over all other resource specifications.

D.2 Table of X Resources for Emacs

The table below lists the X resource names that Emacs recognizes. Note that some of the resources have no effect in Emacs compiled with various X toolkits (GTK+, Lucid, etc.)—we indicate below when this is the case.

alpha (class Alpha)

Sets the ‘alpha’ frame parameter, determining frame transparency (see Frame Parameters in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

alphaBackground (class AlphaBackground)

Sets the ‘alpha-background’ frame parameter, determining background transparency (see Frame Parameters in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

).

background (class Background)

Background color (see Colors for Faces).

bitmapIcon (class BitmapIcon)

Tell the window manager to display the Emacs icon if ‘on’; don’t do so if ‘off’. See Icons, for a description of the icon.

borderColor (class BorderColor)

Color of the frame’s external border. This has no effect if Emacs is compiled with GTK+ support.

borderWidth (class BorderWidth)

Width of the frame’s external border, in pixels. This has no effect if Emacs is compiled with GTK+ support.

cursorBlink (class CursorBlink)

If the value of this resource is ‘off’ or ‘false’ or ‘0’ at startup, Emacs disables Blink Cursor mode (see Displaying the Cursor).

cursorColor (class Foreground)

Text cursor color. If this resource is specified when Emacs starts up, Emacs sets its value as the background color of the cursor face (see Text Faces).

font (class Font)

Font name for the default face (see Fonts). You can also specify a fontset name (see Fontsets).

fontBackend (class FontBackend)

Comma-delimited list of backend(s) to use for drawing fonts, in order of precedence. For instance, the value ‘x,xft’ tells Emacs to draw fonts using the X core font driver, falling back on the Xft font driver if that fails. Normally, you should leave this resource unset, in which case Emacs tries using all available font backends.

foreground (class Foreground)

Default foreground color for text.

fullscreen (class Fullscreen)

The desired fullscreen size. The value can be one of fullboth, maximized, fullwidth or fullheight, which correspond to the command-line options ‘-fs’, ‘-mm’, ‘-fw’, and ‘-fh’ (see Options for Window Size and Position). Note that this applies to the initial frame only.

geometry (class Geometry)

Window size and position. The value should be a size and position specification, of the same form as in the ‘-g’ or ‘--geometry’ command-line option (see Options for Window Size and Position).

The size applies to all frames in the Emacs session, but the position applies only to the initial Emacs frame (or, in the case of a resource for a specific frame name, only that frame).

Be careful not to specify this resource as ‘emacs*geometry’, as that may affect individual menus as well as the main Emacs frame.

horizontalScrollBars (class ScrollBars)

If the value of this resource is ‘off’ or ‘false’ or ‘0’, Emacs disables Horizontal Scroll Bar mode at startup (see Scroll Bars).

iconName (class Title)

Name to display in the icon.

internalBorder (class BorderWidth)

Width of the internal frame border, in pixels.

lineSpacing (class LineSpacing)

Additional space between lines, in pixels.

menuBackground (class Background)

The background color of the menus in non-toolkit versions of Emacs. (For toolkit versions, see Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources, also see Motif Menu X Resources, and see GTK+ resources.)

menuBar (class MenuBar)

If the value of this resource is ‘off’ or ‘false’ or ‘0’, Emacs disables Menu Bar mode at startup (see Menu Bars).

minibuffer (class Minibuffer)

If ‘none’, Emacs will not make a minibuffer in this frame; it will use a separate minibuffer frame instead.

paneFont (class Font)

Font name for menu pane titles, in non-toolkit versions of Emacs. (For toolkit versions, see Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources, also see Motif Menu X Resources, and see GTK+ resources.)

paneForeground (class Foreground)

Foreground color for menu pane titles, in non-toolkit versions of Emacs. (For toolkit versions, see Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources, also see Motif Menu X Resources, and see GTK+ resources.)

pointerColor (class Foreground)

Color of the mouse cursor. This has no effect in many graphical desktop environments, as they do not let Emacs change the mouse cursor this way.

privateColormap (class PrivateColormap)

If ‘on’, use a private color map, in the case where the default visual of class PseudoColor and Emacs is using it.

reverseVideo (class ReverseVideo)

Switch foreground and background default colors if ‘on’, use colors as specified if ‘off’.

screenGamma (class ScreenGamma)

Gamma correction for colors, equivalent to the frame parameter screen-gamma.

scrollBar (class ScrollBar)

If the value of this resource is ‘off’ or ‘false’ or ‘0’, Emacs disables Scroll Bar mode at startup (see Scroll Bars).

scrollBarWidth (class ScrollBarWidth)

The scroll bar width in pixels, equivalent to the frame parameter scroll-bar-width. Do not set this resource if Emacs is compiled with GTK+ support.

selectionFont (class SelectionFont)

Font name for pop-up menu items, in non-toolkit versions of Emacs. (For toolkit versions, see Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources, also see Motif Menu X Resources, and see GTK+ resources.)

selectionForeground (class SelectionForeground)

Foreground color for pop-up menu items, in non-toolkit versions of Emacs. (For toolkit versions, see Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources, also see Motif Menu X Resources, and see GTK+ resources.)

selectionTimeout (class SelectionTimeout)

Number of milliseconds to wait for a selection reply. If the selection owner doesn’t reply in this time, we give up. A value of 0 means wait as long as necessary.

synchronous (class Synchronous)

Run Emacs in synchronous mode if ‘on’. Synchronous mode is useful for debugging X problems.

title (class Title)

Name to display in the title bar of the initial Emacs frame.

toolBar (class ToolBar)

If the value of this resource is ‘off’ or ‘false’ or ‘0’, Emacs disables Tool Bar mode at startup (see Tool Bars).

tabBar (class TabBar)

If the value of this resource is ‘on’ or ‘yes’ or ‘1’, Emacs enables Tab Bar mode at startup (see Tab Bars).

useXIM (class UseXIM)

Disable use of X input methods (XIM) if ‘false’ or ‘off’. This is only relevant if your Emacs is built with XIM support. It might be useful to turn off XIM on slow X client/server links.

inputStyle (class InputStyle)

This resource controls how preview text generated by X input methods is displayed. Its value can be on of the following:

‘callback’

Display the contents of the preview text in the current buffer.

‘offthespot’

Display the preview text inside a separate area of the display provided by Emacs.

‘overthespot’

Display the preview text inside a popup window at the location of point in the current window.

‘none’

Let the input method decide how to display itself. This is usually equivalent to ‘overthespot’, but it might work with more input methods.

‘native’

Use the toolkit for handling input methods. This is currently implemented only on GTK.

‘root’

Use some location on display specific to the input method for displaying the preview text.

synchronizeResize (class SynchronizeResize)

If ‘off’ or ‘false’, Emacs will not try to tell the window manager when it has finished redrawing the display in response to a frame being resized. Otherwise, the window manager will postpone drawing a frame that was just resized until its contents are updated, which prevents blank areas of a frame that have not yet been painted from being displayed. If set to ‘extended’, it will enable use of an alternative frame synchronization protocol, which might be supported by some compositing window managers that don’t support the protocol Emacs uses by default, and causes Emacs to synchronize display with the monitor refresh rate when a compatible compositing window manager is in use.

verticalScrollBars (class ScrollBars)

Give frames scroll bars on the left if ‘left’, on the right if ‘right’; don’t have scroll bars if ‘off’ (see Scroll Bars).

visualClass (class VisualClass)

The visual class for X color display. If specified, the value should start with one of ‘TrueColor’, ‘PseudoColor’, ‘DirectColor’, ‘StaticColor’, ‘GrayScale’, and ‘StaticGray’, followed by ‘-depth’, where depth is the number of color planes.

You can also use X resources to customize individual Emacs faces (see Text Faces). For example, setting the resource ‘face.attributeForeground’ is equivalent to customizing the ‘foreground’ attribute of the face face. However, we recommend customizing faces from within Emacs, instead of using X resources. See Customizing Faces.

D.3 Lucid Menu And Dialog X Resources

If Emacs is compiled with the X toolkit support using Lucid widgets, you can use X resources to customize the appearance of the menu bar (see The Menu Bar), pop-up menus, and dialog boxes (see Using Dialog Boxes). The resources for the menu bar fall in the ‘pane.menubar’ class (following, as always, either the name of the Emacs executable or ‘Emacs’ for all Emacs invocations). The resources for the pop-up menu are in the ‘menu*’ class. The resources for dialog boxes are in the ‘dialog*’ class.

For example, to display menu bar entries with the ‘Courier-12’ font (see Fonts), write this:

Emacs.pane.menubar.font: Courier-12

Lucid widgets can display multilingual text in your locale. To enable this, specify a fontSet resource instead of a font resource. See Fontsets. If both font and fontSet resources are specified, the fontSet resource is used.

Here is a list of resources for menu bars, pop-up menus, and dialogs:

font

Font for menu item text.

fontSet

Fontset for menu item text.

background

Background color.

buttonForeground

Foreground color for a selected item.

foreground

Foreground color.

disabledForeground

Foreground color for a disabled menu item.

highlightForeground

Foreground color for a menu item highlighted by the mouse or key navigation.

highlightBackground

Background color for a menu item highlighted by the mouse or key navigation.

horizontalSpacing

Horizontal spacing in pixels between items. Default is 3.

verticalSpacing

Vertical spacing in pixels between items. Default is 2.

arrowSpacing

Horizontal spacing between the arrow (which indicates a submenu) and the associated text. Default is 10.

shadowThickness

Thickness of shadow lines for 3D buttons, arrows, and other graphical elements. Default is 1.

borderThickness

Thickness of the external borders of the menu bars and pop-up menus. Default is 1.

cursor

Name of the cursor to use in the menu bars and pop-up menus. Default is "right_ptr".

margin

Margin of the menu bar, in characters. Default is 1.

D.4 Motif Menu X Resources

If Emacs is compiled with the X toolkit support using Motif or LessTif widgets, you can use X resources to customize the appearance of the menu bar (see The Menu Bar), pop-up menus, and dialog boxes (see Using Dialog Boxes). However, the resources are organized differently from Lucid widgets.

The resource names for the menu bar are in the ‘pane.menubar’ class, and they must be specified in this form:

Emacs.pane.menubar.subwidget.resource: value

For pop-up menus, the resources are in the ‘menu*’ class, instead of ‘pane.menubar’. For dialog boxes, they are in ‘dialog’. In each case, each individual menu string is a subwidget; the subwidget’s name is the same as the menu item string. For example, the ‘File’ menu in the menu bar is a subwidget named ‘emacs.pane.menubar.File’.

Typically, you want to specify the same resources for the whole menu bar. To do this, use ‘*’ instead of a specific subwidget name. For example, to specify the font ‘8x16’ for all menu bar items, including submenus, write this:

Emacs.pane.menubar.*.fontList: 8x16

Each item in a submenu also has its own name for X resources; for example, the ‘File’ submenu has an item named ‘Save (current buffer)’. A resource specification for a submenu item looks like this:

Emacs.pane.menubar.popup_*.menu.item.resource: value

For example, here’s how to specify the font for the ‘Save (current buffer)’ item:

Emacs.pane.menubar.popup_*.File.Save (current buffer).fontList: 8x16

For an item in a second-level submenu, such as ‘Complete Word’ under ‘Spell Checking’ under ‘Tools’, the resource fits this template:

Emacs.pane.menubar.popup_*.popup_*.menu.resource: value

For example,

Emacs.pane.menubar.popup_*.popup_*.Spell Checking.Complete Word: value

(This should be one long line.)

If you want the submenu items to look different from the menu bar itself, you must first specify the resource for all of them, then override the value for submenus alone. Here is an example:

Emacs.pane.menubar.*.fontList: 9x18
Emacs.pane.menubar.popup_*.fontList: 8x16

To specify resources for the LessTif file-selection box, use ‘fsb*’, like this:

Emacs.fsb*.fontList: 8x16

Here is a list of resources for LessTif menu bars and pop-up menus:

armColor

The color to show in an armed button.

fontList

The font to use.

marginBottom
marginHeight
marginLeft
marginRight
marginTop
marginWidth

Amount of space to leave around the item, within the border.

borderWidth

The width of the border around the menu item, on all sides.

shadowThickness

The width of the border shadow.

bottomShadowColor

The color for the border shadow, on the bottom and the right.

topShadowColor

The color for the border shadow, on the top and the left.

D.5 GTK+ resources

If Emacs is compiled with GTK+ toolkit support, the simplest way to customize its GTK+ widgets (e.g., menus, dialogs, tool bars and scroll bars) is to choose an appropriate GTK+ theme, for example with the GNOME theme selector.

In GTK+ version 2, you can also use GTK+ resources to customize the appearance of GTK+ widgets used by Emacs. These resources are specified in either the file ~/.emacs.d/gtkrc (for Emacs-specific GTK+ resources), or ~/.gtkrc-2.0 (for general GTK+ resources). We recommend using ~/.emacs.d/gtkrc, since GTK+ seems to ignore ~/.gtkrc-2.0 when running GConf with GNOME. Note, however, that some GTK+ themes may override customizations in ~/.emacs.d/gtkrc; there is nothing we can do about this. GTK+ resources do not affect aspects of Emacs unrelated to GTK+ widgets, such as fonts and colors in the main Emacs window; those are governed by normal X resources (see X Resources).

The following sections describe how to customize GTK+ resources for Emacs. For details about GTK+ resources, see the GTK+ API document at https://developer-old.gnome.org/gtk2/stable/gtk2-Resource-Files.html.

In GTK+ version 3, GTK+ resources have been replaced by a completely different system. The appearance of GTK+ widgets is now determined by CSS-like style files: gtk-3.0/gtk.css in the GTK+ installation directory, and ~/.themes/theme/gtk-3.0/gtk.css for local style settings (where theme is the name of the current GTK+ theme). Therefore, the description of GTK+ resources in this section does not apply to GTK+ 3. For details about the GTK+ 3 styling system, see https://developer-old.gnome.org/gtk3/3.0/GtkCssProvider.html.

D.5.1 GTK+ Resource Basics

In a GTK+ 2 resource file (usually ~/.emacs.d/gtkrc), the simplest kind of a resource setting simply assigns a value to a variable. For example, putting the following line in the resource file changes the font on all GTK+ widgets to ‘courier-12’:

gtk-font-name = "courier 12"

Note that in this case the font name must be supplied as a GTK font pattern (also called a Pango font name), not as a Fontconfig-style font name or XLFD. See Fonts.

To customize widgets you first define a style, and then apply the style to the widgets. Here is an example that sets the font for menus (‘#’ characters indicate comments):

# Define the style ‘my_style’.
style "my_style"
{
  font_name = "helvetica bold 14"
}

# Specify that widget type ‘*emacs-menuitem*’ uses ‘my_style’.
widget "*emacs-menuitem*" style "my_style"

The widget name in this example contains wildcards, so the style is applied to all widgets matching ‘*emacs-menuitem*’. The widgets are named by the way they are contained, from the outer widget to the inner widget. Here is another example that applies ‘my_style’ specifically to the Emacs menu bar:

widget "Emacs.pane.menubar.*" style "my_style"

Here is a more elaborate example, showing how to change the parts of the scroll bar:

style "scroll"
{
  fg[NORMAL] = "red"     # Arrow color.
  bg[NORMAL] = "yellow"  # Thumb and background around arrow.
  bg[ACTIVE] = "blue"    # Trough color.
  bg[PRELIGHT] = "white" # Thumb color when the mouse is over it.
}

widget "*verticalScrollBar*" style "scroll"

D.5.2 GTK+ widget names

A GTK+ widget is specified by a widget name and a widget class. The widget name refers to a specific widget (e.g., ‘emacs-menuitem’), while the widget class refers to a collection of similar widgets (e.g., ‘GtkMenuItem’). A widget always has a class, but need not have a name.

Absolute names are sequences of widget names or widget classes, corresponding to hierarchies of widgets embedded within other widgets. For example, if a GtkWindow named top contains a GtkVBox named box, which in turn contains a GtkMenuBar called menubar, the absolute class name of the menu-bar widget is GtkWindow.GtkVBox.GtkMenuBar, and its absolute widget name is top.box.menubar.

GTK+ resource files can contain two types of commands for specifying widget appearances:

widget

specifies a style for widgets based on the class name, or just the class.

widget_class

specifies a style for widgets based on the class name.

See the previous subsection for examples of using the widget command; the widget_class command is used similarly. Note that the widget name/class and the style must be enclosed in double-quotes, and these commands must be at the top level in the GTK+ resource file.

As previously noted, you may specify a widget name or class with shell wildcard syntax: ‘*’ matches zero or more characters and ‘?’ matches one character. This example assigns a style to all widgets:

widget "*" style "my_style"

D.5.3 GTK+ Widget Names in Emacs

The GTK+ widgets used by an Emacs frame are listed below:

Emacs (class GtkWindow)

pane (class GtkVBox)

menubar (class GtkMenuBar)

[menu item widgets]

[unnamed widget] (class GtkHandleBox)

emacs-toolbar (class GtkToolbar)

[tool bar item widgets]

emacs (class GtkFixed)

verticalScrollBar (class GtkVScrollbar)

The contents of Emacs windows are drawn in the emacs widget. Note that even if there are multiple Emacs windows, each scroll bar widget is named verticalScrollBar.

For example, here are two different ways to set the menu bar style:

widget "Emacs.pane.menubar.*" style "my_style"
widget_class "GtkWindow.GtkVBox.GtkMenuBar.*" style "my_style"

For GTK+ dialogs, Emacs uses a widget named emacs-dialog, of class GtkDialog. For file selection, Emacs uses a widget named emacs-filedialog, of class GtkFileSelection.

Because the widgets for pop-up menus and dialogs are free-standing windows and not contained in the Emacs widget, their GTK+ absolute names do not start with ‘Emacs’. To customize these widgets, use wildcards like this:

widget "*emacs-dialog*" style "my_dialog_style"
widget "*emacs-filedialog* style "my_file_style"
widget "*emacs-menuitem* style "my_menu_style"

If you want to apply a style to all menus in Emacs, use this:

widget_class "*Menu*" style "my_menu_style"

D.5.4 GTK+ styles

Here is an example of two GTK+ style declarations:

pixmap_path "/usr/share/pixmaps:/usr/include/X11/pixmaps"

style "default"
{
  font_name = "helvetica 12"

  bg[NORMAL] = { 0.83, 0.80, 0.73 }
  bg[SELECTED] = { 0.0, 0.55, 0.55 }
  bg[INSENSITIVE] = { 0.77, 0.77, 0.66 }
  bg[ACTIVE] = { 0.0, 0.55, 0.55 }
  bg[PRELIGHT] = { 0.0, 0.55, 0.55 }

  fg[NORMAL] = "black"
  fg[SELECTED] = { 0.9, 0.9, 0.9 }
  fg[ACTIVE] = "black"
  fg[PRELIGHT] = { 0.9, 0.9, 0.9 }

  base[INSENSITIVE] = "#777766"
  text[INSENSITIVE] = { 0.60, 0.65, 0.57 }

  bg_pixmap[NORMAL] = "background.xpm"
  bg_pixmap[INSENSITIVE] = "background.xpm"
  bg_pixmap[ACTIVE] = "background.xpm"
  bg_pixmap[PRELIGHT] = "<none>"

}

style "ruler" = "default"
{
  font_name = "helvetica 8"
}

The style ‘ruler’ inherits from ‘default’. This way you can build on existing styles. The syntax for fonts and colors is described below.

As this example shows, it is possible to specify several values for foreground and background depending on the widget’s state. The possible states are:

NORMAL

This is the default state for widgets.

ACTIVE

This is the state for a widget that is ready to do something. It is also for the trough of a scroll bar, i.e., bg[ACTIVE] = "red" sets the scroll bar trough to red. Buttons that have been armed (pressed but not released yet) are in this state.

PRELIGHT

This is the state for a widget that can be manipulated, when the mouse pointer is over it—for example when the mouse is over the thumb in the scroll bar or over a menu item. When the mouse is over a button that is not pressed, the button is in this state.

SELECTED

This is the state for data that has been selected by the user. It can be selected text or items selected in a list. This state is not used in Emacs.

INSENSITIVE

This is the state for widgets that are visible, but they cannot be manipulated in the usual way—for example, buttons that can’t be pressed, and disabled menu items. To display disabled menu items in yellow, use fg[INSENSITIVE] = "yellow".

Here are the things that can go in a style declaration:

bg[state] = color

This specifies the background color for the widget. Note that editable text doesn’t use bg; it uses base instead.

base[state] = color

This specifies the background color for editable text. In Emacs, this color is used for the background of the text fields in the file dialog.

bg_pixmap[state] = "pixmap"

This specifies an image background (instead of a background color). pixmap should be the image file name. GTK+ can use a number of image file formats, including XPM, XBM, GIF, JPEG and PNG. If you want a widget to use the same image as its parent, use ‘<parent>’. If you don’t want any image, use ‘<none>’. ‘<none>’ is the way to cancel a background image inherited from a parent style.

You can’t specify the file by its absolute file name. GTK+ looks for the pixmap file in directories specified in pixmap_path. pixmap_path is a colon-separated list of directories within double quotes, specified at the top level in a gtkrc file (i.e., not inside a style definition; see example above):

pixmap_path "/usr/share/pixmaps:/usr/include/X11/pixmaps"

fg[state] = color

This specifies the foreground color for widgets to use. It is the color of text in menus and buttons, and the color for the arrows in the scroll bar. For editable text, use text.

text[state] = color

This is the color for editable text. In Emacs, this color is used for the text fields in the file dialog.

font_name = "font"

This specifies the font for text in the widget. font is a GTK-style (or Pango) font name, like ‘Sans Italic 10’. See Fonts. The names are case insensitive.

There are three ways to specify a color: a color name, an RGB triplet, or a GTK-style RGB triplet. See Colors for Faces, for a description of color names and RGB triplets. Color names should be enclosed with double quotes, e.g., ‘"red"’. RGB triplets should be written without double quotes, e.g., ‘#ff0000’. GTK-style RGB triplets have the form { r, g, b } , where r, g and b are either integers in the range 0–65535 or floats in the range 0.0–1.0.

Glossary

Abbrev

An abbrev is a text string that expands into a different text string when present in the buffer. For example, you might define a few letters as an abbrev for a long phrase that you want to insert frequently. See Abbrevs.

Aborting

Aborting means getting out of a recursive edit (q.v.). The commands C-] and M-x top-level are used for this. See Quitting and Aborting.

Active Region

Setting the mark (q.v.) at a position in the text also activates it. When the mark is active, we call the region an active region. See The Mark and the Region.

Alt

Alt is the name of a modifier bit that a keyboard input character may have. To make a character Alt, type it while holding down the Alt key. Such characters are given names that start with Alt- (usually written A- for short). (Note that many terminals have a key labeled Alt that is really a Meta key.) See Alt.

Argument

See Glossary---Numeric Argument.

ASCII character

An ASCII character is either an ASCII control character or an ASCII printing character. See Kinds of User Input.

ASCII control character

An ASCII control character is the Control version of an upper-case letter, or the Control version of one of the characters ‘@[\]^_?’.

ASCII printing character

ASCII letters, digits, space, and the following punctuation characters: ‘!@#$%^&*()_-+=|\~`{}[]:;"'<>,.?/’.

Auto Fill Mode

Auto Fill mode is a minor mode (q.v.) in which text that you insert is automatically broken into lines of a given maximum width. See Filling Text.

Auto Saving

Auto saving is the practice of periodically saving the contents of an Emacs buffer in a specially-named file, so that the information will be preserved if the buffer is lost due to a system error or user error. See Auto-Saving: Protection Against Disasters.

Autoloading

Emacs can automatically load Lisp libraries when a Lisp program requests a function from those libraries. This is called “autoloading”. See Libraries of Lisp Code for Emacs.

Backtrace

A backtrace is a trace of a series of function calls showing how a program arrived at a certain point. It is used mainly for finding and correcting bugs (q.v.). Emacs can display a backtrace when it signals an error or when you type C-g (see Glossary---Quitting). See Checklist for Bug Reports.

Backup File

A backup file records the contents that a file had before the current editing session. Emacs makes backup files automatically to help you track down or cancel changes you later regret making. See Backup Files.

Balancing Parentheses

Emacs can balance parentheses (or other matching delimiters) either manually or automatically. You do manual balancing with the commands to move over parenthetical groupings (see Moving in the Parenthesis Structure). Automatic balancing works by blinking or highlighting the delimiter that matches the one you just inserted, or inserting the matching delimiter for you (see Matching Parens).

Balanced Expressions

A balanced expression is a syntactically recognizable expression, such as a symbol (q.v.), number, string constant, block, or parenthesized expression in C. See Balanced Expressions.

Balloon Help

See Glossary---Tooltips.

Base Buffer

A base buffer is a buffer whose text is shared by an indirect buffer (q.v.).

Bidirectional Text

Some human languages, such as English, are written from left to right. Others, such as Arabic, are written from right to left. Emacs supports both of these forms, as well as any mixture of them—this is “bidirectional text”. See Bidirectional Editing.

Bind

To bind a key sequence means to give it a binding (q.v.). See Changing Key Bindings Interactively.

Binding

A key sequence gets its meaning in Emacs by having a binding, which is a command (q.v.)—a Lisp function that is run when you type that sequence. See Binding. Customization often involves rebinding a character to a different command function. The bindings of all key sequences are recorded in the keymaps (q.v.). See Keymaps.

Blank Lines

Blank lines are lines that contain only whitespace. Emacs has several commands for operating on the blank lines in the buffer. See Blank Lines.

Bookmark

Bookmarks are akin to registers (q.v.) in that they record positions in buffers to which you can return later. Unlike registers, bookmarks persist between Emacs sessions. See Bookmarks.

Border

A border is a thin space along the edge of the frame, used just for spacing, not for displaying anything. An Emacs frame has an ordinary external border, outside of everything including the menu bar, plus an internal border that surrounds the text windows, their scroll bars and fringes, and separates them from the menu bar and tool bar. You can customize both borders with options and resources (see Internal and Outer Borders). Borders are not the same as fringes (q.v.).

Buffer

The buffer is the basic editing unit; one buffer corresponds to one text being edited. You normally have several buffers, but at any time you are editing only one, the current buffer, though several can be visible when you are using multiple windows or frames (q.v.). Most buffers are visiting (q.v.) some file. See Using Multiple Buffers.

Buffer Selection History

Emacs keeps a buffer selection history that records how recently each Emacs buffer has been selected. This is used for choosing which buffer to select. See Using Multiple Buffers.

Bug

A bug is an incorrect or unreasonable behavior of a program, or inaccurate or confusing documentation. Emacs developers treat bug reports, both in Emacs code and its documentation, very seriously and ask you to report any bugs you find. See Reporting Bugs.

Button Down Event

A button down event is the kind of input event (q.v.) generated right away when you press down on a mouse button. See Rebinding Mouse Buttons.

By Default

See Glossary---Default.

Byte Compilation

See Glossary---Compilation.

cf.
c.f.

Short for “confer” in Latin, which means “compare with” or “compare to”. The second variant, “c.f.”, is a widespread misspelling.

C-

C- in the name of a character is an abbreviation for Control. See C-.

C-M-

C-M- in the name of a character is an abbreviation for Control-Meta. If your terminal lacks a real Meta key, you type a Control-Meta character by typing ESC and then typing the corresponding Control character. See C-M-.

Case Conversion

Case conversion means changing text from upper case to lower case or vice versa. See Case Conversion Commands.

Case Folding

Case folding means ignoring the differences between case variants of the same letter: upper-case, lower-case, and title-case. Emacs performs case folding by default in text search. See Lax Matching During Searching.

Character

Characters form the contents of an Emacs buffer. Also, key sequences (q.v.) are usually made up of characters (though they may include other input events as well). See Kinds of User Input.

Character Folding

Character folding means ignoring differences between similarly looking characters, such as between a, and ä and á. Emacs performs character folding by default in text search. See Lax Matching During Searching.

Character Set

Emacs supports a number of character sets, each of which represents a particular alphabet or script. See International Character Set Support.

Character Terminal

See Glossary---Text Terminal.

Click Event

A click event is the kind of input event (q.v.) generated when you press a mouse button and release it without moving the mouse. See Rebinding Mouse Buttons.

Client

See Glossary---Server.

Clipboard

A clipboard is a buffer provided by the window system for transferring text between applications. On the X Window System, the clipboard is provided in addition to the primary selection (q.v.); on MS-Windows and Mac, the clipboard is used instead of the primary selection. See Using the Clipboard.

Coding System

A coding system is a way to encode text characters in a file or in a stream of information. Emacs has the ability to convert text to or from a variety of coding systems when reading or writing it. See Coding Systems.

Command

A command is a Lisp function specially defined to be able to serve as a key binding in Emacs or to be invoked by its name (see Glossary---Command Name). (Another term for command is interactive function—they are used interchangeably.) When you type a key sequence (q.v.), its binding (q.v.) is looked up in the relevant keymaps (q.v.) to find the command to run. See Keys and Commands.

Command History

See Glossary---Minibuffer History.

Command Name

A command name is the name of a Lisp symbol (q.v.) that is a command (see Keys and Commands). You can invoke any command by its name using M-x (see Running Commands by Name).

Comment

A comment is text in a program which is intended only for humans reading the program, and which is specially marked so that it will be ignored when the program is loaded or compiled. Emacs offers special commands for creating, aligning and killing comments. See Manipulating Comments.

Common Lisp

Common Lisp is a dialect of Lisp (q.v.) much larger and more powerful than Emacs Lisp. Emacs provides a subset of Common Lisp in the CL package. See Overview in

Common Lisp Extensions

.

Compilation

Compilation is the process of creating an executable program from source code. Emacs has commands for compiling files of Emacs Lisp code (see Byte Compilation in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

) and programs in C and other languages (see Running Compilations under Emacs). Byte-compiled Emacs Lisp code loads and executes faster.

Complete Key

A complete key is a key sequence that fully specifies one action to be performed by Emacs. For example, X and C-f and C-x m are complete keys. Complete keys derive their meanings from being bound (see Glossary---Bind) to commands (q.v.). Thus, X is conventionally bound to a command to insert ‘X’ in the buffer; C-x m is conventionally bound to a command to begin composing a mail message. See Keys.

Completion

Completion is what Emacs does when it automatically expands an abbreviation for a name into the entire name. Completion is done for minibuffer (q.v.) arguments when the set of possible valid inputs is known; for example, on command names, buffer names, and file names. Completion usually occurs when TAB, SPC or RET is typed. See Completion.

Continuation Line

When a line of text is longer than the width of the window, it normally takes up more than one screen line when displayed (but see Glossary---Truncation). We say that the text line is continued, and all screen lines used for it after the first are called continuation lines. See Continuation Lines. A related Emacs feature is filling (q.v.).

Control Character

A control character is a character that you type by holding down the Ctrl key. Some control characters also have their own keys, so that you can type them without using Ctrl. For example, RET, TAB, ESC and DEL are all control characters. See Kinds of User Input.

Copyleft

A copyleft is a notice giving the public legal permission to redistribute and modify a program or other work of art, but requiring modified versions to carry similar permission. Copyright is normally used to keep users divided and helpless; with copyleft we turn that around to empower users and encourage them to cooperate.

The particular form of copyleft used by the GNU project is called the GNU General Public License. See GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE.

Ctrl

The Ctrl or control key is what you hold down in order to enter a control character (q.v.). See Glossary---C-.

Current Buffer

The current buffer in Emacs is the Emacs buffer on which most editing commands operate. You can select any Emacs buffer as the current one. See Using Multiple Buffers.

Current Line

The current line is the line that point is on (see Point).

Current Paragraph

The current paragraph is the paragraph that point is in. If point is between two paragraphs, the current paragraph is the one that follows point. See Paragraphs.

Current Defun

The current defun is the defun (q.v.) that point is in. If point is between defuns, the current defun is the one that follows point. See Top-Level Definitions, or Defuns.

Cursor

The cursor is the rectangle on the screen which indicates the position (called point; q.v.) at which insertion and deletion takes place. The cursor is on or under the character that follows point. Often people speak of “the cursor” when, strictly speaking, they mean “point”. See Cursor.

Customization

Customization is making minor changes in the way Emacs works, to reflect your preferences or needs. It is often done by setting variables (see Variables) or faces (see Customizing Faces), or by rebinding key sequences (see Keymaps).

Cut and Paste

See Glossary---Killing, and Glossary---Yanking.

Daemon

A daemon is a standard term for a system-level process that runs in the background. Daemons are often started when the system first starts up. When Emacs runs in daemon-mode, it does not open a display. You connect to it with the emacsclient program. See Using Emacs as a Server.

Default Argument

The default for an argument is the value that will be assumed if you do not specify one. When the minibuffer is used to read an argument, the default argument is used if you just type RET. See The Minibuffer.

Default

A default is the value that is used for a certain purpose when you do not explicitly specify a value to use.

Default Directory

When you specify a file name that does not start with ‘/’ or ‘~’, it is interpreted relative to the current buffer’s default directory. (On MS systems, file names that start with a drive letter ‘x:’ are treated as absolute, not relative.) See Default Directory.

Defun

A defun is a major definition at the top level in a program. The name “defun” comes from Lisp, where most such definitions use the construct defun. See Top-Level Definitions, or Defuns.

DEL

DEL is a character that runs the command to delete one character of text before the cursor. It is typically either the Delete key or the BACKSPACE key, whichever one is easy to type. See DEL.

Deletion

Deletion means erasing text without copying it into the kill ring (q.v.). The alternative is killing (q.v.). See Deletion.

Deletion of Files

Deleting a file means erasing it from the file system. (Note that some systems use the concept of a trash can, or recycle bin, to allow you to undelete files.) See Miscellaneous File Operations.

Deletion of Messages

Deleting a message (in Rmail, and other mail clients) means flagging it to be eliminated from your mail file. Until you expunge (q.v.) the Rmail file, you can still undelete the messages you have deleted. See Deleting Messages.

Deletion of Windows

Deleting a window means eliminating it from the screen. Other windows expand to use up the space. The text that was in the window is not lost, and you can create a new window with the same dimensions as the old if you wish. See Multiple Windows.

Directory

File directories are named collections in the file system, within which you can place individual files or subdirectories. They are sometimes referred to as “folders”. See File Directories.

Directory Local Variable

A directory local variable is a local variable (q.v.) that applies to all the files within a certain directory. See Per-Directory Local Variables.

Directory Name

On GNU and other Unix-like systems, directory names are strings that end in ‘/’. For example, /no-such-dir/ is a directory name whereas /tmp is not, even though /tmp names a file that happens to be a directory. On MS-Windows the relationship is more complicated. See Directory Names in

the Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

Dired

Dired is the Emacs facility that displays the contents of a file directory and allows you to “edit the directory”, performing operations on the files in the directory. See Dired, the Directory Editor.

Disabled Command

A disabled command is one that you may not run without special confirmation. The usual reason for disabling a command is that it is confusing for beginning users. See Disabling Commands.

Down Event

Short for “button down event” (q.v.).

Drag Event

A drag event is the kind of input event (q.v.) generated when you press a mouse button, move the mouse, and then release the button. See Rebinding Mouse Buttons.

Dribble File

A dribble file is a file into which Emacs writes all the characters that you type on the keyboard. Dribble files can be used to make a record for debugging Emacs bugs. Emacs does not make a dribble file unless you tell it to. See Reporting Bugs.

e.g.

Short for “exempli gratia” in Latin, which means “for example”.

Echo Area

The echo area is the bottom line of the screen, used for echoing the arguments to commands, for asking questions, and showing brief messages (including error messages). The messages are stored in the buffer *Messages* so you can review them later. See The Echo Area.

Echoing

Echoing is acknowledging the receipt of input events by displaying them (in the echo area). Emacs never echoes single-character key sequences; longer key sequences echo only if you pause while typing them.

Electric

We say that a character is electric if it is normally self-inserting (q.v.), but the current major mode (q.v.) redefines it to do something else as well. For example, some programming language major modes define particular delimiter characters to reindent the line, or insert one or more newlines in addition to self-insertion.

End Of Line

End of line is a character or a sequence of characters that indicate the end of a text line. On GNU and Unix systems, this is a newline (q.v.), but other systems have other conventions. See end-of-line. Emacs can recognize several end-of-line conventions in files and convert between them.

Environment Variable

An environment variable is one of a collection of variables stored by the operating system, each one having a name and a value. Emacs can access environment variables set by its parent shell, and it can set variables in the environment it passes to programs it invokes. See Environment Variables.

EOL

See Glossary---End Of Line.

Error

An error occurs when an Emacs command cannot execute in the current circumstances. When an error occurs, execution of the command stops (unless the command has been programmed to do otherwise) and Emacs reports the error by displaying an error message (q.v.).

Error Message

An error message is output displayed by Emacs when you ask it to do something impossible (such as, killing text forward when point is at the end of the buffer), or when a command malfunctions in some way. Such messages appear in the echo area, accompanied by a beep.

ESC

ESC is a character used as a prefix for typing Meta characters on keyboards lacking a Meta key. Unlike the Meta key (which, like the SHIFT key, is held down while another character is typed), you press the ESC key as you would press a letter key, and it applies to the next character you type.

etc.

Short for “et cetera” in Latin, which means “and so on”.

Expression

See Glossary---Balanced Expression.

Expunging

Expunging an Rmail, Gnus newsgroup, or Dired buffer is an operation that truly discards the messages or files you have previously flagged for deletion.

Face

A face is a style of displaying characters. It specifies attributes such as font family and size, foreground and background colors, underline and strike-through, background stipple, etc. Emacs provides features to associate specific faces with portions of buffer text, in order to display that text as specified by the face attributes. See Text Faces.

File Local Variable

A file local variable is a local variable (q.v.) specified in a given file. See Local Variables in Files, and Glossary---Directory Local Variable.

File Locking

Emacs uses file locking to notice when two different users start to edit one file at the same time. See Protection against Simultaneous Editing.

File Name

A file name is a name that refers to a file. File names may be relative or absolute; the meaning of a relative file name depends on the current directory, but an absolute file name refers to the same file regardless of which directory is current. On GNU and Unix systems, an absolute file name starts with a slash (the root directory) or with ‘~/’ or ‘~user/’ (a home directory). On MS-Windows/MS-DOS, an absolute file name can also start with a drive letter and a colon, e.g., ‘d:’.

Some people use the term “pathname” for file names, but we do not; we use the word “path” only in the term “search path” (q.v.).

File-Name Component

A file-name component names a file directly within a particular directory. On GNU and Unix systems, a file name is a sequence of file-name components, separated by slashes. For example, foo/bar is a file name containing two components, ‘foo’ and ‘bar’; it refers to the file named ‘bar’ in the directory named ‘foo’ in the current directory. MS-DOS/MS-Windows file names can also use backslashes to separate components, as in foo\bar.

Fill Prefix

The fill prefix is a string that should be expected at the beginning of each line when filling is done. It is not regarded as part of the text to be filled. See Filling Text.

Filling

Filling text means adjusting the position of line-breaks to shift text between consecutive lines, so that all the lines are approximately the same length. See Filling Text. Some other editors call this feature “line wrapping”.

Font Lock

Font Lock is a mode that highlights parts of buffer text in different faces, according to the syntax. Some other editors refer to this as “syntax highlighting”. For example, all comments (q.v.) might be colored red. See Font Lock mode.

Fontset

A fontset is a named collection of fonts. A fontset specification lists character sets and which font to use to display each of them. Fontsets make it easy to change several fonts at once by specifying the name of a fontset, rather than changing each font separately. See Fontsets.

Formfeed Character

See Glossary---Page.

Frame

A frame is a rectangular cluster of Emacs windows. Emacs starts out with one frame, but you can create more. You can subdivide each frame into Emacs windows (q.v.). When you are using a window system (q.v.), more than one frame can be visible at the same time. See Frames and Graphical Displays. Some other editors use the term “window” for this, but in Emacs a window means something else.

Free Software

Free software is software that gives you the freedom to share, study and modify it. Emacs is free software, part of the GNU project (q.v.), and distributed under a copyleft (q.v.) license called the GNU General Public License. See GNU GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE.

Free Software Foundation

The Free Software Foundation (FSF) is a charitable foundation dedicated to promoting the development of free software (q.v.). For more information, see the FSF website.

Fringe

On a graphical display (q.v.), there’s a narrow portion of the frame (q.v.) between the text area and the window’s border. These “fringes” are used to display symbols that provide information about the buffer text (see Window Fringes). Emacs displays the fringe using a special face (q.v.) called fringe. See fringe.

FSF

See Glossary---Free Software Foundation.

FTP

FTP is an acronym for File Transfer Protocol. This is one standard method for retrieving remote files (q.v.).

Function Key

A function key is a key on the keyboard that sends input but does not correspond to any character. See Rebinding Function Keys.

Global

Global means “independent of the current environment; in effect throughout Emacs”. It is the opposite of local (q.v.). Particular examples of the use of “global” appear below.

Global Abbrev

A global definition of an abbrev (q.v.) is effective in all major modes that do not have local (q.v.) definitions for the same abbrev. See Abbrevs.

Global Keymap

The global keymap (q.v.) contains key bindings that are in effect everywhere, except when overridden by local key bindings in a major mode’s local keymap (q.v.). See Keymaps.

Global Mark Ring

The global mark ring records the series of buffers you have recently set a mark (q.v.) in. In many cases you can use this to backtrack through buffers you have been editing, or in which you have found tags (see Glossary---Tags Table). See The Global Mark Ring.

Global Substitution

Global substitution means replacing each occurrence of one string by another string throughout a large amount of text. See Replacement Commands.

Global Variable

The global value of a variable (q.v.) takes effect in all buffers that do not have their own local (q.v.) values for the variable. See Variables.

GNU

GNU is a recursive acronym for GNU’s Not Unix, and it refers to a Unix-compatible operating system which is free software (q.v.). See The GNU Manifesto. GNU is normally used with Linux as the kernel since Linux works better than the GNU kernel. For more information, see the GNU website.

Graphic Character

Graphic characters are those assigned pictorial images rather than just names. All the non-Meta (q.v.) characters except for the Control (q.v.) characters are graphic characters. These include letters, digits, punctuation, and spaces; they do not include RET or ESC. In Emacs, typing a graphic character inserts that character (in ordinary editing modes). See Inserting Text.

Graphical Display

A graphical display is one that can display images and multiple fonts. Usually it also has a window system (q.v.).

Highlighting

Highlighting text means displaying it with a different foreground and/or background color to make it stand out from the rest of the text in the buffer.

Emacs uses highlighting in several ways. It highlights the region whenever it is active (see The Mark and the Region). Incremental search also highlights matches (see Incremental Search). See Glossary---Font Lock.

Hardcopy

Hardcopy means printed output. Emacs has various commands for printing the contents of Emacs buffers. See Printing Hard Copies.

HELP

HELP is the Emacs name for C-h or F1. You can type HELP at any time to ask what options you have, or to ask what a command does. See Help.

Help Echo

Help echo is a short message displayed in the echo area (q.v.) when the mouse pointer is located on portions of display that require some explanations. Emacs displays help echo for menu items, parts of the mode line, tool-bar buttons, etc. On graphical displays, the messages can be displayed as tooltips (q.v.). See Tooltips.

Home Directory

Your home directory contains your personal files. On a multi-user GNU or Unix system, each user has his or her own home directory. When you start a new login session, your home directory is the default directory in which to start. A standard shorthand for your home directory is ‘~’. Similarly, ‘~user’ represents the home directory of some other user.

Hook

A hook is a list of functions to be called on specific occasions, such as saving a buffer in a file, major mode activation, etc. By customizing the various hooks, you can modify Emacs’s behavior without changing any of its code. See Hooks.

Hyper

Hyper is the name of a modifier bit that a keyboard input character may have. To make a character Hyper, type it while holding down the Hyper key. Such characters are given names that start with Hyper- (usually written H- for short). See Modifier Keys.

i.e.

Short for “id est” in Latin, which means “that is”.

Iff

“Iff” means “if and only if”. This terminology comes from mathematics. Try to avoid using this term in documentation, since many are unfamiliar with it and mistake it for a typo.

Inbox

An inbox is a file in which mail is delivered by the operating system. Rmail transfers mail from inboxes to Rmail files in which the mail is then stored permanently or until explicitly deleted. See Rmail Files and Inboxes.

Incremental Search

Emacs provides an incremental search facility, whereby Emacs begins searching for a string as soon as you type the first character. As you type more characters, it refines the search. See Incremental Search.

Indentation

Indentation means blank space at the beginning of a line. Most programming languages have conventions for using indentation to illuminate the structure of the program, and Emacs has special commands to adjust indentation. See Indentation.

Indirect Buffer

An indirect buffer is a buffer that shares the text of another buffer, called its base buffer (q.v.). See Indirect Buffers.

Info

Info is the hypertext format used by the GNU project for writing documentation.

Input Event

An input event represents, within Emacs, one action taken by the user on the terminal. Input events include typing characters, typing function keys, pressing or releasing mouse buttons, and switching between Emacs frames. See Kinds of User Input.

Input Method

An input method is a system for entering non-ASCII text characters by typing sequences of ASCII characters (q.v.). See Input Methods.

Insertion

Insertion means adding text into the buffer, either from the keyboard or from some other place in Emacs.

Interactive Function

A different term for command (q.v.).

Interactive Invocation

A function can be called from Lisp code, or called as a user level command (via M-x, a key binding or a menu). In the latter case, the function is said to be called interactively.

Interlocking

See Glossary---File Locking.

Isearch

See Glossary---Incremental Search.

Justification

Justification means adding extra spaces within lines of text in order to adjust the position of the text edges. See Explicit Fill Commands.

Key Binding

See Glossary---Binding.

Keyboard Macro

Keyboard macros are a way of defining new Emacs commands from sequences of existing ones, with no need to write a Lisp program. You can use a macro to record a sequence of commands, then play them back as many times as you like. See Keyboard Macros.

Keyboard Shortcut

A keyboard shortcut is a key sequence (q.v.) that invokes a command. What some programs call “assigning a keyboard shortcut”, Emacs calls “binding a key sequence”. See Glossary---Binding.

Key Sequence

A key sequence (key, for short) is a sequence of input events (q.v.) that are meaningful as a single unit. If the key sequence is enough to specify one action, it is a complete key (q.v.); if it is not enough, it is a prefix key (q.v.). See Keys.

Keymap

The keymap is the data structure that records the bindings (q.v.) of key sequences to the commands that they run. For example, the global keymap binds the character C-n to the command function next-line. See Keymaps.

Keyboard Translation Table

The keyboard translation table is an array that translates the character codes that come from the terminal into the character codes that make up key sequences.

Kill Ring

The kill ring is where all text you have killed (see Glossary---Killing) recently is saved. You can reinsert any of the killed text still in the ring; this is called yanking (q.v.). See Yanking.

Killing

Killing means erasing text and saving it on the kill ring so it can be yanked (q.v.) later. Some other systems call this “cutting”. Most Emacs commands that erase text perform killing, as opposed to deletion (q.v.). See Killing and Moving Text.

Killing a Job

Killing a job (such as, an invocation of Emacs) means making it cease to exist. Any data within it, if not saved in a file, is lost. See Exiting Emacs.

Language Environment

Your choice of language environment specifies defaults for the input method (q.v.) and coding system (q.v.). See Language Environments. These defaults are relevant if you edit non-ASCII text (see International Character Set Support).

Line Wrapping

See Glossary---Filling.

Lisp

Lisp is a programming language. Most of Emacs is written in a dialect of Lisp, called Emacs Lisp, which is extended with special features that make it especially suitable for text editing tasks.

List

A list is, approximately, a text string beginning with an open parenthesis and ending with the matching close parenthesis. In C mode and other non-Lisp modes, groupings surrounded by other kinds of matched delimiters appropriate to the language, such as braces, are also considered lists. Emacs has special commands for many operations on lists. See Moving in the Parenthesis Structure.

Local

Local means “in effect only in a particular context”; the relevant kind of context is a particular function execution, a particular buffer, or a particular major mode. It is the opposite of “global” (q.v.). Specific uses of “local” in Emacs terminology appear below.

Local Abbrev

A local abbrev definition is effective only if a particular major mode is selected. In that major mode, it overrides any global definition for the same abbrev. See Abbrevs.

Local Keymap

A local keymap is used in a particular major mode; the key bindings (q.v.) in the current local keymap override global bindings of the same key sequences. See Keymaps.

Local Variable

A local value of a variable (q.v.) applies to only one buffer. See Local Variables.

M-

M- in the name of a character is an abbreviation for Meta, one of the modifier keys that can accompany any character. See M-.

M-C-

M-C- in the name of a character is an abbreviation for Control-Meta; it means the same thing as C-M- (q.v.).

M-x

M-x is the key sequence that is used to call an Emacs command by name. This is how you run commands that are not bound to key sequences. See Running Commands by Name.

Mail

Mail means messages sent from one user to another through the computer system, to be read at the recipient’s convenience. Emacs has commands for composing and sending mail, and for reading and editing the mail you have received. See Sending Mail. See Reading Mail with Rmail, for one way to read mail with Emacs.

Mail Composition Method

A mail composition method is a program runnable within Emacs for editing and sending a mail message. Emacs lets you select from several alternative mail composition methods. See Mail-Composition Methods.

Major Mode

The Emacs major modes are a mutually exclusive set of options, each of which configures Emacs for editing a certain sort of text. Ideally, each programming language has its own major mode. See Major Modes.

Margin

The space between the usable part of a window (including the fringe) and the window edge.

Mark

The mark points to a position in the text. It specifies one end of the region (q.v.), point being the other end. Many commands operate on all the text from point to the mark. Each buffer has its own mark. See The Mark and the Region.

Mark Ring

The mark ring is used to hold several recent previous locations of the mark, in case you want to move back to them. Each buffer has its own mark ring; in addition, there is a single global mark ring (q.v.). See The Mark Ring.

Menu Bar

The menu bar is a line at the top of an Emacs frame. It contains words you can click on with the mouse to bring up menus, or you can use a keyboard interface to navigate it. See Menu Bars.

Message

See Glossary---Mail.

Meta

Meta is the name of a modifier bit which you can use in a command character. To enter a meta character, you hold down the Meta key while typing the character. We refer to such characters with names that start with Meta- (usually written M- for short). For example, M-< is typed by holding down Meta and at the same time typing < (which itself is done, on most terminals, by holding down SHIFT and typing ,). See Meta.

On some terminals, the Meta key is actually labeled Alt or Edit.

Meta Character

A Meta character is one whose character code includes the Meta bit.

Minibuffer

The minibuffer is the window that appears when necessary inside the echo area (q.v.), used for reading arguments to commands. See The Minibuffer.

Minibuffer History

The minibuffer history records the text you have specified in the past for minibuffer arguments, so you can conveniently use the same text again. See Minibuffer History.

Minor Mode

A minor mode is an optional feature of Emacs, which can be switched on or off independently of all other features. Each minor mode has a command to turn it on or off. Some minor modes are global (q.v.), and some are local (q.v.). See Minor Modes.

Minor Mode Keymap

A minor mode keymap is a keymap that belongs to a minor mode and is active when that mode is enabled. Minor mode keymaps take precedence over the buffer’s local keymap, just as the local keymap takes precedence over the global keymap. See Keymaps.

Mode Line

The mode line is the line at the bottom of each window (q.v.), giving status information on the buffer displayed in that window. See The Mode Line.

Modified Buffer

A buffer (q.v.) is modified if its text has been changed since the last time the buffer was saved (or since it was created, if it has never been saved). See Saving Files.

Moving Text

Moving text means erasing it from one place and inserting it in another. The usual way to move text is by killing (q.v.) it and then yanking (q.v.) it. See Killing and Moving Text.

MULE

Prior to Emacs 23, MULE was the name of a software package which provided a MULtilingual Enhancement to Emacs, by adding support for multiple character sets (q.v.). MULE was later integrated into Emacs, and much of it was replaced when Emacs gained internal Unicode support in version 23.

Some parts of Emacs that deal with character set support still use the MULE name. See International Character Set Support.

Multibyte Character

A multibyte character is a character that takes up several bytes in a buffer. Emacs uses multibyte characters to represent non-ASCII text, since the number of non-ASCII characters is much more than 256. See International Characters.

Named Mark

A named mark is a register (q.v.), in its role of recording a location in text so that you can move point to that location. See Registers.

Narrowing

Narrowing means creating a restriction (q.v.) that limits editing in the current buffer to only a part of the text. Text outside that part is inaccessible for editing (or viewing) until the boundaries are widened again, but it is still there, and saving the file saves it all. See Narrowing.

Newline

Control-J characters in the buffer terminate lines of text and are therefore also called newlines. See Glossary---End Of Line.

nil

nil is a value usually interpreted as a logical “false”. Its opposite is t, interpreted as “true”.

Numeric Argument

A numeric argument is a number, specified before a command, to change the effect of the command. Often the numeric argument serves as a repeat count. See Numeric Arguments.

Overwrite Mode

Overwrite mode is a minor mode. When it is enabled, ordinary text characters replace the existing text after point rather than pushing it to one side. See Minor Modes.

Package

A package is a collection of Lisp code that you download and automatically install from within Emacs. Packages provide a convenient way to add new features. See Emacs Lisp Packages.

Page

A page is a unit of text, delimited by formfeed characters (ASCII control-L, code 014) at the beginning of a line. Some Emacs commands are provided for moving over and operating on pages. See Pages.

Paragraph

Paragraphs are the medium-size unit of human-language text. There are special Emacs commands for moving over and operating on paragraphs. See Paragraphs.

Parsing

We say that certain Emacs commands parse words or expressions in the text being edited. Really, all they know how to do is find the other end of a word or expression.

Point

Point is the place in the buffer at which insertion and deletion occur. Point is considered to be between two characters, not at one character. The terminal’s cursor (q.v.) indicates the location of point. See Point.

Prefix Argument

See Glossary---Numeric Argument.

Prefix Key

A prefix key is a key sequence (q.v.) whose sole function is to introduce a set of longer key sequences. C-x is an example of prefix key; any two-character sequence starting with C-x is therefore a legitimate key sequence. See Keys.

Primary Selection

The primary selection is one particular X selection (q.v.); it is the selection that most X applications use for transferring text to and from other applications.

The Emacs commands that mark or select text set the primary selection, and clicking the mouse inserts text from the primary selection when appropriate. See Shift Selection.

Prompt

A prompt is text used to ask you for input. Displaying a prompt is called prompting. Emacs prompts always appear in the echo area (q.v.). One kind of prompting happens when the minibuffer is used to read an argument (see The Minibuffer); the echoing that happens when you pause in the middle of typing a multi-character key sequence is also a kind of prompting (see The Echo Area).

q.v.

Short for “quod vide” in Latin, which means “which see”.

Query-Replace

Query-replace is an interactive string replacement feature provided by Emacs. See Query Replace.

Quitting

Quitting means canceling a partially typed command or a running command, using C-g (or C-Break on MS-DOS). See Quitting and Aborting.

Quoting

Quoting means depriving a character of its usual special significance. The most common kind of quoting in Emacs is with C-q. What constitutes special significance depends on the context and on convention. For example, an ordinary character as an Emacs command inserts itself; so in this context, a special character is any character that does not normally insert itself (such as DEL, for example), and quoting it makes it insert itself as if it were not special. Not all contexts allow quoting. See Quoting.

Quoting File Names

Quoting a file name turns off the special significance of constructs such as ‘$’, ‘~’ and ‘:’. See Quoted File Names.

Read-Only Buffer

A read-only buffer is one whose text you are not allowed to change. Normally Emacs makes buffers read-only when they contain text which has a special significance to Emacs; for example, Dired buffers. Visiting a file that is write-protected also makes a read-only buffer. See Using Multiple Buffers.

Rectangle

A rectangle consists of the text in a given range of columns on a given range of lines. Normally you specify a rectangle by putting point at one corner and putting the mark at the diagonally opposite corner. See Rectangles.

Recursive Editing Level

A recursive editing level is a state in which part of the execution of a command involves asking you to edit some text. This text may or may not be the same as the text to which the command was applied. The mode line (q.v.) indicates recursive editing levels with square brackets (‘[’ and ‘]’). See Recursive Editing Levels.

Redisplay

Redisplay is the process of correcting the image on the screen to correspond to changes that have been made in the text being edited. See Redisplay.

Regexp

See Glossary---Regular Expression.

Region

The region is the text between point (q.v.) and the mark (q.v.). Many commands operate on the text of the region. See Region.

Register

Registers are named slots in which text, buffer positions, or rectangles can be saved for later use. See Registers. A related Emacs feature is bookmarks (q.v.).

Regular Expression

A regular expression is a pattern that can match various text strings; for example, ‘a[0-9]+’ matches ‘a’ followed by one or more digits. See Syntax of Regular Expressions.

Remote File

A remote file is a file that is stored on a system other than your own. Emacs can access files on other computers provided that they are reachable from your machine over the network, and (obviously) that you have a supported method to gain access to those files. See Remote Files.

Repeat Count

See Glossary---Numeric Argument.

Replacement

See Glossary---Global Substitution.

Restriction

A buffer’s restriction is the amount of text, at the beginning or the end of the buffer, that is temporarily inaccessible. Giving a buffer a nonzero amount of restriction is called narrowing (q.v.); removing a restriction is called widening (q.v.). See Narrowing.

RET

RET is a character that in Emacs runs the command to insert a newline into the text. It is also used to terminate most arguments read in the minibuffer (q.v.). See Return.

Reverting

Reverting means returning to the original state. For example, Emacs lets you revert a buffer by re-reading its file from disk. See Reverting a Buffer.

Saving

Saving a buffer means copying its text into the file that was visited (q.v.) in that buffer. This is the way text in files actually gets changed by your Emacs editing. See Saving Files.

Scroll Bar

A scroll bar is a tall thin hollow box that appears at the side of a window. You can use mouse commands in the scroll bar to scroll the window. The scroll bar feature is supported only under windowing systems. See Scroll Bars.

Scrolling

Scrolling means shifting the text in the Emacs window so as to see a different part of the buffer. See Scrolling.

Searching

Searching means moving point to the next occurrence of a specified string or the next match for a specified regular expression. See Searching and Replacement.

Search Path

A search path is a list of directories, to be used for searching for files for certain purposes. For example, the variable load-path holds a search path for finding Lisp library files. See Libraries of Lisp Code for Emacs.

Secondary Selection

The secondary selection is one particular X selection (q.v.); some X applications can use it for transferring text to and from other applications. Emacs has special mouse commands for transferring text using the secondary selection. See Secondary Selection.

Selected Frame

The selected frame is the one your input currently operates on. See Frames and Graphical Displays.

Selected Window

The selected window is the one your input currently operates on. See Concepts of Emacs Windows.

Selecting a Buffer

Selecting a buffer means making it the current (q.v.) buffer. See Creating and Selecting Buffers.

Selection

Windowing systems allow an application program to specify selections whose values are text. A program can also read the selections that other programs have set up. This is the principal way of transferring text between window applications. Emacs has commands to work with the primary (q.v.) selection and the secondary (q.v.) selection, and also with the clipboard (q.v.).

Self-Documentation

Self-documentation is the feature of Emacs that can tell you what any command does, or give you a list of all commands related to a topic you specify. You ask for self-documentation with the help character, C-h. See Help.

Self-Inserting Character

A character is self-inserting if typing that character inserts that character in the buffer. Ordinary printing and whitespace characters are self-inserting in Emacs, except in certain special major modes.

Sentences

Emacs has commands for moving by or killing by sentences. See Sentences.

Server

Within Emacs, you can start a “server” process, which listens for connections from “clients”. This offers a faster alternative to starting several Emacs instances. See Using Emacs as a Server, and Glossary---Daemon.

Sexp

A sexp (short for “s-expression”) is the basic syntactic unit of Lisp in its textual form: either a list, or Lisp atom. Sexps are also the balanced expressions (q.v.) of the Lisp language; this is why the commands for editing balanced expressions have ‘sexp’ in their name. See Sexps.

Simultaneous Editing

Simultaneous editing means two users modifying the same file at once. Simultaneous editing, if not detected, can cause one user to lose his or her work. Emacs detects all cases of simultaneous editing, and warns one of the users to investigate. See Simultaneous Editing.

SPC

SPC is the space character, which you enter by pressing the space bar.

Speedbar

The speedbar is a special tall frame that provides fast access to Emacs buffers, functions within those buffers, Info nodes, and other interesting parts of text within Emacs. See Speedbar Frames.

Spell Checking

Spell checking means checking correctness of the written form of each one of the words in a text. Emacs can use various external spelling-checker programs to check the spelling of parts of a buffer via a convenient user interface. See Checking and Correcting Spelling.

String

A string is a kind of Lisp data object that contains a sequence of characters. Many Emacs variables are intended to have strings as values. The Lisp syntax for a string consists of the characters in the string with a ‘"’ before and another ‘"’ after. A ‘"’ that is part of the string must be written as ‘\"’ and a ‘\’ that is part of the string must be written as ‘\\’. All other characters, including newline, can be included just by writing them inside the string; however, backslash sequences as in C, such as ‘\n’ for newline or ‘\241’ using an octal character code, are allowed as well.

String Substitution

See Glossary---Global Substitution.

Symbol

A symbol in Emacs Lisp is an object with a name. The object can be a variable (q.v.), a function or command (q.v.), or a face (q.v.). The symbol’s name serves as the printed representation of the symbol. See Symbol Type in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

Syntax Highlighting

See Glossary---Font Lock.

Syntax Table

The syntax table tells Emacs which characters are part of a word, which characters balance each other like parentheses, etc. See Syntax Tables in

The Emacs Lisp Reference Manual

.

Super

Super is the name of a modifier bit that a keyboard input character may have. To make a character Super, type it while holding down the SUPER key. Such characters are given names that start with Super- (usually written s- for short). See Modifier Keys.

Suspending

Suspending Emacs means stopping it temporarily and returning control to its parent process, which is usually a shell. Unlike killing a job (q.v.), you can later resume the suspended Emacs job without losing your buffers, unsaved edits, undo history, etc. See Exiting Emacs.

TAB

TAB is the tab character. In Emacs it is typically used for indentation or completion.

Tab Bar

The tab bar is a row of tabs at the top of an Emacs frame. Clicking on one of these tabs switches named persistent window configurations. See Tab Bars.

Tab Line

The tab line is a line of tabs at the top of an Emacs window. Clicking on one of these tabs switches window buffers. See Window Tab Line.

Tag

A tag is an identifier in a program source. See Find Identifier References.

Tags Table

A tags table is a file that serves as an index to identifiers: definitions of functions, macros, data structures, etc., in one or more other files. See Tags Tables.

Termscript File

A termscript file contains a record of all characters sent by Emacs to the terminal. It is used for tracking down bugs in Emacs redisplay. Emacs does not make a termscript file unless you tell it to. See Reporting Bugs.

Text

“Text” has two meanings (see Commands for Human Languages):

Data consisting of a sequence of characters, as opposed to binary numbers, executable programs, and the like. The basic contents of an Emacs buffer (aside from the text properties, q.v.) are always text in this sense.
Data consisting of written human language (as opposed to programs), or following the stylistic conventions of human language.

Text Terminal

A text terminal, or character terminal, is a display that is limited to displaying text in character units. Such a terminal cannot control individual pixels it displays. Emacs supports a subset of display features on text terminals.

Text Properties

Text properties are annotations recorded for particular characters in the buffer. Images in the buffer are recorded as text properties; they also specify formatting information. See Editing Format Information.

Theme

A theme is a set of customizations (q.v.) that give Emacs a particular appearance or behavior. For example, you might use a theme for your favorite set of faces (q.v.).

Tool Bar

The tool bar is a line (sometimes multiple lines) of icons at the top of an Emacs frame. Clicking on one of these icons executes a command. You can think of this as a graphical relative of the menu bar (q.v.). See Tool Bars.

Tooltips

Tooltips are small windows displaying a help echo (q.v.) text, which explains parts of the display, lists useful options available via mouse clicks, etc. See Tooltips.

Top Level

Top level is the normal state of Emacs, in which you are editing the text of the file you have visited. You are at top level whenever you are not in a recursive editing level (q.v.) or the minibuffer (q.v.), and not in the middle of a command. You can get back to top level by aborting (q.v.) and quitting (q.v.). See Quitting and Aborting.

Transient Mark Mode

The default behavior of the mark (q.v.) and region (q.v.), in which setting the mark activates it and highlights the region, is called Transient Mark mode. It is enabled by default. See Disabling Transient Mark Mode.

Transposition

Transposing two units of text means putting each one into the place formerly occupied by the other. There are Emacs commands to transpose two adjacent characters, words, balanced expressions (q.v.) or lines (see Transposing Text).

Trash Can

See Glossary---Deletion of Files.

Truncation

Truncating text lines in the display means leaving out any text on a line that does not fit within the right margin of the window displaying it. See Truncation, and Glossary---Continuation Line.

TTY

See Glossary---Text Terminal.

Undoing

Undoing means making your previous editing go in reverse, bringing back the text that existed earlier in the editing session. See Undo.

Unix

Unix is a class of multi-user computer operating systems with a long history. There are several implementations today. The GNU project (q.v.) aims to develop a complete Unix-like operating system that is free software (q.v.).

User Option

A user option is a face (q.v.) or a variable (q.v.) that exists so that you can customize Emacs by setting it to a new value. See Easy Customization Interface.

Variable

A variable is an object in Lisp that can store an arbitrary value. Emacs uses some variables for internal purposes, and has others (known as “user options”; q.v.) just so that you can set their values to control the behavior of Emacs. The variables used in Emacs that you are likely to be interested in are listed in the Variables Index in this manual (see Variable Index). See Variables, for information on variables.

Version Control

Version control systems keep track of multiple versions of a source file. They provide a more powerful alternative to keeping backup files (q.v.). See Version Control.

Visiting

Visiting a file means loading its contents into a buffer (q.v.) where they can be edited. See Visiting Files.

Whitespace

Whitespace is any run of consecutive formatting characters (space, tab, newline, backspace, etc.).

Widening

Widening is removing any restriction (q.v.) on the current buffer; it is the opposite of narrowing (q.v.). See Narrowing.

Window

Emacs divides a frame (q.v.) into one or more windows, each of which can display the contents of one buffer (q.v.) at any time. See The Organization of the Screen, for basic information on how Emacs uses the screen. See Multiple Windows, for commands to control the use of windows. Some other editors use the term “window” for what we call a “frame” in Emacs.

Window System

A window system is software that operates on a graphical display (q.v.), to subdivide the screen so that multiple applications can have their own windows at the same time. All modern operating systems include a window system.

Word Abbrev

See Glossary---Abbrev.

Word Search

Word search is searching for a sequence of words, considering the punctuation between them as insignificant. See Word Search.

Yanking

Yanking means reinserting text previously killed (q.v.). It can be used to undo a mistaken kill, or for copying or moving text. Some other systems call this “pasting”. See Yanking.